<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Briefe introductions, both naturall, pleasaunte, and also delectable vnto the art of chiromancy, or manuel diuination, and physiognomy with circumstances vpon the faces of the signes. Also certain canons or rules vpon diseases and sickenesse. Whereunto is also annexed aswel the artificiall, as naturall astrologye, with the nature of the planets. Written in the Latin tonge, by Ihon Indagine prieste. And now latelye translated into Englishe, by Fabian Withers.</title>
            <title>Chiromantia. English</title>
            <author>Indagine, Johannes ab, d. 1537.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1558</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 353 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 183 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107417</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843118</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843118</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7828</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03968)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7828)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 250:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Briefe introductions, both naturall, pleasaunte, and also delectable vnto the art of chiromancy, or manuel diuination, and physiognomy with circumstances vpon the faces of the signes. Also certain canons or rules vpon diseases and sickenesse. Whereunto is also annexed aswel the artificiall, as naturall astrologye, with the nature of the planets. Written in the Latin tonge, by Ihon Indagine prieste. And now latelye translated into Englishe, by Fabian Withers.</title>
                  <title>Chiromantia. English</title>
                  <author>Indagine, Johannes ab, d. 1537.</author>
                  <author>Withers, Fabian.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[256] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Apud Iohannis Day [for Richarde Iugge],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1558.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Chiromantia.</note>
                  <note>Publisher's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [cross]⁴ A-P Q⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Palmistry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Physiognomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7828:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7828:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>BRIEFE introductions,</hi> bothe naturall, pleaſaunte, and alſo delectable vnto the Art of <hi>Chiromancy,</hi> or <hi>Manuel diuination,</hi> and <hi>Phiſiognomy:</hi> with circumſtances vpon the faces of the ſignes. Alſo certain canons or rules vpon diſeaſes and ſickeneſſe. Whereunto is alſo annexed aſwel the artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, as naturall Aſtrologye, with the nature of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets. Written in the Latin tonge, by <hi>Ihon Indagine</hi> Prieſte. And now latelye tranſlated into Engliſhe, by Fabian Withers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDINI. Apud Iohannis Day. 1558.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7828:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7828:2"/>
            <head>To the gentle Reader.</head>
            <p>IT was the vſe amongſte the aunciente Philoſophers (moſt gentle Reader) that they neuer admitted or receiued anye ſcholer, vnto whome they did not indict and appoint a certain time to heare &amp; kepe ſilence: willing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in no wiſe for to ſpeke, vntil that by hearinge they had learned to ſpeake wiſeli and diſcretely. Whoſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple being preſent in my mind, and alſo the raſh &amp; temerarious iudgements of many conuerſant before my eyes: I thoughte it good to admoniſh you, that folowing the example aforſaid, to beſtow ſome labour &amp; time in peruſinge and readinge this briefe worke of Chiromancy, or manuel diuina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, before you entre into iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ani effect or certainty of the ſame. The whiche thing if thou diligently &amp; attentiſlye do: I dout not, but that beſide the great pleaſure and delectation, thou ſhalt find therin that thou ſhalt in likewiſe repe &amp; gather no leſſe good frute &amp; profit therof. For herby thou ſhalt perceiue &amp; ſe the ſecrete works of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, how aptly &amp; neceſſarily ſhe hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound &amp; knit eche member with other: ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand (as vnto a table) certain ſignes &amp; tokens whereby to diſcerne and know the inward motions and affectyons
<pb facs="tcp:7828:3"/>of the minde and hearte, with the inwarde ſtate of the whole bodye: as alſo oure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination &amp; aptnes to al our external actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; doings. For what more profitable thing may be ſuppoſed or thought, then when a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in him ſelf, &amp; by him ſelf, maiforſee and know his proper &amp; fatal accidentes: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to embrace and folowe that whiche is good, &amp; to auoid and eſcliue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euils which are iminent vnto him, for the better vnder ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding and knowledge therof. And for as much as the Chiroma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci vnto ſome perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may ſeme obſcure &amp; darke: we haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed hereunto an Epiloge or brief collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the art of Phiſiognomy and circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances vpon the faces of the ſignes, wyth certain canons or rules, aſwel for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as alſo for the curing and helping of diſeaſes, very neceſſary &amp; profitable. Then orderly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming vnto Aſtrology, we haue deſcribed vnto you aſwel by the artificiall Horoſcope, as alſo by the naturall entring of the Sunne into any of the .xii. celeſtiall ſignes: the hole effect and power that anye of the Planets or erraticall ſtarres maye by any meanes worke in vs, Wherby ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing recourſe firſt vnto the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and noting ſuche ſignes and tokens as therin ſhall appere, then becholdinge the
<pb facs="tcp:7828:3"/>proportion and liniaments of the hole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and according to the preſcript rules to way and conſidre the equality &amp; agreable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe betwene them, with like reſpecte had vnto the natiuity, iudging either by thar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Horoſcope, or by the natural courſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sun: y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt not only ſee &amp; perceiue a great neceſſity &amp; affinity betwene our ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrial &amp; the celeſtial bodies, but alſo forſe &amp; know a. M. accidentes either to good or euil prouided vnto vs, &amp; hanging ouer our head. But leaſt that any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld thynke that hereby we attribute ſo much vnto na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as though it wer ineuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; therby vſe it as a refuge or ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctuary, for al their euil actions and doinges. Vnto ſuch we wil obiect thanſwer of Criſippus writing in this maner. Although (ſaith he) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature hath prouided al thing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by her prouidence al things are moued &amp; ſtyrred vp by a certain neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary reaſon and motion: yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; mindes are no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſubiect or in daunger therof, then theyr propriety and quality is concordante and agreable vnto the ſame. For if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by nature our wittes be fyrſt made holſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e and good, and after endued with reaſon and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: either they do vtterly put of and
<pb facs="tcp:7828:4"/>auoid al euil influences and accidentes or els receiue and beare them the more eaſily without hurt or domage. If contrariwiſe our diſpoſitions of them ſelues be rude &amp; groſe, not endued with any kind of letters or good learning to aſſiſte and helpe them withal: with euery light conflict or aſſault of our natural inclination, we runne hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into al kinde of errours &amp; vice. Euen folowinge the enſample of the Cilindre ſtone, which by nature being apt to roll &amp; tomble, and being caſt or throwen downe in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o holow or ſteye places: doth run with out ceaſing, not ſo much becauſe it is caſte or throwen, as for his owne nature &amp; apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes therunto, and not hauing in it ſelf any thing to withſtand the ſame. The aucthor him ſelf in like maner forſeing the cauilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of certaine euill diſpoſed perſones which wold make al thinges ſubiect vnto the influences of the heauenly bodies: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he entreth to ſpeak of the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of natiuities, writeth in this ſort. We ought (ſaith he) firſt to know and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that the ſtars do not prouoke or force vs to ani thing, but only maketh vs apt and prone: and being ſo diſpoſed, doth as it were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure &amp; draw vs forward to our naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In the which if we folow y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rule
<pb facs="tcp:7828:4"/>of reaſon, taking it to be our only guide &amp; gouernour: thei loſe al their force, power, &amp; effect, which they by ani means may haue in, &amp; vpon vs. Contrariwiſe, if we geue our ſelues ouer to folow our own ſenſuality &amp; natural diſpoſition, they woorke euen the ſame effect in vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei do in brute beaſts. And this ſhalbe ſufficiente at this time to anſwer the vain obiection of naturall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, wherby the frute of this woorke might by anye meane ſeme to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted into any vice or error, the which in dede of it ſelf, is veri neceſſary &amp; profitable. What ſhould I nede to ſtand aboute with longe circumſtances, to deſcribe the perticuler co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities of theſe briefe workes anexed togethers: when that the labor is ſo ſmal, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyth once or twiſe dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; attentife re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the hole effect is known &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Notwithſtanding, I wold wiſhe &amp; deſire y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al men which ſhal read or take any frute of this ſmal treatiſe: to uſe ſuch moderation in peruſyng of the ſame, that they do not by and by take in hand to geue iudgment, eyther of theyr owne, or of other mens e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates or natiuityes, without diligent cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection and taking hede. Wayinge &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering how many wayes a man maye be deceyued, as by the prouidence &amp; diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:7828:5"/>of the man in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou geueſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Alſo the diſpenſation of God, and oure fallible and vncertaine ſpeculation.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, let al men in ſeking hereby to forſee their own fortune, take hede that bi the promiſſe of good, thei be not ſo elate or high minded, geuing them ſelues ouer to oſiuetye or idleneſſe, truſtinge altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the naturall influences, neither yet by anye ſignes or tokens of aduerſitye to be derecte or caſte downe: but to take and waye all thinge with ſuche equalitie and moderation, directinge their ſtate of life and liuinge to all perfectneſſe and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that they maye be ready to embrace and followe all that whiche is good and profitable, and alſo not only to eſchue and auoide: but to withſtande and ſet at noughte all euill and aduerſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, when ſo euer it maye happen or chaunce vnto them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:7828:5"/>
            <head>The boke of Palmeſtry.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <hi>The firſt Chapiter of</hi> the diſtinction of the hand.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE auncient Grekes, who (as it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> long and old vſe of the word) did vſe this ſorte and kinde of Diuinatyon, whiche is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by the beholdynge of manne his hande, called it by this propre name of <hi>Chyromancia.</hi> Wherfore I intendynge to write the rules &amp; obſeruations therof, do thinke it neceſſarye and mete firſt of al to diſcribe the hand of man, and point out &amp; ſet forthe his partes, whereby ſuch rules and preceptes as ſhall be geuen v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this manuell diuination, maye the more eaſily be vnderſtand and knowen. The hand therfore being extent or ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:7828:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>abroade, the playne within is called the palme, in the middeſt whereof there is a certaine ſpace called the concaue or holowneſſe, oute of the whiche the fiue fingers haue their originall and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Amongſt the which, the firſt being the ſtrongeſt and mooſte groſſe, is called the Thombe: the next is called the index or forfinger, becauſe in ſhewing or poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to any thing, we do commonly vſe that finger. The next that foloweth and is in the middeſt of the fiue, is by the ſame name called the middle finger: next after this, is the ringe finger: ſo called, becauſe it is commonly to weare a ring of golde vpon it, and ſpeciallye that on the lefthand, for becauſe as learned men hold opinion, there dothe paſſe a certain ſmall ſinnowe from that finger to the heart of man: wherefore it ſemed good in times paſte to the antiquitie, to wear a ringe as a crowne vppon that finger, or els as ſome do ſuppoſe, that goulds by nature doth comforte the heart. The laſte finger and leaſte of all, is called
<pb facs="tcp:7828:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>the eare finger, becauſe it is commonly vſed to make cleane the eares. And thus farre concernynge the fingers. More o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, the hand beyng cloſed or ſhut wyth the fingers turned in, we call the fiſte, the nether parte wherof (amongeſt ſuch as vſe this Arte,) is commonlye called the percuſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſtroke of the hand. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the place where the hand is drawen and gathered in, &amp; ioyned to the arme, is alſo called the wreſte. Furthermore, euerye finger hath his proper riſing or ſwelling of the fleſhe, whiche doth riſe at the rote or nether parte of the ſaide fingers, and of ſome is called hylles, and are attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the names of the Planets. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the whiche is reckened the riſyng or hyll in the nether parte of the fiſt, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the percuſſion of the hande, ſo that in the hande are limitted and appoynted ſeuerall places vnto euerye of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nettes, whereby iudgemente maye be gathered. For the riſynge or hyll of the thombe is aſſigned vnto <hi>Venus,</hi> and marked with this carecter ♀, the hyll
<pb facs="tcp:7828:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the fore finger to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and is thus noted ♃, the middle finger is attribute to <hi>Saturne,</hi> with this note ♄, the ringe finger to the <hi>Sunne,</hi> with this character ☉, the hill of the little or eare finger is vnder <hi>Mercury,</hi> with this marke ☿, the riſyng or hill which is in the percuſſion, the <hi>Mone</hi> doth poſſeſſe, and is thus figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>. Now what place <hi>Mars</hi> ſhal haue we will ſhew you hereafter, but firſt we will make diſcription of the inciſions &amp; diuiſions of the hand, which we call the lines. Amongeſt the which there be two chiefe and principall, which be theſe: the wreſt which diuideth the hand from the arme, and is almoſt ioyned to the line of life, or of the hart, the whiche beginueth vnder the hill of the forefinger, as it wer betwene the forefinger and the thombe, and dothe deuide the hande ſtretchinge downeward towarde the wreſt. In the ſame ſide of the hande at the hyll of the forefinger, beginneth a line whiche paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ouerthwart the hande to the hyll of the <hi>Moone,</hi> and is called the middle <hi>cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean</hi> naturall. And theſe two lines thus
<pb facs="tcp:7828:7"/>beginning and paſſyng ſundry wayes, make the forme and ſhape of a triangle. To the whiche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, if the line of the Liuer or ſtomacke, whiche beginneth ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte the wreſte, and paſſeth vnder the hil of the thombe, to the hil of the <hi>Mone,</hi> by the end of the meane natural line, do apere, as in ſome it doth not, it finiſheth the triangle. And the ſpace conteyned within theſe lines, is attribute and geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto <hi>Mars,</hi> and is called the triangle of <hi>Mars,</hi> noted wyth this figure ♂.</p>
               <p>There is alſo an other line called the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble line, beginninge vnder the eare fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, at the ende of the hyll of the <hi>Mone,</hi> and runneth to the forefinger, and is ſo called, becauſe the ſpace betwene it and the middle or meane natural doth argue or ſhewe the faſhion of a table, and that ſpace is alwayes called the table or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drangle of the hande, and the line is alſo called the lyne of fortune. And theſe be almoſt the chiefe diuiſions or lines of the hand, to the which all other leſſe &amp; ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler inciſions and lines are referred. But nowe as neare as we can wee wyll diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe
<pb facs="tcp:7828:8"/>them all, and as farre as partey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to this Arte, ſhew their nature and ſignification. And firſt I thinke mete to ſpeake of thoſe lines, whiche take their denomination or name of the three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall membres of mans bodie, that is of the hart, the brain, and the liuer. For as in thoſe parts, whatſoeuer is in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered &amp; chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged: ſo bi thoſe thre inciſions and lines, a man may foreſee &amp; pronoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate what ſoeuer ſhall happen, touching health, or aduerſitie, or other thinges na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall. The which if any man thinke to be vaine and triflying: let him call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce the auncient Philoſophers of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> ſecte, who chieflye by the proporcion and liniaments of mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, did declare and pronoſticate the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſtate, and ende of man his life. For what is ſaide of <hi>Socrates,</hi> when that a certain man profeſſying the Arte of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiognomye, or ſpeculation: beholdynge <hi>Socrates,</hi> iudged hym by his outwarde habyte to be a verye euyll manne, of vncleane lyfe, libidinous, and geuen to
<pb facs="tcp:7828:8"/>all euil, was therefore wonderfullye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked of his ſcholers, as thoughe he had ſhamefullye flaundered hym. <hi>Socrates</hi> aunſwered, that in dede naturallye he felte ſuche mocions and inclinations, ſo that if he hadde not corrected the vyces, his nature by the rules of reaſon, he had bene ſuche a one as he hadde pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced hym to bee: meanynge thereby all thoſe vices, whiche nature and deſtenye hath planted in vs, maye eaſilye by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and cuſtome be amended, if we wyll ſtriue agaynſte deſtinye. And the prince of the Paripetecians <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſaide, the hande of manne to be made of Nature, the principall organe and inſtrument in mannes bodye. For ſithens it is his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to miniſter and ſerue all other partes of the bodye, and that in humaine gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the vertues, powers, and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, of all membres do come together. It is verye conſequente and agreable, ſome certaine ſignes and tokens of the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and complexion of man, to be knowen and perceiued by the hande.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:9"/>
               <p>Suche is the proporcion of membres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſelues, that they do partake one wyth another in all thynges. And further, that this arte of <hi>Chyromancie</hi> was vſed in the time of <hi>Plinie,</hi> he him ſelfe dothe affirme. Wherefore I take it to be my dutie to admonyſhe you what you ought to attribute to this arte, and what is els to be ioyned wyth it, leſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man ſhould thinke to include or ſhut vp the knowledge of ſo highe and great thinges into ſo ſtraight and narow cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Wherfore what I thinke herein I thinke good to ſhewe. As often as I muſt anſwere to any that enquireth, by and by as is accuſtomed, I loke vpon the hand, and therwithal beholde the whole bodye with the lineamentes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porcion of the ſame, whiche is called his <hi>Phyſiognomie,</hi> (whereof in the boke fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing I will intreate,) then I caſt my minde to the hour of Natiuitie, moneth, daye, or yere: the whiche knowen, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre ſtrait to the rules of natural Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logye hereafter by mee written, then plainely iudgyng none of theſe by them
<pb facs="tcp:7828:9"/>ſelues ſufficient. And thinking it better to iudge them foles in geuyng light cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, then I to be counted raſhe and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe haſtye in geuyng ſentence. So that when I haue gathered all theſe thinges together, and taken holde of that which I thinke meete for my vſe, I vtter my iudgment, eſtemyng the point of a mad manne by lokyng onely in the hande, to geue iudgemente of the life and all the ſtates of mans bodye. And nowe I returne to the rules of <hi>Chyromancie.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A The table line, or line of fortune.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>B The line of life, or of the heart.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>C The vvreſte of a vvoman.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>D The pomell of the hande.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>E The middle naturall line.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>F The line of the liuer or ſtomacke.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A The table line.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>B The pomell of the hande.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>C The vvreſte of a man.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>D The line of the liuer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>E The table or quadrangle.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>G The hyll of the thombe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>H The line of life, or of the heart</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>I The triangle.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>K The middle naturall line.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                  <head>The names of the fingers after the Planets.</head>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A The imperfect table line.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>B The ſiſter to the naturall line.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>C The line of the liuer or ſtomacke.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>D The ſiſter of the line of life.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>E The line of life.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſeconde Chapiter of</hi> the line of life, or of the heart.</head>
               <p>THe line of life, called alſo the line of the heart, beginneth as is ſaide before at the hyll of the forefinger, paſſing by the midſt of the palme, goeth to the wreſt. The whiche if it be long, ſtraite, liuely coloured, bright and cleare, it betokeneth longe life, endoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with fewe diſeaſes or ſickeneſſe. <hi>Plinie</hi> affirmyng the ſame, ſayth: that it is token of longe life to haue vpryght ſhoulders, &amp; two longe inciſions or lines in one hand, the which are to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande of the line of lyfe, and the meane natural line. If that the natural powers be weake, and that the line doe appeare ſhort and of diuers colours, runnyng in &amp; out, thinne or ſlender, and cut or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſunder, with manye ouerthwart riuels or ſmall creſtes, it dooeth declare ſhortneſſe of life, muche ſickeneſſe, ſmall ſtrength, and that he in whom this is ſo noted, ſhall ſeldome or neuer bringe any
<pb facs="tcp:7828:12"/>thing to a good end. So likewiſe, the line groſe, long, and vndeuided, doth ſhew al the contraries to the ſame. Wherfore, if any man do requyre or aſke a reaſon of this thing, we anſwer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the blud, which doth noriſh the hart, and is alſo thought to be the ſeat &amp; reſting place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde, to be the cauſe efficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this thing. For it is moſt certain, that as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blud is pure, or vnpure: ſo the line ſhal be coloured, either cleare or dark: ſo as long as bloud dothe abounde, it ſheweth reddye and brighte: and contrariwiſe, pale, &amp; ſwart, when the bloude doth fail or war ſcarſe. Wherby aſwel the natural heate dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and the weake bodye, as alſo the ſtrong &amp; luſty body is ſhewed &amp; declared. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if this line be narow, ſubtile, &amp; wel colored, &amp; ſtretch forth toward the mean natural: it ſignifieth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, of ſubtile vnderſtandinge, and of an high and princely minde and ſtomacke. And if it be broade, il coloured, and pale: it ſignifieth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. This is always to be noted in all principal lines, that if they be ſtraite, not deuided, neither
<pb facs="tcp:7828:12"/>cutte, and well coloured, it doth declare a good complexion: if they be contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe diſpoſed or ſet, if ſheweth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trari: Alſo if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> line of life be groſe, depe, and diuerſly coloured: that is to ſay: one place redde, another pale or ſwarte, is a ſigne of malice, craft, enuy, and the man to be a great talker, and boaſter, and one that ſtandeth much in his own conceit. If the line be groſſe and very red, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth a crafty, a filthy, and an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant man, but if it be pale, mixed wyth a certain redneſſe: it ſignifieth an angry man, almoſte mad with anger. And it be very red, mixed with palenes or ſwarth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe like leade: it ſheweth an vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, vnſhamfaſt, wauering, traitorous, and angry man, and delitinge to ſtir vp miſchief, and ſow diſcord. But if it be red in the part next the wreaſte: it ſignifieth cruelty, and oftentimes it chaunceth to be forked in the vpper corner, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth an vnſtable man, a runner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute countryes, and marueſlous in all his doinges, the whiche if it be croked &amp; writhen toward the mean natural line:
<pb facs="tcp:7828:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>if ſignifieth a craftye, diſceitfull, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and a manne of a peruerſe and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward minde: and if you happen to finde in the hande of a woman, a croſſe, with three ſmall lines at the vpper corner of the line of life: it ſignifieth an vnſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſte, and vnhoneſt woman, but if that croſſe be founde aboute the right corner in the line it ſelfe, and be depe in: it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth an vngodlye and miſcheuous woman, whiche ſhall ſuffer greate pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhemente for her miſchiefe. For ſuche a croſſe in that line, dothe alwaies beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken euel, bothe in man and woman. If that there be founde two lines in thend of the riſing of the thumbe, nere the line of life, as they wer liyng on the one ſide: by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> token I iudge the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to die ſhortly. And if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> line of life haue brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out toward the meane natural, in forme as you ſee in the margente: it is a ſine of riches, honor, and perfection. But if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches run dounward toward the wreſt in this maner, it ſignifieth po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty &amp; domage by houſhold ſeruantes, through their vntruthe, and if the ſaide
<pb facs="tcp:7828:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>braunches do paſſe ſtrait thorow the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle to the meane natural: it ſignifieth a man, after diuerſe and ſondrye daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges of fortune, to come to proſperity and riches. Moreouer, manye ſmal lines deuiding the left line, betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth much ſickenes: furder, if there be in the line of life certain points or graines ſcattering: it declareth a man vnſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, a fornicator, and in ieoperdy of hys life for murder in a tumult, whereof he was auctor him ſelf, and ſhalbe diuerſe times ſore wounded.</p>
               <p>When in the beginninge of the lyne of lyfe be thre ſmal croked lines, deuidinge it in this maner: it is a token of a leproſy to come, for it doth declare the il diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the liuer, whereupon this whych is already ſaid maye be gathered, that if the line of life be long, and depe, wel co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured, hauinge a good proportion with the meane naturall line, and the line of the liuer or ſtomacke, and that they two be of due quantity and length, and well coloured: it is a good ſigne of long life, good nature, wit, diſpoſition, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion.
<pb facs="tcp:7828:14"/>And oftentimes there be found in the line of life one ☉ or ☉ ☉ of theſe notes, which do ſignify the loſſe either of one, or bothe eyes, the whiche although they be ſeldome found, yet in my ſelfe I haue had the experience, for in the ſame place of my hand is the ſame marke, the which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſaw, I cald to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance in what daunger I was of one of my eyes, for ſitting by the fire in winter, I fell therein, and tumblinge in the flame with my left eye, I was vehemently tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mented. Albeit I find that not only that did prognoſticate that euel vnto me, but alſo the oppoſition of <hi>Mars,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Mone</hi> in my natiuity. For I finde at the tyme of my birth, <hi>Mars</hi> to be in the eleuenthe houſe in a manlye ſigne, and the <hi>Mone</hi> likewiſe in the fyfthe houſe, whiche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is obſerued of the Aſtronomers to ſignifye ſome ſuche thynge. And in ſo muche as I haue found this true it doth ſo muche the more verify that whyche I ſayd afore, that theſe artes were ioyned together, as it were by a certaine aly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, or affinitie, and that thone wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:7828:14"/>thother could very litle preuail. For it is moſt certaine, the inferior bodyes to be gouerned by them aboue, and as all power and ſtrength haue their influence from thoſe heauenly bodies: ſo like wiſe al lack and default to come by them, it is moſt ſure. Wherfore we may wel conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that nature was a careful workman about the creation of mans body, which hath geuen knowledge to man diuerſiy and manifoldly, to iudge by theſe three moſt noble and principal partes.</p>
               <p>In the other partes, ſhe hathe not ſo done. For ſhe hath ſet in the hand of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> certain ſignes and tokens of the heart, braine, and liuer, becauſe that in them the life of man doth chiefly conſiſt. But ſhe hathe not likewiſe done of the eyes, eares, mouthe, handes, and fete, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe partes and members of the body, ſeme rather to be made for a come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe or beautye to the bodye, then for anye neceſſitye. Therefore all handes haue the thre lynes aforeſayde, but the other inciſions or lynes manye do wante or lacke. Huſbandmen beinge
<pb facs="tcp:7828:15"/>alſo excluded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence for their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al labour. Wherefore, ſithens theſe two ſciences nede ſuch a mutual help, one of the other: I wil declare vnto you oute of aſtrologye, the nature of the <hi>Erratical</hi> ſignes, whiche the Crekes cal Planets. <hi>Saturnus</hi> maketh ſad, circumſpect, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, ſlow, and litle ſpeakers, and ſelf lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. <hi>Iupiter</hi> cauſeth pleaſaunt, liberal, quiet, ſobre. and eloquent perſons, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, <hi>Mars</hi> cauſeth cruel, fiers, and liers. The <hi>Sonne</hi> maketh godly, wittye, happy, or fortunate, and coragious me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Venus</hi> cauſeth incontinent, libidinouſe, comely &amp; faire. <hi>Mercury</hi> cauſeth ſubtile, craftye, learned in ſciences, and nimble men. The <hi>Mone</hi> maketh quicke witted, and comly, but vnſtable and ſlow. Now I haue ſpoken of the diuerſitie of diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and wits: I wil alſo ſhewe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of voice, and ſpeche, wherby the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers effectes and workinge of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nettes amongeſt them ſelfes, maye the better be vnderſtand and knowen. <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus</hi> doth cauſe a ſlow and ſcriking voice or ſpeche, <hi>Mars</hi> a craſhing voice, like the
<pb facs="tcp:7828:15"/>breaking of metals. <hi>Iupiter,</hi> a ſhril, ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and gentle voice. <hi>Venus</hi> maketh a weake, ſoft, pleaſant, &amp; effeminate voice. And ſo likewiſe doth the <hi>Sunne,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> The ſignes alſo haue their proper voices, for <hi>Virgo, Gemini, Libra, Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> do make good voices or ſoundes. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Taurus, Leo, Capricorne,</hi> and the laſt part of <hi>Sagittary,</hi> cauſe meane voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. <hi>Cancer, Scorpio</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> are ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther altogither dombe, &amp; without ſound: or els miniſter ſom great impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpeche, Ther be alſo certain ſignes, cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led fertile, becauſe they do increaſe with <hi>Cancer, Scorpio</hi> or <hi>Piſces.</hi> And others be called barraine. as <hi>Gemini, Leo, Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne.</hi> So that what ſo euer a man can do, may be applied to the ſignes, as fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of the ſame. The which thing in that it canne not be denied, ſo muche the more are they to be counted ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derers, which eſteme &amp; report Aſtrologye not as deuine, but as a vaine friuolous arte, or knowledge, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their places we wil ſet forth with their colours. But nowe to returne to our purpoſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:16"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:16"/>
               <p>If you find a croſſe in this fort about the vpper corner, procedinge oute of the line of life, and on the nether ſide, three ſmal lines, and on thupper ſide two, as you may ſe by this figure, it ſignifieth a libidinouſe and an vnſhamfaſt woman. But if the thre lines be found in the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ende of the line of lyfe towarde the wreſt, it betokeneth that the woman ſhall ſuffer greuous puniſhment for ſome miſchief, or cuel doinge.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:17"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:17"/>
               <p>When that certain ſmal lines do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide or touche the line of life in the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ende, in forme preſcribed: it dothe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the infirmitie and ſicknes of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. But if on thother parte of the meane natural line, there be inciſions in this manner, liynge as it were direcily from the nether parte of the line, and riſinge vpwarde: it betokeneth cuel, as paine in the heade, whiche commeth of exhalati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſtomacke, or ſome ſuche other diſeaſe. And thoſe thre lines on thend of that line, do betoken euel, as ſhal appere hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <hi>The third Chapter, of</hi> the meane naturall line.</head>
               <p>THe line whiche beginneth at the roote of the line of life, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth through<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Palme of the hande, towarde the hyll of the <hi>Moone,</hi> or pommel of the hande: is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perli called the meane natural line. The whiche if it be ſtraite, and vndeuided
<pb facs="tcp:7828:18"/>with ani ſmal ouerthwart lines, it ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth good health, a ſound brayn, a quicke &amp; liuely wit, and alſo a good memorye. If it be long, ſtretched oute to the hill of the <hi>mone,</hi> it doth declare a ſtout ſtomack and long life, which if it be ſhorte, that it paſſe not the holownes of the hand: it be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tokeneth a feareful, couetous, vnwiſe, &amp; vnfaithful man, and if the ſaide line do not ſtretch out to the hill of the <hi>Moone,</hi> but end euer againſt the ſpace, which is betwene the middle finger, and the ring finger: it betokeneth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of il maners, and that ſhal not liue long. Then if the ſame line run out beyond the hill of the <hi>Mone,</hi> and turne in again in forme of a halfe compaſſe: the farther it ſtretcheth, the longer life it betokeneth, but in age pouerty. But if the ſame line at the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per end do riſe toward the fingers, it ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifieth an vnſhamefaſte and malicious man, the which if it riſe verye muche to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the fingers, it doth declare him to be verye folyſhe, and vnwiſe. Contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if it tourne down warde almoſte to the palme of the hand, it is a token of a
<pb facs="tcp:7828:18"/>couetous and vncleane man. On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part, if it turne vpwarde, touch the table line: it ſignifieth ſome great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſſe, and aduerſe or euell fortune: and if the ſame line be writhen, vnequal, and of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers coulours: it is a token of an il diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed mind, and oftentimes of theft. The line being ſtraite, equal, and bright co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured: betokeneth a good conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and iuſtice. But when the meane naturall line is brode and groſſe, with a certaine redneſſe intermedled: it ſignifieth a rude diſpoſicion and lacke of wit. And if it be nether to ſtraight, nor to large, and wel coloured: it betokeneth a mery, chereful, and a fortunate man, but if it be ſubtile, and ſlender, ſwarte, or pale: it declareth weaknes of the braine, and vapores ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the ſtomacke into the heade. And if the line appere groſſe, &amp; very depe &amp; hath a certaine ſmal line nere to it, red coloured: it ſheweth an angry and fury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man. Again if it haue certain knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſpaces in this maner <hi>o,</hi> ſo many knots as there be, it doth declare ſo many mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ether al ready co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, or hereafter
<pb facs="tcp:7828:19"/>to be done. The which knottes if they be not fully cloſed or ſhutte, they are a toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a great quareller, whiche ſhal beate &amp; wounde, but not kill outright. If there be in the ſame line certain groſſe pricks, or pointes: it ſheweth an vnmanerly, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and vnpleaſant manne, the whiche pointes if they be verye redde: it betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a very cruel and fierce man. If the ſame line be croked, makyng halfe a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, with a certaine obſcure or darke co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loure: it ſignifieth daunger by foure fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted beaſt, or els to be ſlain of wild beaſt. And oftentimes, nye the ſame line there be two ſmal lines ioyned together (as in the figure of the hande folowynge you ſhal ſee) which ſignifie wounds, but not with weapon. More ouer, if there be a croſſe in the ſame line, ouer againſte the middle finger: it betokeneth that the man ſhal dye within a yere. If any man haue this line forked toward the wreſt, with ſmal diuiſions: he ſemeth to ſet al his minde on miſchiefe, and neither to feare God nor man.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:19"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                  <p>Linae media naturalis</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:20"/>
               <p>This figure of the hande here deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with the meane natural line, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the rote of the line of life, &amp; paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing directly through the middeſt of the hand, withoute any inciſions: ſignifieth the good ſtate of the body, and health of the braine. And when it maketh a ſharp corner, with the line of life: it declareth a quickeneſſe of memorye, and vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of minde. But if it be (as is reherſed in the cannon before) vnequal, not ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching paſt the pit or caue of the hand: it betokeneth a fearfull, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, and a forgetfull perſone.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:20"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                  <p>L. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſal</p>
                  <p>L. naturalis</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:21"/>
               <p>If the meane naturall line aboue fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured, make as it were a halfe Circle, with a certain obſcure colour: it threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth hurte by beaſtes, and oftentymes death. But if at the ende of this line on eche ſide do appeare two ſmall lines: it ſignifieth woundes by Weapons. If there appere ouer againſt the middle fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger a little Croſſe deuided with ſmall lines, it doth demonſtrate the weakenes of the bodye, and breuitie of life: and ſo muche the rather if the ſquare or quadrangle be lackyng in the hand.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:21"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:22"/>
               <p>If the hande before portured, haue in the meane naturall line certaine pale knottes: howe manye knottes there be, ſo many murders it doth declare alredy committed: if they be red, they do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the perſone to be hereafter bothe a murderer and thiefe. If there be croked inciſions in the ſaid natural line: I iudge him to be a verye vnhappye and vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate manne. And by the croſſe there, I ſuppoſe him to be ful of ſtrife and debate, and deſirous of diſcord.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:22"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:23"/>
               <p>When this meane natural line ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to the table line, and is croked in the ende in forme preſcribed: it decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a noughty euil tonged man, a ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of bloud, and ſhall often be in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for the ſame, &amp; at the lengthe perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture ſuffer condigne puniſhment. If the ſame line haue priuy inciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: it doth denounce a proude, bablyng, and angrye man. But if there be a croſſe in the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per corner, right againſt the riſyng or hil of the thombe: it ſheweth an honeſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and apt and diſpoſed to all kinde of goodneſſe, and ſo likewiſe on the contrary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The fourth Chapter of <hi>the table line.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis line is called the table line, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it maketh the faſhion of a table in the hande, for ſo wee do call the ſpace remainynge betwene it and the meane naturall line. It is alſo called the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gle or ſquare line, becauſe that wyth
<pb facs="tcp:7828:23"/>the mean natural line, it maketh almoſt a quadrangle or ſquare. If this lyne be equal, long inoughe, depe, and ſtraite: it is a token of a good nature and ſtrength of the principal membres of man, of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, temperance, and a conſtant minde in al good workes. If it ſtretche paſt the hill of the forefinger, and touch the hyll of <hi>Iupiter:</hi> it is a ſigne of vehement an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and crueltie, beinge redde aboue, is a ſigne of a promoter, and enuiynge an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other mans felicitie or welfare. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge braunches riſynge ſtraite to the finger of <hi>Iupiter:</hi> it dothe promiſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocion, encreaſe of riches: and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge poore, ſhal come by little and little to honoure and worſhippe. But if the line be naked without anye braunches ſtretchyng toward the roote of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finger: it betokeneth an vnfortunat and poore manne. If it haue in the end three ſmal lines or braunches aboute the hyll of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> runnynge ſtraite forthe to the vpper corner: it ſignifieth a fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, liberall, merye, modeſt, and noble manne, whiche deliteth in all kinde of
<pb facs="tcp:7828:24"/>comely and cleanlye apparel, and ſwets ſmelles and ſauoures. In whoſe byrthe who doth conſider the <hi>Horoſcope,</hi> (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he finde <hi>Taurus</hi> or <hi>Libra,</hi> whome <hi>Venus</hi> dothe rule: or <hi>Sagittarius</hi> &amp; <hi>Piſces,</hi> vpon whome <hi>Iupiter</hi> hath dominion: or what planet els there be) ſhal eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and finde the cauſe and reaſon of this matter: a croſſe ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in the ſame place, doth ſignify a liberal man, a louer of truth, benigne, gentle to be ſpoken to, and in a maner one indued wyth al kind of vertue. But if this line do finiſhe or ende ouer againſte the hil of the middle finger: it betokeneth a lier, a ſelfe louer, inconſtante, diſceitful, vnſhamfaſt man, and a ſower of ſtrife and debate. When this line is ioyned with the mean natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, ſo that they both make a ſharpe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: the ſame man ſhalbe in many dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers bothe of bodye and minde, that he ſhall be euen wearye of his life. And if he lacke the meane natural line, that the table line ioyninge to the line of life do make a ſharp corner or point, I iudge that that manne ſhall loſe hys heade, or
<pb facs="tcp:7828:24"/>bee deadlye wounded, and ſhall neuer bringe nothinge to paſſe. If this line be deuided, that one part loke towarde the meane natural, thother towarde the hil of <hi>Saturne:</hi> it is a token that he ſhall be often in daunger of his life, and yet eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape. The ſame line beinge ſubtile and ſtraite at the ende vnder the hil of <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> it ſignifieth a gouernor of houſhold: and promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or rule ouer his brethren, kindred, and equalles. If it hathe inciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ouer againſte the middle finger: it betokeneth a flatterer, and a double ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged manne, whome fewe menne ſhall loue. If a line comminge directlye from the quadrangle to the hil of <hi>Saturne,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidinge the table line, do make a little croſſe there: it threateneth violent death. For as this line is a token of greate fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie and good fortune, if it paſſe by the hill of the middle finger, and ſtretche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde the hill of the forefinger: ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, not touchinge the middle finger, and endinge vnder the hil thereof, is a ſigne of extreme pouerty, and many ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities and daungers.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:25"/>
               <p>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this line hauing any interruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or inciſions liyng ſcattered, it ſignifieth a foliſh, and an vnconſtant man, whoſe ſtudy or deſire is to be in conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion with women, as now to loue, now to hate, &amp; oftentimes to chide &amp; fighte with them. And this line being depe, ſubtile, &amp; pale, at the end aforeſaid: declareth an honeſt chaſte man, but weake, &amp; much troubled with ſickneſſe and diſeaſes. But it is an ill ſigne, and ſpecially in a woman, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the line beginninge at the meane natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, going to the hil of the middle finger, doth both deuide the table, and the table line, and is forked in the ende. And that woman whiche hathe a line comminge from the line of life, to the hil aforſaide: it ſignifieth that woman to haue killed her owne childe. The whiche line if it turne backeward to the hil of <hi>Iupiter:</hi> it betokeneth that woman ſhal haue great inheritaunce, if that line be redder then the other: it betokeneth pain in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, &amp; knawing about the nauel. Again, if that line be double, cuttinge the table line: it ſheweth that the man ſhal dye a
<pb facs="tcp:7828:25"/>miſerable death. For bothe in man and woman, it is a toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an il end. And of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the table line towarde the hill of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> or <hi>Iupiter,</hi> is ſene forked: whiche doth note the man ſhal ſuffer many we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry laboures and trauailes in his life, the whiche the redder it is, it ſheweth him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more inclined to anger. When there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the ſame line, certaine ſmall lines riſinge one by another: the more there be, the more honorable thei declare him to be, &amp; to haue the greater power and rule. But in whoſe hande there is no table line at all, I coniecture them to be of both kinds, il willing, contentious, angry, vnfaithful, vnconſtant, &amp; ready to al miſchief. More ouer, if there appeare a line, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming from the table line toward the little finger, it is obſerued, that man neither to be good nor fortunate: but co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous, angry, and horribly ſad, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo filthie, enuioue, and a companion of miſchief, if there apere any lines red, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the table line, &amp; the eare finger: it betokeneth ſo many mariages as thei be in nomber, but if they be croked and
<pb facs="tcp:7828:26"/>pale, thei be already paſt. Again, if there be found vnder the roote of the table line certaine croked croſſes, ſo many as there bee, ſo many deadly enemies do they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token. When that a line comming from the table to the hyl of <hi>Saturne,</hi> deuide the table line, and make a croſſe on the ende therof: it is ſaide to be a token of a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent death. And certaine wiſe menne in this ſcience ſaie, that if there be ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions about the vpper end of the ſame line: it betokeneth ſickenes in youth. If they be in the middeſt, in middle age: if at the other ende, in age: and if the ſame lines runne downeward, the diſcaſe ſhal be of cholore, if they aſcend, of fleume: if they riſe out of the midſt vpward, it ſhal be of bloude: and if contrariwiſe thei turne downewarde, it ſhall be of melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholye, after as his coloure is brighte or darcke. Here is to be vnderſtande, that <hi>Cancer, Scorpio,</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> do rule the ſalt fleume, and <hi>Saturne</hi> cauſeth all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes that come of a viſcouſe or ſlimye fleume, as the morphew, leproſy, canker &amp; goute. <hi>Taurus, Virgo,</hi> and <hi>Capricorne,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:26"/>are of like nature, colde, and drye, and rule the melancoly. And therfore <hi>Venus</hi> dothe cauſe colde and moiſte diſeaſes in the throte and priuy membres. Likewiſe the <hi>Moone</hi> cauſeth the dropſye, fallynge ſickenes, and appopleri. <hi>Aries, Leo,</hi> and <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> haue dominion of the cholere &amp; agues, and biles, which come of bloud. Likewiſe <hi>Mars</hi> dothe rule hote agues, fronſies, and the worme in the head: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Iupiter</hi> we attribute the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>buſt bloud, vnto <hi>Mercury</hi> is applied the diſeaſes of the minde, bitter, and heauy thoughtes, &amp; troubled conſcience. The <hi>Sonne</hi> brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth hote &amp; drye diſeaſes. Al which thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhal appeare more plaine hereafter, wher the nature of the planets &amp; ſignes ſhalbe ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, wherfore note always y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the redneſſe of the lines or inciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s come of the heat of <hi>Mars.</hi> Therefore in all the iudgements of this manuel diuinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I wil you to haue reſpect to the nature of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> planets &amp; ſignes, wherin the ſunne was the time of natiuity or birth. And ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the <hi>Phiſiognomy</hi> muſt be taken hede of, &amp; by that meane the wiſe iudge ſhal get both profite &amp; praiſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:27"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                  <p>L. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſal</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:27"/>
               <p>If there be founde in the line of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune (called alſo the line of proſperitie) thre ſmal braunches and be ioyned with the line of life, and therwith deuide the wreaſt: it betokeneth a good and quicke witte, but if it ioyne to thoſe lines, as it is here deſcribed, with a certaine wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge or crokedneſſe: it ſignifieth an euel, peruerſe, wicked, and a malitious ſlaunderer, and one whiche coueteth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie to ſhede bloude. For when ſo euer you ſhal ſee theſe maner of lines, ſtraite remember and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the nature of <hi>Mars.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:28"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                  <p>L. menſalis.</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:28"/>
               <p>The table line thus diſpoſed that it begin and ende in his due places, do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the good ſtate of the body, &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of the members of generation. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, if there be no table line at all, or that it be withoute braunches ſhorte and groſſe, ſtretchinge oute beyonde the hill of the forefinger: it ſignifieth a miſcheuous perſone, and hard of learninge or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:29"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:29"/>
               <p>¶ Theſe three Braunches in the ende about the hyll of the forefinger, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the vpper corner: is a good ſygne bothe in manne and woman. Alſo a little Croſſe in the ſame place, betokeneth good likewyſe. If the ſaide table line haue manye inciſions: it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth hatred of Princes, and of greate menne: but if the inciſions be vnequall and diſperſed, you ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the varietye of Fortune.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:30"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:30"/>
               <p>If that the table line be lackinge in the hande of manne or woman: it is a verye euill ſigne. For it ſheweth a man prompte to all miſchiefe, which alſo ſhal die an euil death. There muſt alſo be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the lines aboute the hill of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> for there is the ſignes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and the iudgemente of ſuche thinges as pertaine to the planet of <hi>Mercury.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:31"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:31"/>
               <p>Againe, if the table lyne do through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye touche the natural line, that it make a ſharpe angle as you maye ſee: it beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth ill, for ſo many perils ſhal hange ouer his heade, that he maye iuſtelye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent that euer he was borne. But if the naturall line be lackynge, and the table line touch the line of the heart: (except I be vtterlye diſceiued) that man ſhall loſe his head, or dye ſome yll death. When a certaine line (as here you may ſee) doths deuide the table line, and make a ſmal croſſe in the vpper ende: it doth betoken a violent death. The which line, if it riſe ſtraite vpright in the hand of a woman, and deuide the table line: it is an euil to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, for the whiche ſeke the cannon or rule afore. If there be a ſmal croſſe in the end of the table line: it betokeneth ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual dignities, and the rather, if there be two croſſes (as I haue often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued:) it ſignifieth eccleſiaſtical promotions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:32"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The fifth Chapter <hi>of the wreſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ſpace which as is aforeſaid ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering in the ioyning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand to the arme, is called the wreaſte, the whiche if it be pure, and of a good liuely colour: it declareth the good eſtate of the body, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe the euil. And note, that for the moſt part there be two lines which as it wer deuide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the arme. If there be two lines, then if that next the hande be equal, ſtraite, and wel coloured, ſtretching vpwarde: it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth riches, yea, although he be very pore, it promiſeth encreaſe and felicitie, and ſo much the rather, if there be ſtrait brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches and not ouerthwart. If that a line riſing at the rote of the arm, do run vp to the rote of the middle finger: it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth good ſucceſſe and proſperous for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. But if ther be in the ſpace or ioynt foure equal lines wel ioyned, deuidinge the arme ouerthwart, beholde great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and dignitie, ſucceſſion, and heritage of thy kinred. And if there be founde in
<pb facs="tcp:7828:32"/>the rote of the arme, neare the hil of the thombe, nigh the line of life (if it deſcend ſo lowe) thre lines or ſtarres or more: it ſignifieth that perſone to be accuſed and betraied by women, and to ſuffre ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bi them. Further, if a line beginning in the midle of the wreſt, go toward the hil of the <hi>Mone:</hi> it doth pronoſticate ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtormes and troubles of fortune, and priuy enmitie and hatred. The whiche line if it be croked &amp; vnequal: it is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of continual bondage, and that that perſon ſhal neuer come to promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor riches. If there be many lines ſcatred in the wreſt, &amp; riſe to the hill of the tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be: he that hath that ſigne, is in daunger to be afflicted, wounded, ſpoiled, or caſte in priſon by his kinred, or by thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he moſt loued. If there begin certaine lines in the arme, and deuide the wreaſte, and ioyne together in the vpper parie: that man without doubte, ſhal die in exile or baniſhment. The which lines if they do not fully cloſe, but be ſomwhat diſtant a ſonder: he ſhal end his life amongſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein nations, far from his own country.
<pb facs="tcp:7828:33"/>The ſame lines tendynge to the pomell of the hande, do for ſhew long nauigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and iourneyes by ſea, &amp; an vnſtable life to be ſpent in ſuch ſea perigrinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Further, if there go a line directly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wreſte, to the hyl of the forefinger: it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth a longe iourney, and a difficult or doubtful returne. Alſo, if there riſe a line at the wreſt, and runne into the caue of the hande, and be very redde: it declareth the weakenes and diſeaſes of the bodye to come. But if it be pale: they be al rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye paſt, &amp; no more to be feared. If there be founde in the hande of a womanne a triangle, tendyng from the wreſte to the hyl of the <hi>Moone:</hi> it ſheweth her to haue ben corrupt, defiled, and defloured in her firſt youth and floure of her age. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, if there be about the wreſt of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man a little croſſe: I iudge her thereby both honeſt, wiſe, and chaſte. Behold the the ſignes of the good eſtate of the body, when the ſpace in the wreſt next the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at the other next the ioynte of the arme, be both of good &amp; liuely colour, hauynge the foure inciſions aforeſaide: it betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:7828:33"/>al goodneſſe. Againe, howe hateful are the three Starres, whiche threaten daunger by accuſation and ſlaunder. Marke alſo going from the wreſt to the pomel of the hand, how manifeſt an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of infelicitie and euil fortune it is. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming from the wreſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hil of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> how it ſignifieth a forain, &amp; far diſtant life to be led. Another riſing vpright, dothe promiſſe riches &amp; fauora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fortune. Moreouer, the ſignes which are in the hil of <hi>Iupiter:</hi> betoken riches, honor, &amp; dignitie. Alſo four lines almoſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſing the arm (as you may ſe in the hand folowing,) are tokens of long life, and certain lines going from the rote of the arme, making a ſharp angle or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and a ſmal croſſe by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: do promiſſe greate quietneſſe of life, and to paſſe his time merilye with promotion. But the croſſe be away: it doth only promiſſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion and heritage of manye. If the croſſe or certaine litle ſtarres be there: that man ſhal lacke nothing neceſſary to his life.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:34"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:34"/>
               <p>If there be founde in the wreſte two large lines, and the nether line be ſubtil: it ſignifieth riches vntil the midle age, and after worſhip, but decreaſe &amp; decay euerye day more and more. If there riſe out of the ſame lines two ſmal lines, as it were ſupporting and holdinge vp one another, and certaine other lines riſe vp directly through the palme to the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral line: it is a token of great integritie, and declareth that man to be of a good conſcience, the which through his beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſhal come to great riches and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, and alſo come to a good end: but yet it will be the lenger or theeſe thinges happen, if the line aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendinge be croked and writhen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:35"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:35"/>
               <p>If that two lines beginninge at the wreaſte, do riſe throughe the Paime to the hil of the <hi>Sunne</hi> or ringe finger, and the ſame hil be deuided with two lines ouerthwart: it ſignifieth a compaſſer or doer of greate thinges, which ſhal haue rule and aucthoritie in kinges buſineſſe and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and therby get both great honor and richeſſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:36"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:36"/>
               <p>If in the wreſt there be ſene a certain groſe line, and then an other ſubtiller and ſlenderer, and the thirde groſſer and deper then the other: it prepoſeth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of richeſſe in the firſt age or youth, infelicitie &amp; pouertie at the middle age: and in the thirde and laſt age, recouerys of al before loſte, with increaſe of riches, and a quiet life vnto the laſte ende. If there be two croked lines aſcendyng to the hyll of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and vppon the firſt ioynte of the ſame appere two lines go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouerthwart: it ſignifieth increaſe of ſubſtaunce, by longe iourneys and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes. The ſame lines goynge to the hyll of <hi>Mercury:</hi> betokeneth a man apte to manye thinges, but not fortunate to great richeſſe. But if they runne to the finger of <hi>Saturne:</hi> there can be no worſe ſigne, for he will al couetouſneſſe, and immoderate deſire, enuye, and diſdaine at an other mannes felicitie and welfare, and a minde geuen to al euil.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:37"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:37"/>
               <head>The ſixte Chapiter of <hi>the Triangle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe triangle in the hande is three lines, (that is to ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e) the line of life, the meane natural line, and the line of the liuer or ſtomack: which are ſo diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſet, that they make the forme of a tria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gle. And the ſpace incloſed within thoſe lines, is deuided into thre partes or corners: wherof the firſte is made by the line of life, and the natural line, and is called the vpper angle. Thother which is formed by the line of life, and the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the triangle: is called the ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or lifte angle. The triangle being<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of equal angles, hauinge lines faire, wel coloured, and ſtraite: doth repreſent the good qualitie of nature, and of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, wyth healthe and ſecuritye of the minde, with fame and renoume, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo longe lyfe. And contrariwiſe, the lines beinge darcke, vnequal, no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge a playne triangle: dothe derlare the contrarye. Further, if the ſpace of the Triangle bee wide and broade,
<pb facs="tcp:7828:38"/>it doth argue a ſtoute, liberal, and bold ſtomacke. Againe, if it be ſtrait &amp; ſhorte, it betokeneth nigardy, couetouſnes, and fearfulnes. If the plain within be pale, declininge to ſwarthneſſe: it ſignifieth an angry and diſceitful perſone. Alſo, if it be cut and deuided with many wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kels: it ſhe weth the ill diſpoſicion of the body. Moreouer, the vpper angle is clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the line of lyfe, and the natural line thre maner of waies: firſt of al, if it cloſe in the caue of the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ouer againſt the valley: betwene the forefinger and the middle finger: we iudge thereby a miſerable life, endaungered with cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and captiuitie, and a minde ful of anxietie and care, and oftentimes as it were drowned and ouercome, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for the deſire of mony. Secondlye, if it be wel cloſed with a ſharpe corner vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the midſt of the hil of the forefinger: it declareth a good nature, a quick wit, and good diſpoſition, happy and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſucceſſe, with integrite of maners. And all theſe thinges are ſo muche the perfecter if the angle be wel and ſharply
<pb facs="tcp:7828:38"/>cloſed. Thirdly, the lines not ioyning to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether, but hauinge a certaine ſpace left betwene: is an argumente of an ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious man, a ſelfe louer, vnpure, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly, a ſlaunderer, and cruel, a lier, &amp; liuing withoute praiſe or good name. The whiche man if he happen to come in captiuitie or bondage: he ſhall neuer recouer againe his libertye. And if he be fre, yet he ſhal die miſerablye. The ſpace within the triangle roughe and harde: is a ſigne of anger, and crafte, and ſubtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, if it be roughe with wrinkles: it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth enuy, hatred, &amp; ſlaunders. When there doth appere a certain line betwene the two lines ſo nere, that it touch either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: it ſignifieth that man ſhal either be poiſoned, or haue ſome mortal wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. When there appeare in the vpper ſpace foure lines deuidinge one another like croſſes: it ſheweth enuie, backebitinge, with ſtudye and deſire to oppreſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For the two lines ioyning ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye together, dothe declare the goodneſſe of the hole body, but if they ende in the caue or pitte of the hande preciſely ouer
<pb facs="tcp:7828:39"/>againſte the finger of <hi>Saturne,</hi> makinge an angle: it betokeneth bloudſheadinge diuerſe and ſondry waies: as woundes of the head, fluxe of the belly, and if this ſigne be in women it ſignifieth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant fluxe of the menſtrue, and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in childbearinge. If there be in the triangle a figure like a ſtarre: it ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and aduoutrous woman, &amp; paſt ſhame and furious, which throughe her irrefre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable anger, ſhal fal into ſuche a frenſye and madneſſe of minde, that ſhe ſhal co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet and go about to cut her own throte. When ſo euer you perceiue in the hand of a woman in the place aforeſaid, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſtarre puttinge forthe a long role: iudge that woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue four huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. If in the ſame ſpace ther be a croſſe with out any inciſion: it betokeneth good both in man &amp; woman. For in thoſe whiche haue that ſigne, it betokeneth a life wel paſſed, and to ende with good name and fame. The right angle being veri ſharp, doth ſhewe a circumſpect, witty, and ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring man: the ſame beinge obſcure and groſſe: is a ſigne of rudeneſſe, ſlouth, and
<pb facs="tcp:7828:39"/>much geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſlep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The left angle ſharp, betokeneth a babler and crafty man, not withſtanding witty and painful: but if the vpper corne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be not ſharpe, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge as it were the ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acter of <hi>Saturn:</hi> it is a token of an euel and plaine <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> nature. And he whoſe fingers are ſo ſet, that there be in euerye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oynte as it were certaine ſpaces or riſinges croked and vnequal: it betokeneth him to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very pore, &amp; to liue miſerablye. If there be in the vpper parte that is in the third ioynt, an euident writhing or cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: it is a ſigne of enuye, diſceite, malice, and altogether of an euel diſpoſed minde, which man alſo ſhal leade a life ful of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and calamitie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:40"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:40"/>
               <p>The Triangle bothe in the hande of man and woman, dothe ſignifie muche goodneſſe. But if there be founde in the hande of a woman within the triangle, the ſimilitude of a ſtarre: it betokeneth an vnchaſte woman, and geuen ouer to the luſt of the fleſhe. Alſo, in a manne it is a ſigne of euill. Further, if there be in the hande of a manne abouie the right angle, an expreſſe playne ſtarre: it dothe plainly declare an vntruſty, troubleſome diſceitfull, and ſlaunderous perſone: Alſo a thiefe and robber, doinge al thing be it right or wronge, by violence, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined &amp; alſo inſtructed in al euil, who at the length ſhal dye an euil death. Smal braunches in the beginnyng of the line of lyfe, or table line: dothe betoken abounn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and encreaſe of houſhold.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:41"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:41"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:42"/>
               <p>If a ſtarre hauinge a longe ſtalke or braunch going from it, be founde in the hande of a woman: it do the declare that ſhe ſhal haue many huſbandes, as often as the two lines of the vpper corner be diſtante a ſunder with a ſpace betwene them, it is an euil ſigne. Alſo, foure lines deuidinge them ſelues in the vpper cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in maner of a croſſe: do demonſtrate an enuious detractor, and a man of euel fame and name. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a figure as it wer the caracter of <hi>Saturne,</hi> dothe pronounce an euel end: the table line alſo faſhioned as you may ſe, doth betoken an infortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate man, and geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the belly, if there be the figure of a forke either vpward or downward in the ſaid triangle: it ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth an inconſtant and libidinous man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſeuenth Chapter</hi> of the Quadrangle.</head>
               <p>THe quadrangle is called that ſpace which is betwene y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> line &amp; the meane naturall. Then if the inciſions of thys quadrangle be of a bright and liuely co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loure,
<pb facs="tcp:7828:42"/>it dothe promiſſe the equitie and vprightneſſe of life: and contrariwiſe, it doth declare a wicked &amp; naughtye man. The ſame ſpace ample, &amp; large: betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth liberalitie and ſtou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes of ſtomack. A croſſe alſo in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame place of the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſignifieth good ſucceſſe in eccleſiaſtical miniſtrations, and is ſo muche the more fortunate, if the figure be doubled or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled like vnto a lattiſe: but if the ſame croſſe be croked or vndeuided with ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart inciſions, it doth pronoſticate the contrary to al that is aforeſaide. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, an euident ſtarre in the ſame place, dothe demonſtrate a ſtoute manne, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righte, true, and of a good conſcience. The whiche manne although throughe aduerſitie and miſfortune he fal into po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, yet he ſhal riſe againe by his own vertue and goodnes: Yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, it ſheweth him to be a femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine man, which alſo ſhal ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſome aduerſitie and trouble for women.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:43"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:43"/>
               <p>Oftentimes alſo the hole table is lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: then if the table line ioyne with the natural line, and beginne a triangle: it ſheweth that man to be in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to be ſlaine by many that ſhal lye in wait for him. But if in the end of the table about the pommel of the hande there be a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt croſſe: iudge therby many perigri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, longe iourneis, and often chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of place, but therby good fortune. When the two lines whiche make the table be far diſtant, with a greate ſpace betwene them: it is a token of ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heate, and vntemperate humoures in the body. Contrariwiſe, the plaine or table of the hande beinge narowe and ſtraight: betokeneth a couetous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to get goodes, and therwithal dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye cruell. And this is ſufficientlye ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the principall inciſions or lines whiche are within the hande. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentlye wee will intreate of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges or hilles of the fingers, and alſo of the fingers them ſelues, with the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the planettes, and what ſo euer els ſhal remain nedeful to be ſpoken of.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:44"/>
               <p>You haue heard before declared what theſe characters, lines, &amp; croſſes in the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, do ſignifie &amp; foreſhew. The ſtarre alſo in the middeſt of the Table, doth ſhew a louer, and mainteyner of all honeſtie &amp; goodneſſe, and therfore had in reuerence, &amp; aſpiringe to great dignitie. And let this be a general rule, for al thoſe whoſe handes doe quiuer and ſhake by nature, (for vnto many it happeneth by chaunce, and to other ſome by ſickneſſe and diſeaſes,) to iudge them as angrye, ſcolders, and braulers, vnclene men, and dronkerds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <hi>The .viii. Chapter of</hi> the hilles of the fingers, and firſt of the hill of the thombe, called alſo amongſt auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t writers, the hill of <hi>Venus.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOwe that there is ſufficientlye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of the principall lines of the hande: we will alſo write of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer inciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the fingers, and of their hilles: laiyng before your eyes their ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
<pb facs="tcp:7828:44"/>with the natures of the ſeue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> planets, wherby you may know what is agreable among them, and contrariwiſe what doth hurt. The riſing or ſwellyng of the fleſh, beginnyng at the line of life, deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng ſtraite to the wreſt is called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hill of the tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b: it is alſo called the hil of <hi>Venus,</hi> becauſe it is ſoft and plain with very few or no wrinkcles or inciſions, &amp; being ruddy and liuely coloured: it ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth the good quality &amp; eſtate of the body, alſo a louer of women, &amp; one delityng in cleanely and fine appare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. But if there appere in the ſame place a certaine ſhort line going down ward by the line of life, (&amp; therfore called the ſiſter of the line of life:) it ſignifieth a man delitynge in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerye. Notwithſtanding, the ſame line being long, not broken of, wholy accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paniyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> line of life thorow: doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe continual richeſſe. But if it begin not in the vpper ende of the hill, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture in the midſt, or not farre from the nether ende: it betokeneth lacke and penury in youth, but after abundaunce &amp; plenty. Often alſo there be foure lines
<pb facs="tcp:7828:45"/>equally diſtant, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge from the top of the hil to the wreſt, whiche do promeſſe richeſſe and honoure euen in the firſte age, the which lines if they begin not at the verie, top but at the ioynt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be: they do promiſſe the ſame ſucceſſe, but lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger and latter to come to paſſe, euen in the extreme age. If the ſame foure lines do deuide the vpper ioynt of the thombe a litle within the naile, or be very neare the ſame ioynt, and be long, brighte ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: they betoke preſent honour and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. And alſo ruie and dominion if the ſame foure lines be deuided or cut, with other ſmal lines going ouerthwart. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times there is a ſubtile incſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the top of the hil of the thombe, going toward the line of life: which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth that man ſhal die by ſome ſtroke of weapon. Alſo, many brighte lines ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge ouer againſte the fore finger, and deuidinge the line of life, are tokens of manye perigrinations and longe ioure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neis into diuers places. The ſame lines deuiding the line of life in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpper part or beginninge: ſheweth a boaſter and
<pb facs="tcp:7828:45"/>an ambitious manne, riotous, and dene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. In ſome alſo a red line wandringe vp and downe the hil of the thombe: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth inceſt, and carnal companye with his kinred. Albeit, I wold not haue ſuche credite geuen to this ſcience, that this ſhoulde ſtraite be iudged true, the hande beinge loked vppon, for when we ſpeake of accompaniynge with kinred, we woulde haue it vnderſtande that man to be ſo enflamed with fleſhly luſte and appetite, that there is but little hope that he wil abſtain from them. To the whiche thinge it behoueth muche to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the face and hole bodye of the man, whiche dothe declare the ſtate of life to come. For they which be pleaſaunt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nered, leadinge a mery and ioconde life, beinge conuerſaunte and reioyſinge in plaies and daunſes, haue ſmal ſtarres in their hil, for this is the whole ſtudye of <hi>Venus:</hi> and ſuche menne haue theyr hil commonlye deuided with many ſmal and brighte inciſions, whome if you do wel behold, you ſhal ſee his face wel co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured, his body decently co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pact, his eyes
<pb facs="tcp:7828:46"/>blacke and cleare, a pleaſaunte counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce &amp; honeſt geſture, and altogether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enerous, and therefore wanton, rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, lecherous, delitinge in diſe playe, daunſing, and other paſtimes, hauinge pleaſure in flours, roſes, and ſwete ſmels coſtly apparel, deſirous of golde and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, often laughing, conuerſant amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt women, deſirous and apte to learne all ſciences of this ſort and nature, and of a dul wit and vnderſtanding to lerne any other thing. Alſo light of belief, eaſye to be deceiued, liberal, gentle, iuſt &amp; faithful, deliting in painted tables &amp; pictures, &amp; al ſo deſirous to learn to paint him ſelf, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing good fortune in al thinges of that ſort, in the contraries not ſo fortunate: Whoſe life ſhalbe pleaſaunt with mean ſubſtance, not couetous of lucre &amp; gain, beloued of manye, geuen to all kinde of pleaſure, not eaſilye moued with anger, not careful about hard &amp; doutful buſines, but content with his preſent eſtate, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting al anxiety &amp; trouble of minde apart, &amp; ſo liuing to his laſt end. For likewiſe as in this, ſo in all other is the nature of
<pb facs="tcp:7828:46"/>man to be conſidered, aſwel by the habit and proportion of the body, as by loking in the hand, wherfore that which is here expreſſed, let it be an example to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in al others. Further, they which haue the hil of the thombe deuided with many ſmal wrinkles not equally diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but ſcattering and out of order: are to be counted fleſhli, vnpure, froward, &amp; braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, delitinge to be in contention with women, burninge ſo much in luſt that they be neuer ſatiſfied but ſeke ſtraunge and vnaccuſtomed kindes of vſe like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to monſters &amp; beaſtes, howe be it they be of an vnpleſant conuerſation &amp; life, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in no kind of wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or learning, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profiting any thing at al therin, but very apt to learne al handye craftes, and to deuiſe and inuente al thinges pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto riot. The cauſe of this I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne to <hi>Venus</hi> beinge in the .vi. or .viii. houſe in the birth of ſuch men. Wherby you may perceiue how <hi>Aſtrology</hi> &amp; <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy</hi> do mutually embraſe thone tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo that one without thother can not wel be vnderſtand, as ſhalbe ſhewed hereafter more at large.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:47"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>Venus.</head>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:47"/>
               <p>If there be about the firſt ioynt of the thombe a creſte like a ring going round about, and deuiding the thombe: many do ſtifly iudge and ſay that that manne ſhalbe hanged. The which thing I haue proued true in one man, but becauſe I haue ſene many hanged which haue lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked that marke, I leaue it as vncertain. Alſo thre or foure inciſions in breadth vnder the firſt ioynt: betokeneth richeſſe and honor in youth, if they be aboue that ioynt, it ſhalbe in the middle age, but if the ſame inciſions be neare the ſeconde ioynt: it ſignifieth the ſame effecte, but in the extreame or laſte age. If any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manne haue her thombe ſo marked (as is deſcribed in the ſecond figure) I iudge her to be eſchewed and auoided, as craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and noughte. Alſo this marke ☉ in the midſt of the hil of <hi>Venus:</hi> ſignifieth a libidinous, euel mannered, &amp; an aduou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, willingly putting forth her ſelfe to hordome &amp; vice, wonderful vnte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, &amp; vnſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iable in copulation. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what maried woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath thre lines
<pb facs="tcp:7828:48"/>ſomwhat vnequally diſtant, deuidinge the firſt ioynte of the thombe: it ſheweth her to be in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger either of death, or of a wounde by her owne huſbande. More <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uer, many ſmal croſſes vnder the ſecond ioynt, declareth a verye holy woman, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to religion. Againe, onelye two of thoſe markes dothe ſignifye an vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful babbler, and a woman full of ſtrife and diſcord. Alſo many ſmal braunches in the ſame place dothe betoken a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton women, and one ſone ripe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <hi>The .ix. Chapiter of</hi> the hil of the forefinger, and of the finger, with the nature of the Iouialles.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IVpiter</hi> the moſt benificial planet of al, hath his place in the hil whiche is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the forefinger, the whiche hil beinge plaine and ſmoth, dothe ſhewe vnto the honeſty of life and goodnes of nature. And ſo muche the rather, if there be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſmal darke riules going out from the ſame finger, the whiche if they be
<pb facs="tcp:7828:48"/>not farre diſtant: it betokeneth honoure and dignity by princes. And ſome being bolder, do define and ſaye, that he ſhal attaine to ſo many degrees of honor, or eccleſiaſtical dignities, as there be ſuche inciſions in his hande. It is alſo a token of magnitude and boldneſſe, deſire, and ſtudy to compaſſe greate thinges, as alſo a deſire of renowme and glorye: when a ſtrait cleare line beginning at the rote of the forefinger, almoſt at the mean na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural line, doth turne backe again to the corner of the hil. A ſmal line alſo goinge from the table line to the hil of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finger: doth ſignify the ſame aforeſaide. If that certain ouerthwart riules do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the lines aforeſaide, they betoken wounds in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head. Alſo a groſſe, bright, and ruddy line, deuidinge the forefinger from the middle finger in a man, dothe betoken the ſickeneſſe of the intrailes or bowels, in a woman it ſignifieth daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in childe bearinge, and ſo muche the more daunger, if it be very red. More o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, croſſes in the hil of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> do ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy honoure and promotions in ſo manye
<pb facs="tcp:7828:49"/>degrees, as there be founde croſſes, for it hath bene often ſene, ſuch men to haue gotten henefices and eccleſiaſticall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocions abundauntlye. And thoſe men hauyng thoſe markes, are chiefly called Iouials, or of the nature of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng for the moſt parte good ſucceſſe in al affayres of that ſorte or kinde, who for the moſt part are of a meane ſtature, and pleaſant forme or ſhape, whitely co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured, thicke heered, comely eyed, geuen to clenlines &amp; mirth. They be naturally ſtout ſtomaked, &amp; hie minded, hauyng to do in great &amp; waighty affaires, liberall ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times aboue their abilitie, coueting to rule and haue dominion ouer other, deſpiſers of al mediocrite and meane e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, honeſt, noble, couetous of glorye &amp; renowne, ambicious, pleaſant and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, faythful and frendly, abhorrynge al fraud, and diſceit, peaceable, apt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to al learnyng and wiſedome, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique, and eloquente. The walkyng or goyng is meane, neither faſte nor ſlow, betokenyng a great conſtancy of minde. No menne more fortunate then they, or
<pb facs="tcp:7828:49"/>that ſoner obteyne their deſires. For the moſt part alwaies in fauour with prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or gréate men, louyng dearely their wyfe and children. Alſo proſperous and happye in ſucceſſion and poſteritie. More ouer, they bee greate eaters, and therfore often diſeaſed wyth the rawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſtomack or liuer, or els long liued, hauynge a cleare and ſhril voyce, &amp; the formoſt two vpper teeth ſtickinge oute. And thus muche of them on whoſe byrthe <hi>Iupiter</hi> is lorde, without coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of any euil wyth hym. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, many lines goynge ouerthwarte in the vpper ioynte of the forefinger in the hand of a woman, do declare that ſhe ſhal haue large inheritance by the death of her frendes and kinred. The ſame in the middle ioynt, do ſignify enuy, lying, and diſceit, which ſignes if they be in the hil of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> do miniſter ſuſpicion of an angry, teſty, vnmanerly, and ſcolding woman.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:50"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>Iupiter.</head>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:50"/>
               <p>And thus haue I alſo founde oute the number of children: If anye wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man haue in the middle ioynte three bryght inciſions runnyng lengthwaies, whereof the middlemoſt is ſhorte and blunte at the one ende, and an other bright line goyng ouerthwart, &amp; two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther darke lynes whiche touche not the middle ſhorte lyne. Alſo wicked and noughtye women haue ſtarres wyth a halfe compaſſe in the hyll of <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:51"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:51"/>
               <p>The ſame alſo do declare thre crok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d lines almoſt equally diſtant within the vtter ioynt of the forefinger. Contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, it is a token of honeſtie and chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, when the middle ioynte is deuided with many lines going in length, with a ſtarre in the middeſt. Alſo it promiſeth great inheritance or riches to come (whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther it be by order of inheritaunce, or of eccleſiaſticall dignities or promocions) vnto hym that hath a cleare ſtarre not interrupte with anye line or wrinkle in the hyl of <hi>Iupiter.</hi> A line going from the hil of the middle finger to the wreaſte: ſheweth fearful and weake harted men, but notwithſtandyng enuious. Some alſo affirme, that thoſe which haue that line, if they chaunce to be taken &amp; caſte in priſon: either they ſhal dye there, or be greuouſly puniſhed, or very hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſcape and be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The .x. Chapiter of the</hi> hill of the middle finger, appropriate to Saturnus of the finger it ſelfe with the nature of the Saturnines.</head>
               <p>THe middle finger of the hande as is aforeſaid in this ſcience, is attribute vnto <hi>Saturne,</hi> and called by his name, &amp; therfore the riſynge vnderneth it, is alſo called the hill of <hi>Saturne.</hi> The which hil if it be plaine and ſmoth without wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles or inciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: it declareth a ſimple ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, paineful, and without diſceit. If that a riule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng from the table line do cut the hyll of <hi>Saturne:</hi> it ſignifieth a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful man, diſquieted and vexed with day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubles and cares, alwayes ſtudiyng and muſyng on ſomthing, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng ſeldome riche. Alſo many inciſions in the ſame place, do declare an heauy &amp; penſiful life, full of penurie &amp; neceſſitie, priſonment, and tormentes. Likewiſe, a line bowyng from the rote of the rynge finger to the hyll of <hi>Saturne,</hi> ſheweth a flouthful and ſluggiſh man, foliſhe, and
<pb facs="tcp:7828:52"/>raſhe, neuer doyng any thing wittely, albeit ſometime foliſhe, bolde, of a folyſh and rude minde and vnderſtandynge. They ſaye alſo, that woman which hath more lines betwene the fingers of the <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>Saturne,</hi> then betwene the <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>Mercurye,</hi> there beinge ſome lines alſo: to be apt to generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of men childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This alſo I know certaine, that if any ſmal lines go from the principal lines of the hande to the hil of <hi>Saturne:</hi> thei declare an euil diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and not a verye honeſt life. It is alſo iudged a token of ſterilitie and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennes in a woman, to haue a croſſe or a ſtarre in the firſt ioint of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> finger. And thoſe whiche haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hil diuerſly deuided with riules, thother hil beinge ſmothe and plain, are to be iudged Saturnins, whoſe nature for the moſt parte is to be pale coloured, vncomelye vyſaged, their eyes fixed downeward to the grounde, in goynge ſlowe, leane, and oftentimes croked backed, and for the moſt part euil manered. For <hi>Saturn</hi> maketh them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, diſceitful, and craftye, delitinge
<pb facs="tcp:7828:53"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to be alone, regardyng no man, without al frendſhippe. Not very curious aboute their meates, great drinkers, and often times great eaters, continually diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with cares and miſeries, neuer free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, ful of heauy and fearful thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtes and imaginations, louyng fennes
<pb facs="tcp:7828:53"/>and ſtandyng waters, liuynge filthelye, ſlow and rare of ſpeach, colde of nature, weake bodied, and ſickly, of a low voice, hoorſe, and ſluttyng, lightly enuiyng o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and whom thei hate, thei perſecute continully without remiſſion. Their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite is to buylde, to plante, plowe, and al thinge that will continue, hauyng no great pleaſure in women, and therfore ſeldome hauynge children, but diynge without iſſue. Wonderful defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders and kepers of their libertie, iudgynge it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme miſerie and euil to ſerue and be in bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage, deliting in blacke, &amp; therfore clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing them ſelues therwith, ful of ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and feare, geuing great regard vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to dreames: and thus far of Saturnins. That womanne that hathe fiue or ſyxe lines in the firſte ioint of the middle fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger runnynge downewarde, ſhal beare a ſonne which ſhal be a prieſt. Alſo that manne which hath a ſtarre in the ſame iointe, ſhal either kil or be killed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:54"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The .xi. Chapter of the</hi> ringe finger and hyll, and the nature of them borne vnder the <hi>Sunne.</hi>
               </head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the Sun</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>THe hil of the ringe finger, called al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of moſt learned men the hil of the <hi>Sunne,</hi> is that which riſeth in a certayne ſpace betwene the finger and the table line, if there procede from the rote ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the table lyne, certaine ſmal lines: they worke the ſame effect that <hi>Mercury</hi> doth amongſt the Aſtrologians, whiche maketh a man of a pregnant and quick wit, geuen to diuers kinde of learning, proude, and eloquent, alſo fortunate to promotions, as wel prophane as ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual. But if there be other lines drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouerthwart the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or that they deuide one
<pb facs="tcp:7828:54"/>another: it ſignifieth the clene contrary. But if the ſame lines do not touche or deuide the other: it is a good token that he ſhal ouercome &amp; treade doune al his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. The which, if they neither touch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> finger, neither be equally placed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the table line, but be hangyng betwene, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the alteration of the lynes: they note the chaunge of eſtate, and lyfe. Alſo, manye ſlender redde lynes in the ſame hil, do ſhew a wiſe and mery man, the which lines if thei be croked and red: betoken diſeaſes wherewith a man is preſently vexed and troubled. If they be pale, paines al ready paſt. Again, if they deuide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues like a ſaint And rewes croſſe, ſtretched from the table line to the firſt ioynt: it ſignifieth a prouidente and circumſpect man in doing his buſineſſe. There is alſo another token pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing fortunate thinges, ſpecially in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of honour and dignity, and al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges pertaininge to vertue, liberality, and wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which are two croked lines, equal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly diſtant going from the wreſt, as you may perceiue by this figure.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:55"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Alſo many lines in the hand of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man about the vpper ioynt runninge to gether, do ſhew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. And more ouer, that ſhe ſhalbe had in reuerence &amp; made rich by her huſbandes, alſo they ſhewe her to be deuout, but not to lead no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtical life. So likewiſe, if they be in
<pb facs="tcp:7828:55"/>the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ioynt, they declare that ſhe ſhal alwaies be had in reputacion and honor but amongſt them of her own ſtocke. Alwaies they ſignify riches, aſwel in menne as in women. But they are euel if they ſtretche to the hil of the <hi>Sunne.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <hi>The .xii. Chapter of</hi> the hil and finger of Mercurye, and of his nature.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Mercury</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>THe hil of the eare finger or rather of <hi>Mercury,</hi> is betwene the little finger and the table line. It is greatlye materiall whether it be plaine withoute inciſions or vaines.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:56"/>
               <p>For it being wel colored without wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles, ſheweth a conſtant mind in a man, in a maide integritie. A ſlender line ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing at the table to the rote of the hil: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth liberality. Alſo mani ſuch lines beginning betwene the table line, and the little finger: ſignifieth ſo many ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages as there be lines. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, the lengthe, coloure, and ſlender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of them muſt be marked: for the pale lines ſignify mariages paſt, the long and wel coloured the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come. It happeneth often ſome of them to be groſſe and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry red, wherby thou ſhalt iudge a lier, a theſe, and robber, and one defiled with al kinde of miſchief. Now if there be a cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked line, as it were a circle goinge from that finger to the middle finger: it decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth an excellente wit and diſpoſicion, in whome there is great hope, that he wil he apt and prompt to al kind of affaires. If there be ſmal croked lines in the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per part of the litle finger in the hand of a woman: it ſheweth a condition propre to al women, which is pride, much talke and babling, with inconſtancy. And this
<pb facs="tcp:7828:56"/>for the moſt part is the <hi>Phiſiognomy</hi> of al the <hi>Mercurians,</hi> meane coloured be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne blacke and white, hie foreheade, round face, faire eyes like a cat, blacke and thin berd, ſlender body, comelye ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, thin lips, ſharp noſe, ſhril voice and ready, a quicke motion and ſtirringe. If thou wilt for know this by the hil: if it be ful of ſtrait lines, he is alſo of a pregna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wit, bold, a horemonger, faithful, readye to lie, a louer of his owne ſectes, a hater of ſuperſtition, not regardinge temples nor oracles, apt to al ſciences <hi>Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> and <hi>Geometry.</hi> Finallye, a man fit for al aſſaies, a doctoure, a poete, endued with the knowledge of tonges, a ſercher of ſecretes, a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> harty, modeſt, but ful of wordes, hurting no man, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liting in the cleaneſt handye craftes, as in painting and ſuch like. Albeit, he is more vexed with ſickeneſſe and troubled with deluſions of ſpirites, then other men.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:57"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:57"/>
               <p>There be alſo certaine tokens, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the firſt in the firſt ioynt doth declare a man to be ſtudious, chiefely of <hi>Retho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rike,</hi> arrogant, proude, and of a ripe wit. That in the ſecond ioynt although it vary fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt, yet hathe it the ſame effecte, it ſheweth an excellente preacher or oratoure, if it ſtand ouerthwart: he is troubled with ſondrye paſſions, horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dreames, and euel fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſies. If in the thirde ioynt there be a croſſe, it is a ſure ſigne of pouertie and neceſſity. And this is ſufficient of <hi>Mercury,</hi> although the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure do not conteine al the ſignes, yet we haue deſcribed the chiefeſt and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, for who can comprehende ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye ſortes of lines &amp; tokens of ſo diuerſe diſpoſitions in ſo ſmall a roume. Wee haue lefte nothinge oute in the cannon or rule, which might be to any effecte or purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:58"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <hi>The .xiii. Chapter of</hi> the vtter part of the Triangle, and of them ouer whom the mone hath power and dominion.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of a devil</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>FIrſte of al, I will declare what the <hi>Chiromanciers</hi> cal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtter part of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Triangle, it is the ſame whiche by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon name is called the line of the ſtomacke or liuer, with riſinge at the tail of the line of life, touching the mean natural, maketh a triangle, if ther be no let in the natiuitye. Albeit, I knowe in ſome it doth not ioyne, yet it is not to be left out, for it is found to be of as muche force as al the other, for if it make a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite Triangle with the meane natural and line of life: it ſheweth the floriſhing helth and proſperitie bothe of bodye and
<pb facs="tcp:7828:58"/>mind. If it happen to be darke coloured &amp; ful of points: it ſheweth the il digeſtion of the ſtomack, morphew, colick, flegme, bindinge of the bellye, paine of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke and ribbes, and ſpecially if it be pale. But if it be wel drawen, ruddye, nearer the line of life then the midle na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural: it betokeneth paine in the head, if contrariwiſe, it be nearer the middle na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, it ſignifieth the inflamation of the lungs, anexed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ague, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kongh, and ſtinke of the mouth. Alſo, ſuch a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in the place of the <hi>Mone,</hi> ☉ although it ſeme to be but a reft, yet it betokeneth the loſſe of one eye, if there be two ☉☉, the loſſe of bothe eyes, whiche thinge I haue proued true bi my own hurt. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a ſtarre in the ſame place, ſignifieth a wicked and miſcheuous man. If you deſire to know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phiſnamy of the luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, they be whitlye faced with ſome red, their browes ioyned together, their face and cheekes blowen, vnequal eyed, ſomwhat blacke, peraduenture marked in the face, vnthrifty, ſickelye, vnſtable, ſlow, foliſh, pore in youthe, in the ſeconde
<pb facs="tcp:7828:59"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                     <p>locus line</p>
                  </figure>
age richer ſomwhat. But in thertreame age miſerable again, dotinge, vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and borne to trauail, geuen to the fallynge ſickeneſſe and Palſye, to the flixe &amp; blaſtyng, except the <hi>Moone</hi> in the rote of natiuitie haue the <hi>Sunne</hi> or <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> propice and in amitie with her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:59"/>
               <head>The .xiiii. Chapter of the place of Mars, and the nature of the Martialiſtes.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                     <p>locꝰ Martis.</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Mars.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:60"/>
               <p>VVe thought it mete before we ſpake of <hi>Mars,</hi> to place hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the caue of the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the triangle, ouer againſt the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural line: in the which if there apere an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other perfit triangle according to al the natural properties of the <hi>Martialiſts:</hi> you may pronoſticate, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> by hew much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame is larger &amp; bigger the man is to be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the more vicious. And ſpecially if it be wel proportioned with the lines. The phiſnamye herein is not to be diſpiſed, which I haue therfore adioyned becauſe it ſhuld helpe the <hi>Chiromancier</hi> the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in iudgemente, otherwiſe it can not be ſo exactly iudged. Thei be hie colored in the face, as burnte of the <hi>Sunne,</hi> thinne heered and curled, ſmall eyes, ſomewhat croked bodied, with a ſharpe and fiers aſpecte, boulde, couetous, diſceitful, a briber, vnfaithful, a ieſter, vnſhamefaſt, lighte, vnconſtant, angry, ſeditious, ſuſpicious, impaciente, a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, a boaſter, a mocker, periured, and a counterfaiter of all thinges, that maye be counterfaited.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>¶ The concluſion of this worke of <hi>Chiromancy.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:60"/>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>Chiromantial prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> or manual diuinations, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the places of the. vii, Planets.</head>
               <p>BEſides the Charecters &amp; lines which are commonlye in the hande, there dothe often appeare ſtraunge notes and markes, whiche betoken ſome great vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen thinge, wherefore our intente now is to ſhe we their effect &amp; meaning. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue ſhewed before the natures of the ſignes, and what Planet is lorde of euerie man, nowe we will attempte to knowe what ſuſpecte tokens bee in the Planettes: I meane not thooſe in the heuens, but (heir charecters which be in the fingers, of what force they be.</p>
               <div n="Mars" type="planet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:61"/>
                  <head>Of the place of Mars.</head>
                  <p>THe place of <hi>Mars</hi> is in the Triangle, wherefore if you perceaue or finds ſuche a marke or ſigne drawen in thys ſort in the triangle, iudge that man to be a Martialiſt, &amp; that he ſhal be hanged. The other three markes ouer againſte the table of the hande: ſignifieth bolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſtubburneſſe, ſeueritie, waſtinge of his patrimonie and inheritaunce, wyth oppreſſion of his frendes and kinſfolke.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Venus" type="planet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:61"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure> 
                     <hi>Of the finger of Venus.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VEnus</hi> doth poſſeſſe the thombe &amp; the hyll therof, which for the plainneſſe of it, is called the hil of <hi>Venus,</hi> if there be in the firſt ioint ſuch a marke, they ſhal proſpere in all their affayres. In the
<pb facs="tcp:7828:62"/>ſeconde iointe, it betokeneth pouertye, and neare the naile, that he ſhal haue a leprous childe, or els in the place of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> it ſhe weth a venerous man, geuen to inceſt and aduoutrie, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if the markes be in the hill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="Jupiter" type="planet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:62"/>
                  <head>Of the finger of Iupiter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IVpiter</hi> hathe alſo his proper markes, who poſſeſſeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> forefinger, as is here preſccibed, in the firſt ioint they ſignifie an aduoutrer, &amp; in thupper ioints riches, and ſpeciallye in age. The other ſignes for the moſt part betoken no yll.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="Saturn" type="planet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:63"/>
                  <head>Of the finger of Saturne.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SAturne</hi> the higheſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, kepeth the midle finger with his priuate cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectes here diſcribed, which declare a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnine ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe nature you may part<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly gather bi that which is aforeſaid, and partly we wil define more at large hereafter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="sun" type="planet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:63"/>
                  <head>Of the finger of the Sunne.</head>
                  <p>A Line portured in this ſort appearing in the ring finger, called properly the finger of the <hi>Sunne,</hi> ſignifieth long life and proſperitie, al other apparances are tokens of euill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="Mercury" type="planet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:64"/>
                  <head>Of the finger of Mercury.</head>
                  <p>THey haue appointed vnto <hi>Mercurys</hi> the little finger with certaine lines, whereby you may perceiue and know a Mercurial here briefly expreſſed, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token benefites or offices, all other ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie ſadneſſe, melancholy, and heauines.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="Moon" type="planet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:64"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the place of the Moone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>THe place of the <hi>Mone</hi> is in the pomel of the hande. Wherfore if thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the lines here diſcribed riſing from the wreſte: it ſheweth ſluggiſhnes, in the place of <hi>Iupiter</hi> dulneſſe and foliſhnes, &amp; ſpeciallye in women, whiche by nature are not very wiſe.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>chiromantic diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:65"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Concluſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>YOu haue hearde (deare Reader) the ſignes and markes of the planets, by the which without <hi>Aſtrology</hi> you maie learne and knowe vnto what planet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye man is ſubiecte, deſieryng you to take this our Treatiſe in good worth, &amp; to make a proufe thereof with labour &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, leſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we mai be thought herein to haue ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t our time &amp; labour in vaine. There lacketh but only iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour or pain is nothing: for ſo much as the hole effecte maie be vnderſtand and knowen by once or twiſe readyng at the moſte.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fare ye well.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:7828:65"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>The ſeconde Boke</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of an <hi>Epiloge</hi> or briefe collection of the hole ſumme of the Arte of <hi>Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ognomy.</hi> By the which you may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and perceiue, what euery membre from the crowne of the head, to the ſoule of the foote, dothe ſignifye and meane. Alſo a brief introduction vppon the faces of the ſignes, with certaine cannons and rules, vpon ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; diſeaſes. And firſt to begin with the eyes.</head>
            <p>THe eyes therfore being moiſte and cleare, ſheweth mirthe, good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and an honeſt life, declininge and loking downward, red, &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great: betokeneth glotony, and fleſhly luſte. Smal hollowe eyes, couetouſneſſe. Graye eyes an euil man: hollowe eyes a craftye man, waueringe vnſtable eyes, declare a ſeditious, ſuſpitious, vnfaithful boſter. Great eyes ſlouth, tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blinge eyes ſluggiſhnes, gliſtering eyes betoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, ſmal eyes vnſhamfaſtnes, diuerſe coloured &amp; ſmal: ſignifieth crafty flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Turning toward the noſe, betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:7828:66"/>lecherous men. Greate dropping<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eyes with an vnſtable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance, mad men. Dry eies, crafty men. Black cleare eyes, iuſt, witty, libidinous, and cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning. The circle of the ball gren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: declareth a craftye wicked man and a theefe. Moiſte eyes ſtoutnes of ſtomacke, perfect ſpeche and good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel. Great gliſtering eyes: ſhewe mad men, light, &amp; glotons, Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hollow and dry eyes, declare vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full and traitorous perſons. Highe eyes, large, cleare, pure, &amp; moiſt: are tokens of circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpect, diligente perſons, and louers. Alwaies running and droppinge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe of ſicknes, declareth foliſhnes. Miſty dry eyes, vnfaithful me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Larg eyes gliſtering, moiſt, &amp; cleare: ſignifieth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and high men, violent, ſtout, and boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Blacke and ſhining eyes, fearful and euel men. Swelling eyes and raw: ſheweth glotons and vnamiable men. Smal and holow eyes, couetous, diſceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men. Chereful eyes betoken iuſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, prone to laughter, gentle, &amp; holy. Moiſt eyes, good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel. Winking eyes, a theſe and a lier in wait. Bleared eyes, libido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
<pb facs="tcp:7828:66"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Vpright browes, amiable, the browes hanging ouer effeminate plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge with the bries: ſignifieth adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous perſons.</p>
            <p>The forhed narow, ſheweth a foliſhe perſon, long, one apt to learne. A hie fore hend ſwelling and round, is a ſigne of a crafty man &amp; a coward. Ful of wrinkles, ful of cares, round, enuious and craftye, A large forhed betokeneth a liberal ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>The browes heery, ſignifieth ſtutting: &amp; being extent to the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples vnclean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nes.</p>
            <p>The face plaine and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lat, declareth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ful of debate and ſtrife, without any riſing or ſwelling: infurious, and an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane perſon. A leane face is token of a wiſe man. A fleſhy face one apt to learn. A ſad face ſheweth ſomtime foliſhneſſe, ſometime wiſdome.</p>
            <p>Open eares betokeneth a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon or vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, great eares an vnwiſe man, ſmal eares a fole, ſquare eares a learned and wiſe man.</p>
            <p>A ſharpe noſe ſheweth an angry per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, thicke and lowe, euil manner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. The noſe tending or ſtretching to the mouth,
<pb facs="tcp:7828:67"/>declareth honeſty, ſtrength, and apte to learning. A great noſe good, a litle noſe a diſceitful perſon. A noſe like an ape, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth a libidinouſe &amp; riotous perſon.</p>
            <p>The noſethrilles thicke and ſtronge, betokeneth ſtrength: round, feare: drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, mery &amp; coragious: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noſethrils narow &amp; round are tokens of a fole.</p>
            <p>A bigge mouth ſheweth a bolde and hardy warriour. The mouth very bigge with the vpper lippe hanging ouer: ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth a glotton and an vngodly man, a babler, raſh, foliſh, and vnſtedfaſt.</p>
            <p>Slender, thinne, and ſubtile lips, beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken eloquence, but thin lips with a litle mouth, an effeminate perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Fleſſhy lips a fole. And they whoſe dogge teethe do beare out their lippes, are to be counted co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumelous, ſlanderers, and vnfaithfull. A ſharp throtbole ſignifieth a vain ſeſter</p>
            <p>A long ſlender necke declareth a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful euil mannered man, thicke and long: a furious, fearful, and ſtubburne perſon. A meane necke, a ſtronge and vertuous man, and apt to learning. A thick necke, ſheweth rude, barbarous, and vngentle
<pb facs="tcp:7828:67"/>perſons. Sharpe neck a ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. A ſhort neck raſhnes. A croked neck a couetous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The necke turned to the right ſide: ſheweth a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perat man. Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> left ſide, a hore maſter &amp; a fole.</p>
            <p>A great breſt is alway praiſed, a larg breſt doth repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Magnanimitie, bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and honeſtye. A little breaſt a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful perſon. A purſye or groſſe breaſte, an vngentle and cruel man.</p>
            <p>The paps hanging downe from the breſt, do ſhewe a violente man.</p>
            <p>A great belly, declareth an vndiſcrete foliſhe man, proude, and riotous. A lanke belly with a bigge breaſte, a man of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and counſel.</p>
            <p>A brode backe declareth gentleneſſe. The mean proportion both of the backe and breaſt, is alwaye commendable: a croked backe is token of a nigarde, and couetous perſone.</p>
            <p>Very long armes are ſigne of boldnes, honeſty, and ſtrength, ſhort armes a ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of diſcord and riot.</p>
            <p>The handes very ſhort doth ſignify a groſſe &amp; rude perſon, fat and fleſſhy with
<pb facs="tcp:7828:68"/>the fingers likewiſe inclined to thefte. Smal handes crafty men.</p>
            <p>The feteful of fleſh declareth foliſhnes, Smal and ſlender fete, hardneſſe.</p>
            <p>Slender legges ſhew ignorance, groſſe legges, boldnes and ſtrength. Large and ful of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>owes, fortitude, &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. Short &amp; fat legs, crueltye. Croked &amp; hollow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, is a token of very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> men. Soft and ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lling legges, euil ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nered men.</p>
            <p>The ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nne groſſe &amp; ſhort with a ſharp heele and fatte thighes, do prognoſticate madneſſe or frenſye to come or happen to that partie.</p>
            <p>Thus haue you here theſe briefe intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions to this art of <hi>Phiſiognomy,</hi> by the which a man may iudge the diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of other. Folowing herein <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> and <hi>Valla,</hi> who did the like, by whoſe help we haue performed herein that we may or can. Wherefore, if any man wil ſlaunder vs, let him know that we haue not written any commentaries, but a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious treatiſe of this ſcience, and thus an end.</p>
            <div type="introductions">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:68"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <hi>Briefe introductions</hi> upon the faces of the ſignes, what effect the Sunne doth worke in euerye houſe or manſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow that we haue fully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed &amp; alſo determined aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel to inſtruct, as to induce and allure the ſtudious and deſirous, to the ſtudye and knowledge of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> and that there be many things to be obſerued and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked therein, as the ſituation and placing of the houſes, and the iudgements of the <hi>Horoſcope:</hi> we thinke now onlye to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine neceſſary to intreate or ſpeake of the faces or triplicities of the ſignes, and of their worke and effect in euery degre. For the <hi>Sunne</hi> and euerye other Planet haue diuerſe and ſondry effectes in eche degre &amp; face, working one thinge in the firſt triplicity, another in the ſecond, and a far different and contrarye operation in the thirde face. The whiche that you may the better vnderſtande, euery ſigne
<pb facs="tcp:7828:69"/>is deuided into thirty degrees. The ſame thirty being parted again into .iii. parts, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt part or order to ten, doth make the firſt face or triplicity, &amp; al whiche cometh betwene ten &amp; twenty, is attribute to the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: &amp; that which remaineth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirty degre, is added to the third face. And in this manner muſic you deuide al the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſignes: and theſe degrees as thei in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in number, ſo do they in force and ſtrengthe. So towarde the ende they be of loſſe power then they were in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginninge or middeſie of the triplicitye, and ſpecially in the laſt faces or triplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Theſe notes and others we haue brieflye drawen or taken out of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Haly, Alcabitius, Firmicus</hi> and ſuche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Wherefore, if anye zoylous or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious perſone, wil obiecte or demaunde whye we ioyne theſe thinges to our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges: wee anſwere that thoſe learned menne did not fullye and diſtinctly write the whole effects, which a perfect Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logian mighte altogether do. But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to admoniſhe their owne Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and ſcholers then to teache others.
<pb facs="tcp:7828:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>And theſe thinges thus beinge touched, we wil procede to ſpeake of <hi>Aries.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Sunne in the firſte face of Aries. ♈.</head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Sunne</hi> in <hi>Aries,</hi> which is the firſt and principall ſigne, amongſte the twelue, and in the firſte tenne degrees of the ſame, dothe commonlye make thoſe whiche be then borne, red coulou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſmal viſaged, lanke and ſlender bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied, and leane, marked in the lefte ſote, or elbowe, hauinge manye frendes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting euil and louing al that is good.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond face whiche is from the tenth degre of <hi>Aries,</hi> to the twenty degre of the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, it maketh them blacke co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lored, the which blacknes is not reputed as any vice or deformity, but for a come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and great ciuilitye. They be alſo of a mean ciuility, angry, ſuſpitious, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful, and hartye, compaſſed and beſet with many ennemies which ſhal purſue him euen vnto death.</p>
                  <p>In the thirde face it maketh them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes red, inclining to a ſaffro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> colour ſolitary, and deuiſing craftes &amp; diſceites</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſun in the firſt face of Taurus.</hi> ♉</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:70"/>
                  <p>Maketh them that be borne apt or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, great eyed, and greate lips, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the necke, but very merye, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies occupied in riot and banketinge.</p>
                  <p>In the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d face, it maketh them wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and riotous, (but not ſo muche as in the firſt face) runners aboute countries, and vnſtedfaſt.</p>
                  <p>In the thirde face it cauſeth a colder complexion becauſe of <hi>Saturne</hi> whiche doth poſſeſſe this laſte face, and bringeth the paines or diſeaſes of the eares, belly, and thighes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The <hi>Sunne</hi> in the firſte face of <hi>Geminy.</hi> ♊</head>
                  <p>VVho ſo euer hapneth to be born the <hi>Sunne</hi> being in the firſte face of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> is for the moſt part of a meane ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wel bodied, euery membre decently compact, marked in the heade or knees, gentle, and painful, vnfortunate through women, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly without iſſue.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond face it doth miniſhe the ſtature, adding blacknes of colour, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the elbow or preuy members, and that whiche ſemeth to be deminiſhed or
<pb facs="tcp:7828:70"/>wanting in thother partes, is repaired &amp; fulfilled with eloquence.</p>
                  <p>In the declination of the thirde face, it maketh theim to decreaſe in honeſtye and the due proporcion of the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres, making them foliſhe, and inuentors and ſpreaders abrode of ieſtes &amp; vain trifles.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Sunne in Cancer</hi> ♋.</head>
                  <p>THey which are borne in the firſt ten degrees of <hi>Cancer,</hi> are comelye bothe of bodye and heere, narrowe browes, quicke and pregnant witted, marked in the right arme and thighes, hauynge a good ſpirite and diſpoſition, and plenty of frendes.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond face redde heeres, ſhort ſtature without any beard, and marked in the eyes.</p>
                  <p>In the third face it maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> groſſe and dull, with heery browes, ful of ytch, and as it were blowen or puffed vp in the face.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Sunne in Leo</hi> ♌.</head>
                  <p>SO in the firſt face of <hi>Leo,</hi> is the gift of life, and it maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a ſmal come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly body, reddy coloured, mixed with ſome
<pb facs="tcp:7828:71"/>white, rouling eyes, ſtraight bodye, ful of diſeaſes in their feete, &amp; ſpecially in age: famous and notable, ſimple, and beloued of the kinges and rulers of the earth.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond face it maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> large breaſted, the ſtones and priuy members ſlender, harty and honourable.</p>
                  <p>In the third face ſhort of ſtature, roſe coloured, mixed with white, vexed with much ſickneſſe, a whoremonger, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of women.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Sunne in Virgo.</hi> ♍</head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Sunne</hi> poſſeſſing the firſt face of <hi>Virgo,</hi> cauſeth a comely ſtature, high and tal body, a faire face, witty, prudence and quicke, curled heere, a player of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, with a quicke and ſhril voice, learned in many ſciences, but vnfertil &amp; barren in hauinge or bringinge forthe of children.</p>
                  <p>In the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d face it maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> likewiſe comly cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenanced, ſmal eyes, fair noſe, religious, learned, honeſt, without blame or reproche, and deſirous of praiſe.</p>
                  <p>Vnder the third face, ſimple, fair, apt, witty, prudent, and good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Sunne in the firſte face of Libra.</hi> ♎</head>
                  <p>BEing a ſigne of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſhape or form cauſeth a fayre face, a ſimple, painful and modeſt perſon, which ſhalbe woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the heade.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond face it maketh likewiſe a faire face, but blexe eied, or ſquint eyed, for they ſhal haue ſome default in them.</p>
                  <p>In the third face it maketh them ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, reuerent, and comely: in thend of this face it maketh them oftentimes of both kindes, and let them take hede they take no venemous thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſunne in Scorpio.</hi> ♏</head>
                  <p>CAuſeth them whiche are borne to be euel fauored, marked in the heade or ſhulders, or in the left fote or arme, large breſted, mery, &amp; pleſant in geuing checks or tauntes, ſobre, and diſcrete.</p>
                  <p>In the ſeconde face it cauſeth a great head, and a great babler, marked in the knees or backe.</p>
                  <p>And vnder y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> third face maketh a ſmal and litle ſtature, gogle eyed, a glotton or great eater, and a horemonger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Sunne in Sagittarius.</hi> ♐</head>
                  <p>MAketh them of a comely countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and tall ſtature, belonginge to the Courte, ſtudious and deſirous of good thinges.</p>
                  <p>Vnder the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d face it cauſeth a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; faire countenance &amp; ſtature, inclined to a ſaffron colour, thin browes, &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the breaſt.</p>
                  <p>In the third face tal and comly, large &amp; big breſted, marked in the breſt &amp; fote.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sunne in Capricorne.</hi> ♑</p>
                  <p>MAketh oftentimes a large breaſte, a tender and ſoft perſon, of a compete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtature, but ſomwhat black colored, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the elbow or breſt craftye.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond face fair, marked in the left arme, but if the natiuity be by night, it maketh them malicious, longe noſed, and quicke witted.</p>
                  <p>In the thirde face it cauſeth a comely body, a citrine face, marked in the arme or knee, angrye, louelye, and a louer of women.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Sunne in the firſt face of Aquarius.</hi> ♒</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THe <hi>ſunne</hi> in the firſt face of <hi>Aquarius</hi> maketh a comely bodi &amp; face, marked in the breſt or left fote, alſo benigne, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy and gentle to be ſpoken to, tractable, &amp; familiar amongſt men.</p>
                  <p>Vnder the ſecond face, it maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very long red face, marked in the backe or elbow, endomaged with many vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and tribulations.</p>
                  <p>In the third face it cauſeth a ſhort ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a roſe coloured countenaunce, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnder the elbow, and a louer of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: but if it happen him to be borne in the laſt degree, he ſhal not only be diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary diſpoſed in the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the bodye, but in all his actions and doinges.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Sunne being found in Piſces.</hi> ♓</head>
                  <p>CAuſeth a ſoft body, white, bigge breſt, comely beard, faire forhed, clear ſkin, large &amp; fayre eyes, ful of fleſhe &amp; honeſt.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond face, an equal and ſhort ſtature, blacke bearde, thin heared, nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and mery.</p>
                  <p>In the third face it maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and decent in al members, and geueth
<pb facs="tcp:7828:73"/>alſo clerenes of ſound or voice.</p>
                  <p>This alſo we haue iudged worthy to be noted and marked, that in artificiall <hi>Aſtrology</hi> there be certaine formes or ſignes, whiche do cauſe greatneſſe or bigneſſe, as <hi>Leo, Virgo, Sagittarius:</hi> and certaine which cauſe diuination or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king leſſe, as <hi>Piſces, Cancer, Capricorne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The beginninges alſo of <hi>Aries, Leo,</hi> and <hi>Taurus,</hi> do cauſe bodyes to tende to groſeneſſe and ſtrengthe, the endes of the ſame, do contrariwiſe cauſe leannes, ſlenderneſſe, and debilitie: likewiſe the beginninges of <hi>Gemini, Scorpio,</hi> and <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> cauſe leanneſſe and debility, and the endes of the ſame, groſneſſe, and ſtrength, but <hi>Virgo, Libra</hi> and <hi>Sagittarius</hi> cauſe equalitye and good proportion. <hi>Taurus, Scorpius,</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> as <hi>Halye</hi> writeth, do woorke and cauſe a diuerſe and vnequall proportion of the bodye. For they whiche are borne in the daye, are clearer then they whiche are borne in the nyghte: for the nyghte doothe helpe the Planettes, ſignifying obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and blackeneſſe. Alſo the <hi>Moone</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:7828:73"/>coniunction with <hi>Mercury,</hi> in the houre of natiuitie, and not beinge aſcendent: cauſeth the fallinge ſickeneſſe, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallye if <hi>Saturne</hi> be in anye angle in the day birth: or <hi>Mars</hi> in the nighte birthe. Alſo <hi>Saturnus</hi> in anye of the angles, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the nighte or daye birthe, cauſeth madneſſe, and ſpeciallye when <hi>Cancer, Virgo</hi> or <hi>Piſces,</hi> are founde in any of the angles. More ouer, <hi>Saturne</hi> in the houſes of the lightes: that is to ſay, the <hi>Sunne</hi> or <hi>Mone,</hi> whiche are <hi>Cancer</hi> and <hi>Leo,</hi> it be tokeneth the paſſion or hurt of the eyes.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ſignes, <hi>Aries, Cancer, Scorpius Capricorne</hi> and <hi>Piſces:</hi> do ſignify &amp; cauſe biles, leproſy, red ſpottes, itches, ſcurffes, deafeneſſe, ſtuttinge, baldeneſſe, and a ſmal bearde.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cancer, Scorpius,</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> are ſignes of manye ſonnes or men children. Alſo theſe ſignes betoken the honeſty of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, their religion &amp; puritye of life, <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, Leo, Aquarius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe ſignes haue reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and are called reaſonable ſignes, <hi>Gemini, Virgo, Libra,</hi> the firſt part of <hi>Sagittarius</hi> &amp; al <hi>Aquarius</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:74"/>
                  <p>Signes mouing to anger and ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, are <hi>Aries, Leo,</hi> and <hi>Scorpio.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>More ouer, <hi>Gemini, Virgo,</hi> and <hi>Libra</hi> cauſe great, loude, &amp; ſhril voices, <hi>Cancer, Scorpio,</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> are dombe, &amp; without voice or ſounde.</p>
                  <p>There be thre planets which do geue riches: that is to ſaie, <hi>Iupiter,</hi> the <hi>Sunne,</hi> and <hi>Venus.</hi> The <hi>Sunne</hi> alſo geueth wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>Mercury</hi> eloquence, and <hi>Venus</hi> goodlye vtterance or pronunciation.</p>
                  <p>There be alſo three ſignes oriental or of theaſt. <hi>Aries</hi> is the heart of theaſt. <hi>Leo</hi> the ſecond triplicitie and the lift part of theaſt, &amp; <hi>Sagittarius</hi> his right part or ſide <hi>Capricorne</hi> is the heart of the Southe, <hi>Taurus</hi> the liſt ſide, &amp; <hi>Virgo</hi> the righte. <hi>Libra</hi> is the heart of the weſt, <hi>Aquarius</hi> the liſt ſide, and <hi>Gemint</hi> the right.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cancer</hi> is the heart of the north, <hi>Scorpio</hi> his lifte parte, and laſte of al <hi>Piſces</hi> his right ſide.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore, if you wil knowe to what ende this reſpecte or diſpoſition of the ſignes doth belonge or attaine, you ſhal briefly hear. We haue ſaid there be thre
<pb facs="tcp:7828:74"/>ſignes oriental, or of the eaſt, three meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dional, three perteininge to the northe, &amp; three to the weſt. The oriental ſignes profite vs, if that thei riſyng, &amp; the ſunne beinge in them, we order &amp; direct al our doinges to that coaſt, parte, or place.</p>
                  <p>As if thou w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lt leade an healthful lyfe, ſlepe quietly, proſpere in children if thou be maried, or haue any thing to ſuccede or go forwarde, if thou wilt ſell or make any bargaine, or hope for any honour or gaine, or any ſuch like: to directe al your doinges toward that place, in the which the ſines hauing reſpect to thoſe things, are ſituate or placed. So contrariwiſe, if that we feare the euill ſucceſſe of anye of thoſe thinges, the contrarye ſignes are to be eſchued. And in this ſort maye you ſudge of the other ſignes. Alſo wee haue made a larger diſcription hereof, where as we make mention of the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie &amp; nature of the houſes. Thus haue we here no leſſe copiouſlye then brieflye diſcribed the nature of the faces of the ſignes, neither do I perceaue how they coulde more compendiouſlye haue bene
<pb facs="tcp:7828:75"/>touched, not iudgyng it of great effect to haue taried longe herein with great cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. At be it, they be neceſſarye vnto <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> yet are they not of ſuch force (that as is ſaide in the prouerbe, bothe ſhippe, and helme were to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto them) or that the hole rule, and gouernance of <hi>Aſtrology</hi> did depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d on theim. For as they can not well be left vnknowen, yet are they with ſuche a moderation to be learned and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, that vpon the knowledge of them a man oughte not to iudge him ſelfe by and by an <hi>Aſtronomer.</hi> Wherfore, who ſoeuer thou art that ſemeſt to be prope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe or apte to this ſcience,<note place="margin">mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n of ctor.</note> I warne thee to vſe moderation, and to do nothing raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, neither vnaduiſedlye to geue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of anye man his natiuitie. There are ſo many thinges whereby we mate be diſcetued, as the wiſdome and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>on of the man, the diſpenſation of O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, and our vncertaine iudgemente. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>or example, it maye be that a man home vnder <hi>Aries,</hi> bee verye fierce and angrie, who waiyng wyth hym ſelf the
<pb facs="tcp:7828:75"/>foulnes of the vice, doth moderate &amp; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his anger. If I then ſhould iudge this man an angrye or teſtye man, who would not mocke me and laughe me to ſcorne, albeit nature and deſtinye do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thereunto: yet notwithſtandynge the ſentence and iudgemente is ſo to be tempered and ruled, that without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect reſpect had to all thinges, thou vtter nothinge raſhely. The whiche if you do not take hede of, be aſſured you ſhal nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prognoſticate or foreſhewe anye truth: but alſo become a mockyng ſtocke to all men. And this I do euerye where admoniſhe you of, becauſe I haue kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen manſe to haue erred and bene fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye diſceiued: who thinkyng them ſelfes ſure, haue bene (as they ſaye) ſixtene fote of from the marke or pricke.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="rules">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:76"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Certaine cannons or rules</hi> vpon ſicknes or diſeaſes, bi what meanes the patientes may be cured and holpen by the aſpectes of the ſignes.</head>
               <head type="sub">The preface.</head>
               <p>THE foliſhe and vnaduiſed ſorte of <hi>Phiſitions</hi> which in theſe our daies we ſee ſo much to aduaunce them ſelfes, and claime vnto them ſelues the ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy ouer vs, albeit they be commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded bi their auctours not to take in hand to cure any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without hauing reſpect vnto the ſtarres. So farre are they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from the true knowledge of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, which are ignoraunt of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> that they ought not rightly to be called <hi>Phiſitions,</hi> but diſceauers. Howbeit, it is now come to this poynt, that amongeſt an hundred you ſhal ſcarſely finde one, the which can truely diſcerne what time euerye medicine ought to be miniſtred. The which is no maruaile, for how can they finde any time to beſtow or occupy
<pb facs="tcp:7828:76"/>them ſelues in <hi>Aſtrologye,</hi> whiche haue no leaſure to read <hi>Galene</hi> or <hi>Hipocrates,</hi> but do all thinge a head or vnaduiſedlye by certaine preſcript receiptes. Like as there was a certaine (no ſimple man) at <hi>Moguntia,</hi> whom you would haue iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to haue bene the thirde <hi>Cato</hi> or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Galene,</hi> if that grauitie would help any thinge thereunto. This man being moſte rude and vnlearned, vied two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptes, from whence he had drawen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I knowe not. There was in them. <hi>3.</hi> ſz. of <hi>Elleborns,</hi> or ſo much <hi>feamonye,</hi> to purge the wombe. Theſe he miniſtred bi courſe, without hauing reſpect either to the completion or ſickenes: by the which vaine trifles he ſcraped together ſo much money, that being deade, he left behinde him. <hi>3000.</hi> gilders. He iudged the whole effect of this ſcience to conſíſt in loſinge of the bealy. Such effect hath au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thoritie and boldenes in <hi>Phiſicke.</hi> Theſe ſorte of rude and groſſe men the which diſdaine to learne, we wil neither admoniſh nor yet reduce into the right way. But vnto others whiche intende hereafter to bee
<pb facs="tcp:7828:77"/>
                  <hi>Phiſitions,</hi> we wil preſcribe certain rules whereby ſetting apart al olde vaine tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, they maie learne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue to helpe the patient or diſeafed. For it hath-bene many times experimented and proued, that that which many <hi>Phiſitions</hi> coulde not cure or remedye with their greateſt and ſtrongeſt medicins: the <hi>Aſtronomer</hi> hathe brought to paſſe with one ſimple herbe, by obſeruinge the mouyng of the ſignes, the which we haue wholly deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Canons.</p>
               <p>THe firſt Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. There be four ſignes the which beholde or gouerne the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward partes of a man, the which Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions do cal the ſpiritual me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres. Thoſe are <hi>Cancer, Leo, Virgo,</hi> and <hi>Libra.</hi> Of theſe <hi>Cancer</hi> beholdeth the Liuer, the lunges, and the heart ſtringes. <hi>Leo</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth the ſtomacke, &amp; the mouth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Virgo</hi> the nether part of the ſtomack, the bealy, the midriffe, and the bowels. <hi>Libra</hi> hath reſpect to the nether part of the bealy, the loynes, and the nauell.</p>
               <p>The .ii. Canon. <hi>Cancer</hi> which goner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:7828:77"/>the lunges, engendreth the cough, the pertiſes, and pleuriſie. <hi>Leo</hi> cauſeth impoſtumes, taunders, feuers, and peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. <hi>Virgo</hi> the ſwelling of the bealye, the dropſy, and hardnes of the belly, and collicke. <hi>Libra</hi> cauſeth the exulceration of the bowels, pain in the bealy, &amp; about the ſmall of the backe: and chieflye if the ſignes aforeſaide happen into thoſe houſes whiche are naturally euil. Such as are the. <hi>6.</hi> houſe, the. <hi>8.</hi> &amp;. <hi>12.</hi> houſe from the aſcendent or <hi>Horoſcope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The .iii. Canon. He whiche is borne vnder <hi>Taurus</hi> for the moſt part ſhalbe in peril by poyſon, witcheraft, or the colick: and ſpecially in the fatall yeres, whiche are the .vi.viii.xviii.xx.xxiii.xliiii. accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the reuolution of euerye twelfe yere, beginninge at the .viii. yeare of the natiuitie. And becauſe that <hi>Taurus</hi> doth gouerne the throte, thei do alſo refer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the ſquinancy &amp; al impoſtumes &amp; biles which happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the throte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which when the expert Phiſition dothe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande and know, let him take hede that he miniſter not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vnaduiſedly.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:78"/>
               <p>For this is almoſte a general rule, that the <hi>Sunne,</hi> or rather the <hi>Mone</hi> beinge in any ſigne which beholdeth any member vered or diſeaſed during that reuolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ther be no medicine miniſtred therunto, or els that it be miniſtred in ſuche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>te, not to cure or heale, but to comforte and nouriſh, leaſt that it decline into a worſe eſtate, vnto ſuch time as the <hi>Sunne</hi> be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued out of that ſigne.</p>
               <p>The. <hi>4.</hi> Canon. They whyche are much vexed or troubled with the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulion or ſtone, or with any ſuch kind of diſeaſes, moſte commonly are borne, the <hi>Sunne</hi> being in <hi>Aries</hi> or <hi>Gemini.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The. <hi>5.</hi> Canon. They that haue <hi>Piſces</hi> in their aſcendent, or are born vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Piſces,</hi> are in daunger of hote infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: as hote feuers, knawynge of the bealye, and poyſon, becauſe of <hi>Libra</hi> and his lord of the .viii. houſe. Theſe diſeaſes ſhall partlye happen by harlottes, and euil women, and ſpecially in the. <hi>44.56.78.</hi> yeres, in the which he ſhalbe in great daunger of death. Wherefore, the wiſe <hi>Phiſition</hi> oughte carefullye to obſerue
<pb facs="tcp:7828:78"/>thoſe things. There be alſo certaine euil times &amp; yeres of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s life, which are at euery ſeuen yeres e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h: ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euery ſeuenth yere is perilous. Wherfore, if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wilt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the daies of thy life: as ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thou comeſt to euery .vii. or .ix. yere, (if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> geue any credit to <hi>Marſilius ficinꝰ</hi> or <hi>Firmicꝰ</hi>) dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly conſult with an <hi>Aſtronomer,</hi> from whence, and by what meanes any pearil or daunger maye happen or come vnto thee, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either go vnto a <hi>Phiſition</hi> or vſe diſcreſſion and tempera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and by that meanes thou maiſt defer &amp; prolong thy natural ende, throughe the rules of <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> &amp; the help of the <hi>Phiſition.</hi> Neither bee aſhamed to enquire of the <hi>Phiſition,</hi> what is thy natural diet: &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Aſtronomer,</hi> what ſtarre dothe moſle ſupport and fauour thy life, and to ſe in what aſpect he is with the <hi>Mone.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, in the beginninge of thy ſickeneſſe to behold the <hi>Sunne</hi> in the daye, and the <hi>Moone</hi> in the nighte. They, if they be letted or hindred, there muſt be great hede and diligence be had vpon the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. The like is to be feared in al ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:7828:79"/>when the <hi>Moone</hi> and the lorde of the aſcendent be letted in the .viii. houſe, whiche is called the houſe of death. For in ſuche caſe it is paſt all hope, without the great diligence and labour of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert and wiſe Phiſition. Theſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſuch like thinges, the wiſe and learned Phiſition oughte diligentlye to obſerue and take hede vnto.</p>
               <p>The .vi. Canon. <hi>Leo</hi> in theyght houſe engendreth to him that is borne vnder <hi>Capricorne</hi> theſe kinde of diſeaſes: that is to ſaye, knawynge of the ſtomacke, the plureſie, the coughe, inflamation of the liuer, &amp; impoſtumes of the ſtomacke. Wherfore in curyng or helpyng therof, you muſt eſchue wedenſdaye, bicauſe of ♊, the ſixt houſe Sunday, becauſe of ♌ in the .viii. houſe, and thurſdaye, becauſe of <hi>Sagittarius</hi> in the .xii. houſe.</p>
               <p>The .vii. Canon. <hi>Cancer</hi> cauſeth the inflamation of the lunges, with a feruët ague. The <hi>ſunne</hi> beinge in <hi>ſagittarius,</hi> engendreth likewiſe the Ethica, &amp; ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of the lunges. But and if <hi>Saturnus</hi> be in <hi>ſagittarius,</hi> it cauſeth the ſwellyng
<pb facs="tcp:7828:79"/>of the feete, and the goute. <hi>Saturnus</hi> in <hi>cancer</hi> cauſeth the payne of the coddes, ſtones, and priuy members.</p>
               <p>The .viii. Canon. <hi>Scorpius</hi> engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth the gowte in the hande the <hi>ſciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> and ſometime the paine in the head. If <hi>Saturne</hi> bee in <hi>ſcorpio,</hi> it cauſeth alſo payne vnder the ancley. Wherefore let this diet be vſed, not to waſh their heads vppon a tueſdaye, neither vſe any hotie bathes, the ſunne beinge in <hi>Aries,</hi> leſt they fall into a continual headatche, for then they ſhall be in greate daunger of freneſye or madneſſe.</p>
               <p>And for becauſe that the euill dayes, monethes, and yeres, are to be obſerued and taken heede of: let theim abſtayne ſpeciallye from hotte thinges. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate dayes for the cure and healpe of ſuche as are infected wyth that kinde of melancholye, are thurſdaye, mondaye, and Sondaye. The infortunate dayes are tueſdaye and wedenſdaye. And for ſo muche as <hi>Scorpio</hi> dothe beholde the priuy membres, thei ought not to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred vnto the ſunne being in <hi>Scorpio.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:80"/>
               <p>The. <hi>9.</hi> Canon. They that haue <hi>Virgo</hi> in their <hi>Horoſcope,</hi> or els are borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Virgo,</hi> for the mooſte parte haue the natural infirmitie of the legges or fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſwollen: the legges runnyng with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte and filthye matter, or els the eye liddes or chekes full of pimples. In like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, great paines in the head throughe the exhalation of humours out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ete vnto the heade. The which paines are ſone dela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed and appeaſed by cutting the ſwelling of the feete. And ſo muche the rather if <hi>Saturn</hi> be in <hi>Virgo</hi> at the time of natiuitie. Wherfore if thou diligently conſider it, thou ſhalt perceiue and ſee it to be a natural diſeaſe, and for the moſt part ineuitable. And therfore onlye to be au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ided and put of by the natural obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the ſignes. Such ought to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from hot houſes, whether they be to waſhe or ſweate in, which if they can not altogether eſchue, let them abſtaine Tueſdaies and Saturdaies, and the euel monethes &amp; yeares before preſcribed: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> at thoſe times more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at anye other, they do moſt vehemently pour out
<pb facs="tcp:7828:80"/>their miſchief and poyſon. Let them alſo refraine from al Autumnal frutes.</p>
               <p>The. <hi>10.</hi> Canon. The infortunate dayes vnto ſuch as are borne vnder <hi>Leo</hi> are Saterday and Thurſday, the which thing muſt be taken hede of in their diet: for all ſharpe and pepered meates, are hurtful for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Moreouer, they may take no drinckes or purgations. And in like caſe when the <hi>Sunne</hi> remoueth oute of <hi>Leo,</hi> and cometh vnto <hi>Capricorne</hi> or <hi>Piſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces,</hi> they muſt abſtein fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al kind of ſalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh and diminution or letting of bloud.</p>
               <p>The. <hi>11.</hi> Canon. If that any manne chaunce to fal ſicke, the <hi>Sunne</hi> beinge in <hi>Aries,</hi> and thou be admitted or called for <hi>Phiſition:</hi> vnderſtand that he in eſpecial, engendreth the paines of the heade, and deafeneſſe, therof with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes of ſight. Wherfore, beware that thou miniſter no hote bathes or ſtewes, becauſe of <hi>Mars,</hi> and ſpecially in October, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>ſunne</hi> doth poſſeſſe <hi>Scorpio,</hi> neither geue him in his diet, any Mutton, Rammes fleſh, or Lambe, neither ſuffre him to waſhe his heade vpon the Tueſdaies, wedenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes
<pb facs="tcp:7828:81"/>becauſe of <hi>Mercury</hi> being Lord of <hi>Virgo</hi> in the .vi. houſe, whereas <hi>Mars</hi> al ſo doth priuely reioyſe, and <hi>Scorpius</hi> in the eight houſe, for then thei prolong the ſicknes, not only bicauſe the .vi. houſe is manſion of ſickeneſſe: as alſo that <hi>Virgo</hi> is a ſigne colde and drye, earthlye and <hi>Melancholye.</hi> Not withſtandinge, this hope remaineth that the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhal not depart. And al be it <hi>Scorpio,</hi> as is afor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide, be in theight houſe whiche is the manſion of death, becauſe that <hi>Mars</hi> is Lord of the ſame ſigne, it preuaileth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, for no euil Planet is noyſome or hurtful in his proper manſion or houſe: and ſuche kinde of menne mooſte of all, ſhall be withoute pearill of the ſwearde. Wherfore after his recouery or amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you muſte warne the patiente that he do not take in hande anye ioure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, the <hi>Sunne</hi> beinge in <hi>Piſces,</hi> whiche is the. <hi>12.</hi> houſe from the <hi>Horoſcope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or elſſe not to haue to do with nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries or ſcribes, grauere, or gold ſmithes. Alſo that he abſtaine from wemen, and
<pb facs="tcp:7828:81"/>horſſes. For by al theſe thinges infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or ſickeneſſe maye happen vnto him, by reaſon of the .vi. houſe, whiche is the houſe of ſickeneſſe, and chiefly in Auguſt the <hi>Sunne</hi> hauinge his courſe in <hi>Virgo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The. <hi>12.</hi> Canon. In like maner, the noumber of the yeares of the pacient are diligentlye to be obſerued and marked, for alwaies euerye .vii. and .ix. yeare, are mortal and deadly, and are called of the <hi>Aſtronomers:</hi> the perillous time of a mans life at euery .vii. yeares end. The cauſe thereof, is the greate mutacion and chaunge of the bodies, that happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in thoſe yeres. For <hi>Saturne</hi> whiche in the other yeares is farre diſtaunte from vs, is then ioyned to the <hi>Moone,</hi> which is the loweſt planet of al. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſſe obſerue in the reuoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the yeares, the aſpectes of thoſe Planettes: and thereby iudge whether there be anye daunger towarde the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiente or not, or whether <hi>Saturne</hi> or <hi>Mars</hi> which alſo gouerneth euery .ix. yeare, be in ſtrengthe or power to woorke their
<pb facs="tcp:7828:82"/>malice vpon vs, or elſſe if that any good or fauorable Planet, haue the rule or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer him. And by this meanes y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt not only put away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſicknes: but alſo through thengines of Aſtronomi, de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer and pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong the fatal end and death.</p>
               <p>The. <hi>13.</hi> Canon. Alwaies the diet of the patient is to be enquired, ſecondlye the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> of the natiuity, and then by a figure erect to beholde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtars of the planets, &amp; by the ſituation of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their houſes to know their ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth &amp; operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the cauſe of thinfirmitie, &amp; the lord of the birth: &amp; ſo by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary qualities of the ſignes, to driue awaye the diſeaſe, as we wil declare hereafter by exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples.</p>
               <p>The. <hi>14.</hi> Canon. Furthermore, you muſt note and marke euery .vii. day, and the courſes. For therby is life or deathe to be loked or hoped for, but whiche be thoſe <hi>Cretical</hi> dayes, we haue referred to be learned of the <hi>Phiſition.</hi> As for as much as examples to moſt inſtructe and teach, we haue anexed one. It may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen peraduenture, that in the beginning of the ſicken<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Moone</hi> be in <hi>Aries,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:82"/>which is a hote and drye ſigne, &amp; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to his nature, dothe inflame the diſeaſes. Here thou ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt admoniſh the ſicke perſon to be paciente, and that his paine wil be delayed at the .vii. daye, at which time the <hi>mone</hi> wilbe remoned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Cancer.</hi> For <hi>Cancer</hi> beinge colde and moiſte, and being a quartile aſpecte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Aries:</hi> except the ſickneſſe be very fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, will moderate the ſame throughe his coldnes and moiſtures. The whiche thing if thou diligently attend &amp; marke, thou ſhalt ſone perceiue and vnderſtand. And in like ſort thou muſt worke b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the other ſignes, conſidering how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i ſignes of like nature, diſeaſes are augmented and increaſed: and by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traries, they be cured and holpen.</p>
               <p>The. <hi>15.</hi> Canon. In likewiſe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde number of daies is to be obſerued and marked, whiche is the. <hi>14.</hi> daye, the whiche dothe geue a certaine and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate iudgemente, by meanes of the ful <hi>Moone,</hi> not ſo much for the <hi>Criſis</hi> as for the influence of the <hi>Mone</hi> beinge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in oppoſition. As <hi>Aries,</hi> &amp; <hi>Libra, Taurus,</hi> and <hi>Scorpio.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:83"/>
               <p>The. <hi>16.</hi> Canon. The medicines the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues haue likewiſe their propre ſignes, neither are they indifferentlye to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred at all times. For ſome ſerue for gargles, ſome for ſuffumigations, and other ſome ſorpotions or drinks. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to auoide tediouſneſſe, I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende all theſe in oure Canon. The <hi>Mone</hi> being in <hi>Aries, Leo</hi> and <hi>Sagitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> it is good to corroborate and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth the vertue attractiue in a man.</p>
               <p>Vnder <hi>Virgo</hi> and <hi>Taurus</hi> the vertue retentiue, the digeſtiue in <hi>Gemini, Libra</hi> and <hi>Capricorne,</hi> gargiles, vomettes, and ſuffumigations are to be miniſtred, the <hi>Mone</hi> being in <hi>Aries,</hi> and ſometime on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye gargles in <hi>Taurus, Laxatiues</hi> by drincke in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> by <hi>electuari</hi> in ♋, by pilles (if you will) in <hi>Piſces,</hi> in <hi>Gemini</hi> and ♒ al confortable medicines is to be receiued and taken. In <hi>Libra</hi> or <hi>Scorpio,</hi> ſuppoſitories or gliſters.</p>
               <p>The. <hi>18.</hi> Canon. In the miniſtringe of purgations, there is greate reſpect to be had vnto the <hi>Mone,</hi> and her aſpectes.
<pb facs="tcp:7828:83"/>For ſhe beinge in <hi>Cancer,</hi> and hauynge a trine or ſextile aſpecte with <hi>Venus,</hi> it is good to pourge cholere, hauinge the lyke aſpectes with the <hi>Sunne:</hi> is good to pourge flegme, and with <hi>Iupiter</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholye. either by pilles or by gobbets, called of the phiſitians <hi>Boli.</hi> But if thou wilte pourge by drinkes: vſe the ſame aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectes in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> and likewiſe in <hi>Piſces</hi> for miniſtring of pilles. And if that two Planettes at one time be in the aſpectes aforeſaide with the mone, two purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be taken at once. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, if the <hi>Mone</hi> be at one time in a trine or ſextile aſpecte with <hi>Venus</hi> &amp; the <hi>Sun,</hi> you may pourge bothe Choler &amp; flegme together.</p>
               <p>The. <hi>19.</hi> Canon. Suche as haue in the roote of their natiuity, <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Aries,</hi> or on his triplicitye, are colericke, for the moſt part indaunger of hot feuers, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of cholere, phreneſi, puſhes or biles co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of blud, ſcuruy itch, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges, and ſuche diſeaſes as conſume
<pb facs="tcp:7828:84"/>and eat the fleſh, the holy fire. The which diſeaſes, if they can not vrterly be auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and eſchued the <hi>Phiſition</hi> or <hi>ſurgean</hi> muſt take dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e that he may driue awaye the diſeaſe by the rules of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſignes before expreſſed.</p>
               <p>The. <hi>20.</hi> Canon. The like is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande of al thoſe with <hi>Mercury</hi> euill placed in the houſe of <hi>Mars,</hi> the whiche when thou perceiueſt in anye natiuitie: iudge therby hote feuers, pimples riſing of bloud, the canker, the kinges euel, and holy fire, darkeneſſe of the eyes, ſuffoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and moreouer, horrible and fearful thoughts &amp; verations of the minde. Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept there come any temperament vnto the <hi>Mone,</hi> either in the ſignes or places appointed vnto <hi>Venus,</hi> and ſpeciallye in collericke men.</p>
               <p>The. <hi>22.</hi> Canon. The infirmities of the phlegmaticke, are of an other ſorte: for vnto them happeneth moſt comonlye the agewes called <hi>Quotidians,</hi> and are much vexed with cold, the whiche is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by the Vrine, which for the moſte part is thicke and raw. Wherfore ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:7828:84"/>muſt vſe exerciſe and laboure, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from al fat fleſh and ſwine fleſhe, alſo from cheſe and milke, and from the marrowe and braines of be aſtes.</p>
               <p>The. <hi>23.</hi> Canon. <hi>Saturne</hi> with the <hi>Mone</hi> engendreth the fallen ſickeneſſe, blacke chollere, leproſy and fiſtula. Alſo the morphew, goute, and oftentimes ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine panges.</p>
               <p>The which diſeaſes when they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen are leaſurelye and gentellye to be dealt withal, neither maiſt thou in ſuche caſe ſtriue againſte the Planets: excepte the medicine be ſuch as will endeuoure with al force and ſtrengthe, to expel and driue away the ſickeneſſe, and pul it vp cleane by the rotes. Alſo, if anye man be borne, at the time of the coniunction of the <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>Mone:</hi> alwaies that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity is iudged euil, for it maketh men when thei come to age, daungerouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted as it were with euil ſpirites, to be ſickely, enclined to the falling ſickeneſſe, to madneſſe, and ſuch kinde of diſeaſes, as may hardly and difficultlye be cured by the Phiſition.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:85"/>
               <p>The. <hi>24.</hi> Cannon. You maye alſo iudge by the courſe of the <hi>Sunne,</hi> the ſickeneſſe whiche we are in daunger of, if that ye marke the month in which the man is born. As for example. The man borne vnder <hi>Scorpio,</hi> ſhall be endoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the diſeaſe of the ſhoulders, the goute in the handes, and the contracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or conuulſion of the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds or fingers. If it be a woman, it cauſeth the paine in the ſplene and ſtomacke. Likewiſe, they which are borne vnder <hi>Cancer,</hi> ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vered with a drye ſcuruy itche, or rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſkin, biles, and puſhes. The we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with knawyng in the bowels, and pearils by waters. <hi>Taurus</hi> bringeth the infirmities aboute the throate, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other vexatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the body: &amp; ſpecially in the euil monethes &amp; yeres preſcribed. Alſo <hi>Leo</hi> cauſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paines of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomack. And <hi>Aquarius</hi> engendreth quotidian fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, as we haue briefly touched before.</p>
               <p>The. <hi>25.</hi> Canon. This is alſo to be noted no leſſe profitable vnto the ſicke manne then to the Phiſition, that is to ſaye: if that the patiente haue <hi>Saturne</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:85"/>or <hi>Mars</hi> in the ſeuenthe houſe, it is not conuenient to meddle, neither with phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition nor Phiſicke: althoughe the Lorde of the houſe, be neuer ſo vnfortunate, for ſo <hi>Galene</hi> thoughte it meete. Alſo if the Phiſition be <hi>Saturnine</hi> or <hi>Mertiall,</hi> ſuche as is the patiente: It is approued and knowen, that theſe kinde of menne are borne for the deſtruction of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde. For it is vnpoſſible that they ſhoulde euer cure or helpe, or bringe any thinge proſperouſlye to paſſe, excepte peraduenture amongeſt prophane and ruſticall people. Suche one we haue knowen, a man ſurelye well learned, and in greate reputation amongeſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble menne, in whome there wanted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge as touchinge the arte or ſcience, howe be it beynge admitted eyther to prieſtes, noble men, or eccleſiaſticall ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, his labour and knowledge was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies fruſtrate &amp; in vaine, and brought the moſt part of them to their ende: but contrarywiſe amongeſt the prophane and rude ſorte. he did cures withoute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye difficultye or paine. Hereby you
<pb facs="tcp:7828:86"/>may perceiue as wel in this as in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges, of what force and ſtrength the planets are. And this dare I be bolde to profeſſe, that who ſo euer hathe <hi>Mars</hi> conioyned with <hi>Venus</hi> in the .vi. houſe, that he ſhalbe an excellente <hi>Phiſition.</hi> And ſuche kinde of men, oughte not to geue them ſelues to anye other kinde of learninge or knowledge. I coulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe vnto certaine graue men, <hi>Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> witneſſes hereof: vnto whome it is a ready and eaſy matter to cure &amp; helpe: yea, euen without any paine or labour. And againe, other ſome vnto whome it is ſo difficult and hard, that withal their poſſible endeuour, they can ſcarſly bring any thing to paſſe, whoſe names we wil kepe vnder ſilence, leaſt we may ſeme to backbite or ſlaunder any man. Thus we haue briefly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not hereby to expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all thinges whiche can not be done in ſo fewe wordes: but to miniſter occaſion vnto <hi>Phiſitions,</hi> that beholding and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the vtilitie and profit of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy,</hi> hey may with their hole power and endeuour embrace the ſame, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:7828:86"/>learne not only by the preſcript rules of men to helpe the diſeaſed: but alſo by their owne wit and engine to put away the diſeaſes, euen without medicines. For euery ſicke man is not of that ſorte that he can beare ſalues or medicines. For ſome by diet, and others by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations of the ſignes maie be cured and holpen. Scorne vs who will, we verelye haue written theſe thinges of a ſincere minde and affection, intendyng ſhortlye to ſet forth greater things. But firſt we thought it good to declare the things in general: and afterwarde the ſome and effect wheron the matter dependeth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:7828:87"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A compe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dious</hi> diſcription of <hi>Naturall Aſtrologye,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo briefely handeled before. Made by, <hi>Iohn Indagine</hi> Prieſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt of all and chiefelye, it is mete to reſell and put of the obiections of ſuche as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecte and ſaic: that beſidethe <hi>Sunne</hi> and the <hi>Mone</hi> we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute verie little or nothinge at all to the other Planets, but do collocate and ſet the whole ſumme &amp; power of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logye</hi> in them two onelye. Wherefore let euerie man vnderſtande and knowe, as muche vertue and force to be in them two, as in all the other. And that the <hi>Sunne</hi> hathe the whole power and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernance in the daie, and the <hi>Moone</hi> in the night, ſo that it is not neadefull to
<pb facs="tcp:7828:87"/>haue reſpecte to anye of the other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nettes. And this is the onely difference betwene naturall and arificiall <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logye,</hi> that that thinge whiche artificial <hi>Aſtrology</hi> dothe by the ſeueral obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of euerye Planet and <hi>Horoſcope:</hi> the ſame doth natural <hi>Aſtrologye</hi> bring to paſſe by the onely obſeruation of the motion of the <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>Mone.</hi> Or els they are ſo knitte and toyned together, that the one without the other can not well be learned or vnderſtande. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he ſhall not lofe his laboure whiche ſhall ioyne them bothe together, as well for the learnynge, as for the pleaſure of them: for the naturall hathe ſomewhat more delectation then the artificiall, albeit the other ſeme the better. But now we wil define what a houſe is.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7828:88"/>
            <p>A Houſe is a certaine ſpace in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deuided by certain degrees, by the which the planets haue their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo <hi>Metaphorically</hi> called. For as in a houſe there be many mantions: ſo euery planet hath his proper place in the heauen or firmament, by the whiche they do moue, and in the which they be reſident and ſituate. And it is called the diſcription or diuiſton of the ſignes by. <hi>30</hi> degrees, for euerie houſe or ſigne hathe <hi>30.</hi> degrees.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:88"/>
               <head>The number of the houſes.</head>
               <p>AS the <hi>Aſtronomers</hi> do make menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in their common Rithmes, there be .xii. houſes, the whiche wee will here aſcribe with their interpretations.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The firſt is interpreted the houſe of life</item>
                  <item>The .ii. the houſe of faculties or ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, called alſo of thimportunity of the place, the gate of hell.</item>
                  <item>The .iii. is the mancion of brethren.</item>
                  <item>The .iiii. beinge the bottome of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and the angle of the earth, is the houſe of parentage.</item>
                  <item>The .v. is the pleaſure of <hi>Venus,</hi> the houſe of children.</item>
                  <item>The .vi. of euil fortune, ſeruauntes, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the pleaſure of ♂</item>
                  <item>The .vii. being oppoſite to the firſte, is the houſe of mariage and open enemies</item>
                  <item>The .viii. is the houſe of death.</item>
                  <item>The .ix. of religion or long iourneys, the delite of the Sunne.</item>
                  <item>The .x. being the middle of the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is the houſe of rule or gouernance.</item>
                  <item>The .xi. is the houſe of Fortune, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:89"/>
                  <item>The .xii. is the houſe of priſons, euil for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, the pleaſure of <hi>Saturne.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ <hi>Of the principall Angles or houſes of the heauen or firmament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AMongeſt theſe .xii. there be certaine which are called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principall angles or coruers of the firmament, whiche are the firſt, the tenth, the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th, the fourth. The firſte is the angle of the Eaſte, the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> of the birth, and the houſe of <hi>Aries.</hi> The ſeconde is the midſt of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and the houſe of <hi>Capricorne.</hi> The thirde is the angle of the weſt, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth to <hi>Libra.</hi> The fourth of <hi>Firmic<hi rend="sup">9</hi>
                  </hi> is called the bottome of the firmament. And in theſe foure almoſte the whole iudgement dothe depende and conſiſte. For they are the principall angles and houſes, &amp; the planets haue more power and ſtrength in them then in any of the other.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:89"/>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Medium celi.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Oriens.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Occidens.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Imum celi.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <p>I Iudge it but ſuperſticious vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to intreate much of the beginning of the natiuitic, becauſe it dothe rather pertain to artificial <hi>Aſtrology:</hi> as of the fall of the ſede into the wombe, and the aſcendente of the houre of the natiuitye, whiche (as I ſaid) perteyneth to an other kinde of ſpeculation. Our intention at thys preſente is fullye derected to the <hi>Sunne,</hi> and the ſigne wherein the <hi>Sunne</hi> is the daye of natiuitie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:90"/>
               <p>For as <hi>Ptolomye</hi> is witneſſe, there are as great effectes and vertues in the <hi>Sunne</hi> as in al the other Planets. And thoſe thinges which nature &amp; long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath taught vs: we will make eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vnto you, letting paſſe all ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious thinges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the effectes of the Planets.</head>
               <p>FIrſt of all it is conuenient to declare the natures and effectes of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets in euery houſe, the which although we haue ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly handled in our boke intituled <hi>Octocedro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> yet I am nothing a haſhed to deſcribe it here the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d time.</p>
               <p>If any man be borne betwene the .x. or .xi. daye of Marche, (when the ſunne commonlye dothe enter into <hi>Aries</hi>) and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth there through thre decanes or faces, vnto the .x. or .xi. daye of Aprill, <hi>Mars</hi> is founde larde in the day of nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie: who beinge by nature fierye, and <hi>Aries</hi> likewiſe, dooeth augmente and increaſe his heat and furye, and al other cull diſpoſitions, more then if he had ben in an earthly or watery ſigne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturnus</hi> whereſoeuer he be, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallye
<pb facs="tcp:7828:90"/>in the .vi .viii. or .xii. houſe, is the auctoure of all miſeries, calamities, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, and ſickeneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> being temperate, cauſeth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be a louer of women, of playes, ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and bankettes, and all thinges per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining vnto mirth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> is the miniſter and geuer of wiſdome and eloquence, lawes, retho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, ſubtile workes, merchaundiſe, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Mone</hi> cauſeth madneſſe, vnſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtnes, moiſtneſſe, and ſtouth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter</hi> in the angles is the auctor of beauty, richeſſe, honor, and rule.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sunne</hi> in the aſcendente, or in the angles maketh a greate and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſonage, and had in reputation amongſt princes and greate men.</p>
               <p>The ſignes alſo cauſinge beautye, are <hi>Gemini, Libra, Virgo,</hi> and the firſte part of <hi>Sagittarius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Workers of meane beauty, <hi>Scorpio, Capricorne</hi> and <hi>Piſces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Barren ſignes, are <hi>Gemini, Leo, virgo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Cauſinge defection or lacke of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="tcp:7828:91" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Aries, Taurus, Libra, Sagittarius, Capricorne,</hi> and <hi>Aquarius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Meane and without voice, <hi>Cancer, Scorpio, piſces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Miniſtring reaſon, <hi>Virgo, Libra, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarius, Gemini.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The qualities of the ſignes I iudge are wel inoughe knoweit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aries, Leo,</hi> and <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> are hotte and drye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taurus, Virgo, Capricorne,</hi> melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, colde, and drye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cancer, Scorpio,</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> are colde, moyſt, and waterye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gemini, Libra, Aquarius,</hi> are hotte, moiſt, and ayrye.</p>
               <p>And thus always thre ſignes agreing in one nature, do make a triplicitie. And euerye Planette likewiſe haue certaine powers and effectes in their priuate or proper houſes, as for example.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aries</hi> and <hi>Scorpius,</hi> are the houſes of <hi>Mars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taurus</hi> and <hi>Libra,</hi> of <hi>Venus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gemini</hi> and <hi>Virgo,</hi> of <hi>Mercury.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:91" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sagittarius</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> are the houſes of <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Capricorne</hi> and <hi>Aquarius,</hi> are attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to <hi>Saturne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Sunne</hi> hathe onlye one houſe, which is <hi>Leo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Mone</hi> poſſeſſeth alſo <hi>Cancer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Euerye ſigne hath likewiſe his proper ſignification in the creation of the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of mans bodye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aries</hi> hathe of the bodye of man, the head and the face.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taurus</hi> the necke, and the throte bole.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gemini,</hi> the ſhoulders, armes, and handes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cancer</hi> the breſt, the heart, ſtomack &amp; ribbes, ſplene, and longes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the nether parte of the ſtomacke, backe, and ſides.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Virgo</hi> the belly or midriffe, <hi>Diaphrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> and bowels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Libra</hi> the loynes, the nether parte of the belly and nauel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scorpio</hi> the priuye members, ſtones, blather, and thighes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:92"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sagittarius</hi> the buttocks with the apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances. And <hi>Capricorne</hi> the knees. <hi>Aquarius</hi> the legges, <hi>Piſces</hi> the feete and ſoules.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>Certaine vvorthy notes concerning the ſunne and Moone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>LEaſte that any ſhoulde herein be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, we thinke it not mete to be let paſſe, concerning the <hi>ſunne</hi> and <hi>Mone,</hi> the which al be it they be the chiefe and princes of the Planettes: yet are they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Lordes of the natiuity, as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Mone</hi> be in <hi>Gemini,</hi> or in <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> whiche is her owne houſe, when a childe is borne: yet ſhall not the <hi>Moone</hi> haue the dominion of the birthe, but it ſhalbe imputed to the Lord of the houſe folowing. So likewiſe, if a man be born the <hi>Sunne</hi> being in <hi>Leo,</hi> which is his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per houſe: yet he loſeth the dominion of the natiuity, and it is deriued vnto <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> being patrone of the next manſion <hi>Virgo.</hi> Againe, the <hi>Mone</hi> being in <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, Venus</hi> is Ladye of the birthe, becauſe of <hi>Libra</hi> folowing which is the houſe of <hi>Venus.</hi> Neither is it vnprofitable to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh
<pb facs="tcp:7828:92"/>you alſo of his, which I perceiue euery wher to be doubted of, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euel planets as <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> are not ſo hurtful &amp; pernicious in their own proper houſes, as thei be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of others. I wil propound an example of the firſte ſigne, wherby it may appeare more eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. We wil ſet the <hi>Sunne</hi> to be in the time of ſome natiuitye in <hi>Aries,</hi> whoſe nature you al ready know, and what ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect he worketh being in the <hi>Horoſcope.</hi> Then in therection of the figure, ioyne <hi>Mars</hi> with <hi>Aries</hi> beinge Lorde of the houſe: and therby iudge that he whiche is born ſhal liue long. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, <hi>Mars</hi> who although he be nought, &amp; ill, yet he doth not ſo much pour out &amp; ſhew his malice being in his own houſe; as if he were in another houſe, ſacring that in ſtede of hurt by the ſword, he threatneth ſode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne ſickeneſſe, becauſe <hi>Mars</hi> being in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> the .viii. houſe, neyther ſhall thoſe ſickeneſſe bring death. And this is for an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. The like is alſo to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of <hi>Saturn,</hi> being in <hi>Capricorn</hi> or in <hi>Aquarius.</hi> And left we may ſeine here
<pb facs="tcp:7828:93"/>vtterly to neglect artificial <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which we do not denye, but to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, to the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of the natural. Wherefore, we mindinge to declare the force &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of the ſignes, we wil firſt do it by artificial <hi>Aſtrology:</hi> ſo that anye ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lacking <hi>Firmicus</hi> and his tables, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a plaine <hi>Aſtrolobe,</hi> and beholding thaſcendent at thoure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> natiuity: may by theſe ſmal inſtructions geue iudgmet. And after this in order, in another phraſe I wil do the ſame by natural <hi>Aſtrology</hi> the which ſhal helpe the artificial.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the firſt houſe and horoſcope in Aries</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IF any man wil peraduenture demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what operation &amp; effect the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> in <hi>Aries</hi> doth worke in vs. Firſt of all I admoniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the ſtars or ſignes do not ꝓuoke or force vs to any thing, but onlye doth make vs prone &amp; apt:<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being ſo apt, they do moue ſtir vs vp vnto the things we are ſo prone vnto. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe motion we are fre and oute of daunger, that folowing the rule and gouerna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they ſhal haue no effect in vs. But if co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traciwiſe, we onli folow our natural
<pb facs="tcp:7828:93"/>ſtinction they ſhal worke the ſame effect in vs, that they do in a manner in brute beaſtes. Wherfore, this <hi>Horoſcope</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them which are borne, floriſhing in youth, withoute brethren, or one at the moſt, if they be fortunate: hauing a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table inheritance, now gotten, now loſt, and now loſt, and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ait recouered again, inclined to the diſeaſes of the hed, rather then to ani other ſickneſſe (becauſe <hi>Aries</hi> hath chief reſpect to the hed). For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part beſtowing his labor &amp; good wil vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnthankful perſons, &amp; ſpecially <hi>Aries</hi> being in the <hi>Horoſcope.</hi> Nexte after the <hi>Horoſcope,</hi> muſt hede be taken vnto the chiefe angles, &amp; what ſigne is in eche an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, which may eaſily be rekened, by the fingers or els bi a figure erect, as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. <hi>Aries</hi> being in the firſt houſe, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> poſſeſſeth the nether part of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <hi>Capricorne</hi> the midſt, and <hi>Libra</hi> the weſt, and now we wil ſhew, what theſe principal angles do promiſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Capricorne</hi> in the midſt of the heauen, doth diſcern honors, riches, promotions, ſecretes of religion, and a ſuttel wit.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:94"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>Libra</hi> in the weſt ſheweth the life and courtly maners, the which life few do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: for it is vnconſtant, caſting down a man from honor and reputation, into in famy and reproche: fortune nowe flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and laughing vpon him, and bi and by vering him with ſondry miſeries and calamities, ſo that he ſhal haue no como<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dity or gaine, withoute incomoditye and loſſe. Al this ſhal happen throughe emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſpite of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions. But
<pb facs="tcp:7828:94"/>al theſe euils, whatſoeuer thei are <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer</hi> in the nether part of the heauen doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and recompence. We haue ioyned hereunto a figure, by the whiche as in a table you may perceiue all thinges per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ſecond houſe and Horoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope in Taurus.</head>
               <p>NExt after <hi>Aries, Taurus</hi> doth orderly follow, and is placed in the figure to the ſecond houſe: the which, as we ſaide before, is the houſe of ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or riches. If any man therfore wil know whether he ſhalbe rich in the firſt, ſecond, or thirde age: let him iudge accordinge to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes of the triplicities &amp; their places. Whiche we wil do hereafter. Now we will only ſpeake in general.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Horoſcope</hi> or aſcendent, beinge in <hi>Taurus,</hi> thou ſhalt iudge in this ſort: that that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe painfully diſquieted with ſondry cares for getting of richeſſe, which he ſhal eaſely attain vnto, and be as apt to loſe the ſame againe, and ſhall triumph ouer his enemies.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:95"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aquarius</hi> alſo in the middeſt of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maketh him acceptable vnto Princes &amp; great men, and geueth him rule in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like affaires and offices, and peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in buſines perteinynge to waters, becauſe he ſemeth to be moſte geuen to the nature of the water.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scorpius</hi> in the weſt cauſeth a harty &amp; beneficial perſon, the which ſhal loſe his wife, if it be a woman, ſhe ſhal loſe both her huſband, and her ſonne or childe.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> in the nether parte of the heauen
<pb facs="tcp:7828:95"/>cauſeth him to chalenge his patrimonie, the which (notwithſtandynge al the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours &amp; liyng in waite of his kinred) he ſhal obteine and get.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the aſcendent in Gemini.</head>
               <p>VVhoſoeuer hathe this <hi>Horoſcope,</hi> ſhal haue proſperitie &amp; good fortune by his parentes, brethren, frendes, kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke, and great menne.</p>
               <p>According vnto <hi>Firmicus Piſces</hi> being in the middeſt of the heauen, cauſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are ſo borne, to get their liuynge by moiſte and watery thinges, howbeit for a tyme he ſhall not liue of his owne coſtes, but ſhal get the ſtipende or fee of ſome prince or citie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sagittarius</hi> in the weſt doth contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe threaten deſtruction vnto his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and kinred, whereby throughe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers cares and vexations being put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his minde, he ſhal be a longe tyme tormented. After this his enemies wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge fierce, and vyolentlye commynge vpon hym, and the waues of miſchiefes ſtyll increaſynge: he ſhall be compelled to forſake hys owne natyue countrey,
<pb facs="tcp:7828:96"/>and ſhal be baniſhed &amp; driuen awaye as Cain was, vntil at lengthe by the helpe of God, he ſhall be reſtored into his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer eſtate and condition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Virgo</hi> likewiſe in the bottome of the heauen doth threaten the very ſame, but by chaunge and increaſe of time (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the ſtate of the incommodities and hurtes) it doth increaſe abundaunce and good fortune.</p>
               <p>¶ Here you may behold the figure.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:96"/>
               <head>Of the Horoſcope in Cancer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cancer</hi> in the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> doth diſpoſe the natural diſpoſition, and al other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in this ſorte. It maketh a man of a quicke and ſubtile wit, albeit ſomewhat ſlowe, pleaſaunt, quiet, and angry, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly purſuynge all euil perſons, whoſe anger is ſone appeaſed. Alſo ſtrong, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, and graue, by the which gifts he ſhall be promoted vnto publike offices, &amp; haue his liuing by them. Manye ſhal o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him, and ſome by compulſion flatter him but fainedly and not hartely. <hi>Saturn</hi> is alſo hurtful vnto him, if that he be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> or any near aſpect For he dothe forſhew not onely violente death, but alſo continual veration wyth ſickenes, and the death of his brethren.</p>
               <p>Howbeit <hi>Aries</hi> beinge preſent in the midſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauen, doth reſiſt him al that he may, and maketh him alſo acceptable vnto princes and great men, deſirous of good thinges, alſo waſtyng and recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng again his patrimony &amp; inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
               <p>With like clemency <hi>Capricorne</hi> in the occide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhal cauſe him to be ſpotted with
<pb facs="tcp:7828:97"/>infamy, which he ſhal ſhortly after wipe away, and many other miſfortunes, and ſhal reſtore him into his former eſtate. And ſhal alſo encourage him to ſeke out hidden and ſecrete things, but not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great vexation and trauaile.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>Libra</hi> in the bottome bringeth ſorow vpon ſorow, diſperſying the patrimonye, and gettyng it againe, preferryng hym to publike or ciuil offices, whereby great and ſecreate affaires ſhall be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:7828:97"/>vnto hym, which are not accuſtomed to be committed, but onely vnto verye good menne.</p>
               <p>And where as <hi>Saturne</hi> before in the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> doth threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a violent death, <hi>Libra</hi> doth alienate the ſame, promiſing an honeſt death and burial. And if <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> be in the ſigne folowynge, it cauſeth the firſt childe to be a ſonne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Horoſcope in Leo.</head>
               <p>THey alſo which haue <hi>Leo</hi> in the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſcope</hi> for the moſte parte are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with buſineſſe not perteinynge to them ſelues, whereby thei get them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues immortall name and fame, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them ſelues vnto other nacions, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing libertie, neither willynglye ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſubiection: beſtowinge all their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure and trauayle to preſcribe lawes and ordinaunces to other. <hi>Mars</hi> in the artificial figure being oppoſite vnto <hi>Leo</hi> dothe to al effectes denye men children: except <hi>Iupiter</hi> beinge preſent do appeaſe his rigour, who peraduenture wil geue a daughter.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:98"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taurus</hi> in the middeſte of Heauen, cauſeth hym to bee ſuſpecte amongeſt Princes and greate menne, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hym a ruler of publyke offices. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo promoted into dignityes by greate menne, wittye in all thinges, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe fortunate in all thinges but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in mariage, for becauſe he ſhal refuſe the moſte honeſt and beautifull women, and marrye either an olde woman, or a woman of euyll name, or els a wydow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aquarius</hi> beynge in the occidente dooeth geue bothe increaſe and loſſes. <hi>Scorpius</hi> in the nether parte of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, maketh hym a ruler ouer certaine affayres. And they alſo haue <hi>Taurus</hi> in the middeſt of the heauen, whome <hi>Mars</hi> beholdynge wyth a contrarye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte, dooeth threaten bothe impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, and alſo death in a ſtraunge place or contrey.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:98"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ <hi>Of the Horeſcope in Virgo.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Horoſcope</hi> in <hi>Virgo</hi> dothe vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentlye prouoke a manne to lechery and riote, and cauſeth him to bee ſo farre in loue with women, that he wold abuſe all women. It dothe alſo miniſter riches and religion, and maketh him ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ouer aunſwers and oracles, ſo that he ſhal be thought to be of the noumber of the Goddes, wittye and cunnynge in all thynges, ſearchynge out al thinges
<pb facs="tcp:7828:99"/>a good artificer, with aboundance of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe, whether it happen by religion, by learning, or by marchandiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gemini</hi> beinge in the middeſt of the heauen, dothe promiſſe in a manner the ſame effecte: howe be it, noc ſo ſone, but doth adde a goodly wit and diſpoſition in ſeking out of ſecrete thinges, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribinge rules and preceptes of liuinge vnto others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Piſces</hi> alſo tending towardes the weſt doth not only for ſhow the ſame: but alſo more pleſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ioyful thinges, as beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or comlines, liberality, gentlenes and ſoftneſſe, with fauor &amp; loue amongſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sagittarius</hi> doth adde vnto this the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and giftes of the goddes, as felicity and plenty of all thinges, as of children, eccleſiaſtical rule, and agility and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to do al theſe thinges. And this is the deſteny of him, which hath <hi>Virgo</hi> in his <hi>Horoſcope,</hi> the other thre ſignes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge alſo gathered, as you maye here perceiue.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:99"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Horoſcope in Libra.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LIbra</hi> being aſcendente at the houre of natiuity, cauſeth ſickneſſe, daungers, enemies, &amp; great ſtrifes and debates, how be it, after all thoſe daungers, it decreeth victory and triumphe. Alſo promotions, religion, ſincerity, and integrity of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In nothing ſo vnfortunate as in hauinge of children, for when he hathe gotten certaine children, and beginneth to put all his hole confidence and truſte
<pb facs="tcp:7828:100"/>in them by and by, they ſhall decaye and dye, euen thoſe in whome he had ſet his ful hope and truſt in.</p>
               <p>If any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſire to know what digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties he ſhal haue &amp; in what place, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> may very wel be perceiued by <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer</hi> being aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the mideſt of the heauen. Who promiſeth eccleſiaſtical promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, and to haue his liuing oute of the common treaſure. Hither alſo are to be referred the ſubſtance, nobility, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, which ſhal happen aboundantly in age: how be it he ſhal not be ſo fortunate in children, except <hi>Iupiter</hi> do behold him with ſome foundly aſpecte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aries</hi> being in the accident, ſhal mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter all theſe thinges in watery places, or about the water: ſhal alſo bring him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to great daungers, lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g iourneys, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert places, into pearils by his wife: and peraduenture into a frenſye or madneſſe til he draw in age, and then he ſhal haue an end of all theſe miſeries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Capriobrne</hi> ſhall teſſe him hither and thither, and ſeldome ſuffer him to be in quiet, nether wil he ſuffer his patrimony
<pb facs="tcp:7828:100"/>to be in ſuretie, but now vp, now down, now loſſe, now recouered again: becauſe for the moſt parte they be wanton whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che haue <hi>Capricorne</hi> in the nether parte of the heauen. Alſo be ſhall haue a ſonne by an vnlawfull woman.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Horroſcope in Scorpio.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Iudge the nature of the <hi>Horroſcope</hi> in <hi>Scorpio</hi> to be manifeſt, accordynge to the naturall guiding of the thing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king life therin. For it maketh an angry
<pb facs="tcp:7828:101"/>man, priuily pouring out his poiſon, and backbityng with his peſtilent tong, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rich, and toſſed with many perils, and thereby almoſt brought to deſperation: the which being ſomewhat quieted and pacified, he ſhal enioy a quiet fruite and vſe of glorie, dignitie, miniſtration, and religion. It addeth alſo a liuely ſpirite &amp; vigour of minde, with adournament of ſpeache. Further, notwithſtanding his former damages, it geueth increaſe of children, whiche ſhal recompence his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes paſſed.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:101"/>
               <p>For ſo much as it happeneth ſeldom but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thother pricipall angles perform the ſame which the aſcendent doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe: ſo <hi>Leo</hi> poſſeſſyng the midſte of the heuen, doth promiſſe that which is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, adding therunto fortitude &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to perform the ſame withal, geuing alſo dignitie, as an imortal reward of vertue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taurus</hi> in the accident geueth him vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory ouer his enemies, as wel priuy, as apert. Howheit he ſhal be infamed for lechery, the whiche he ſhal alſo wipe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by little and little, now encreaſyng and augmentyng his inheritaunce, and ſhortly diſperſing and ſpoyling it again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aquarius</hi> in the nether angle threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth peryll and daunger by water, and ingratitude of them vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath bene moſt beneficiall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Horoſcope in Sagittarius.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Horoſcope</hi> in <hi>Sagittarie</hi> is recke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned amongſt them which wrappeth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in manifold dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers &amp; perils beinge aſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for it doth allure them whiche are borne vnder it to trauayle longe iourneys, &amp; to commit them ſelues to the
<pb facs="tcp:7828:102"/>ſeas and great waters. It miniſtreth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo naturally a prompt and ready wit to all good learnyng and diſcipline, ſo that they folow nature.</p>
               <p>Wherfore, if <hi>Virgo</hi> happen to be in the middeſt of the heauen, it dothe aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his fortune, recompenſyng the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of his minde and wit with ſome notable preferment, bi the which he ſhal excell others: vſing the ſame liberalitye in helpynge others, althoughe they bee vnthankefull.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:102"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gemini</hi> in the weſt geueth children &amp; neuewes by and by in the middle age, and ſhall geue hym rule or office ouer bokes and ſecrete thinges.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Piſces</hi> in the nether part of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ueth helpe out of watery places, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him faithful, to whom ſecrets may be committed, noble, either by bloude or gentlenes: whome, if <hi>Iupiter</hi> do beholde with any meane aſpect, he ſhal marye a wife which hath bene defiled before, or an adulterous woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Horroſcope in Capricorne.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CApricorne</hi> in the <hi>Horroſcope</hi> is not altogither an ill ſigne, for it cauſeth a man to be louyng, mery, faithful, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what crafty, abundant, but faint harted, and very ſuperſticious in prayer. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, libidinous, and the pleaſure beinge once paſte, he wil ſtraite be at defiaunce and miſhandle the women. Alſo of a ſtraunge life or liuing, and a ſecrete ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore or iudge, and ſpeciallye of religion, or ſuch like maiters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Libra</hi> in the midſt of the heauen brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in his gaine by the loſſe and deathe
<pb facs="tcp:7828:103"/>of others, maketh him alſo honeſt, godly, acceptable, eloquent, and learned: and in his neceſſitie wowyng &amp; praiynge vnto God, wherby after all euils and miſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, he ſhall obteine a proſperous and happye age.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Horoſcope in Aquarius.</head>
               <p>THe effect of this <hi>Horoſcope</hi> is ſuche that it maketh them meanely riche, promoted them vnto great men, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth them into manye daungers, out of the which, euen in the midſt of deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſhal be releued by the holy of god. It maketh them alſo kepers of hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, liberal, and prodigal, and a patrone to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſeme to excel in good ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, handlyng &amp; diſpenſing holy matters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scorpius</hi> poſſeſſyng the midſte of the heauen, geueth ſtrengthe, and cauſeth a harde and vile lyfe, neuer permanent or abidyng in one place, hauyng ill fortune by his wiues. But laſt of al, he ſhal be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered out of al theſe euils by the helpe of good men. <hi>Leo</hi> in thoccide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhal cauſe him to be often at varia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with his wife or concubine, he ſhal alſo mary with an olde woman, whyche ſhall flatter hym,
<pb facs="tcp:7828:104"/>promiſyng him great giftes, but in her hart ſhe ſhal loue other better then him. His owne houſhold ſhal be his enemies, by whoſe healpe his other enemies ſhal go aboute to deſtroye him. And he ſhal marie either another mans wyfe, or els a widdow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taurus</hi> in the nether angle, encreſeth his glory and pompe which he is geuen vnto, enrichynge hym alſo with other mennes goodes, and cauſynge hym to liue longe.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:104"/>
               <head>Of the Horoſcope in Piſces.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PIſces</hi> maketh them very witty, bold, harty, faithful, fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, &amp; ſomwhat hie minded, promoting them alſo to honor. <hi>Sagittarius</hi> in the vpper angle, ſhal caſte him headlonge into manye pearils and daugers. Notwithſtanding, maketh him perſonable, and bold to moue debate and ſtrife with great men, and ſhal bring o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens goodes in pearil and danger, and therby poſſeſſe that whiche is none of his owne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Virgo</hi> in the occidente, maketh him hartye, a keper of hoſpitalitye, ſecrete, a ſteward, and one louing his wife immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratly, whom ſhe contrariwiſe ſhal not loue, and al other vnto whome he hathe beneficial, ſhalbe vnthankeful. Wherby he ſhal be often vexed &amp; troubled through his wife and children.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, he ſhall be troubled with ſickeneſſe, by reaſon of <hi>Gemini</hi> in the nether angle. He ſhal alſo haue a diſeaſe whome none ſhal know but him ſelf, he ſhal loſe his ſubſtaunce, and recouer the ſame againe, and alſo be holpen by his
<pb facs="tcp:7828:105"/>fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>des, leſt he might ſeme deſtitute. He ſhal ſurrendre his ſpirit to his maker in a ſtrange land or place, out of his owne country by ſodaine deathe.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ <hi>Hereafter folovveth the natural iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of Aſtrology, according to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolution of the Sunne, throughe the .xii. ſignes of the Zodiacke.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HItherto we haue intreated y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obſcure ſayinges of others, concerninge the iudgementes of the <hi>Horoſcope.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we only promiſed to intreat briefli of thoſe thinges, which others haue ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:7828:105"/>with long comentaries: ſome perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture wold impute theft vnto me, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding other mens doing vnto mine. Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which theft I am nothing aſhamed: for albeit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> theft in al thinges be reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, yet in learning only it is comenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and praiſe worthy, &amp; eſpecially when that a man goeth aboute by the ſame to enucleat and diſcuſſe the darke &amp; obſcure ſayinges of others. This we ſpeake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch as enuy al our doinges, like as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> barbarous people, whiche beinge nether apt, nether prompt to any kinde of good learninge: yet they iudge all thinges in their own tong &amp; la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage vile &amp; nought. Thou, who ſo euer thou art, that readeſt theſe thinges, rather waye and conſider our minde and intent, then our wordes, mindinge to teach and make euident all thinges vnto thee: which if it come other wiſe to paſſe, it is contrary to our minde and purpoſe. Nowe we wil enter vppon the natural iudgementes, wheras briefly concerning <hi>Aries,</hi> it is in this ſort.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:106"/>
               <head>The Sunne in Aries.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Sunne</hi> beinge in <hi>Aries,</hi> maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are born, nether riche, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther very pore. Alſo angry, but ſone plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, ſtudious, eloquent, diuerſe, proude, liyng, and luxurious, promiſing (as they ſay) mountains of gold, and performing nothinge, euel reported of amongſte his kinred, and ſhalbe broughte in daunger by his enemies, whiche ſhalbe men of power. He ſhall be burie by foure foted beaſtes, as being caſt of a horſe, he ſhal receiue great woundes with daunger of death. So much vnfortunate and aduers ſhal al kinde of hauking, hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting, fiſhing and al thinges to be done on horſeback, be, &amp; happen vnto him: in other things he ſhalbe more fortunate and happy, and alſo long liued. Alſo if it be maid which is born, ſhe ſhalbe geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to liyng, angry, faire, curious, deliting in new &amp; ſtrange thinges, enuious and fruteful in childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe firſt childe ſhalbe ſlain: ſhe ſhalbe in many pearils and daungers; whereby ſhe ſhal get a marke or ſkar in the head, or elſſe be naturally marked there, or in
<pb facs="tcp:7828:106" rendition="simple:additions"/>the féete. This we haue noted alſo out of certayne authors, that the children of <hi>Aries,</hi> being borne in the day, ſhalbe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate and of greate reputation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowme amongſte greate men and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: contrariwiſe, they whiche are borne in the nighte, to be infortunate, and of no reputacion.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sunne in Taurus.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:107"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>TAurus</hi> doth make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bold and fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pting hard and waightie affaires &amp; buſineſſe, a victor or conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of his enemies, a great trauailer, &amp; baniſhed from his natiue countrye. Alſo ſeruile, familiar, angrye, but more in youth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for age ſhal take away al inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities and diſpleaſures, &amp; ſhal bringe richeſſe and mariage, by whiche meanes he ſhall be exhilerate and made ioyful &amp; glad. For if he go about to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in youth, he ſhal ſcarſe attain vnto it, how be it age doth not take away ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but increaſeth ſadneſſe, melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, blacke choler, and cauſeth hurt, as bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a dogge, and that about the .xxviii or .xxxv. yeare of his age. Theſe thinges once paſſed, he ſhal floriſh again &amp; liue ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. It maketh alſo the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wanton, painful, obediente, &amp; ful of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: alſo infamed for whoredo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy ſhal vaniſh away by litle and litle, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe cometh to the age of .xxi. yeres, ſhe ſhal haue many huſbands &amp; children, wiſe and witty in helping and counſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling others alſo circumſpect and rich.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:107"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sunne in Gemini.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GEmini</hi> beinge naturallye faire, dothe cauſe alſo a fair childe, merciful, wiſe and wittye, liberall, a boaſter, a runner and ſtrayer about countries, taking ſmal regard to his owne buſines, whereby he ſhall be neither riche, neither oppreſſed with pouerty, but of a meane eſtate. And of ſuche fidelitye and faythfulneſſe, that he ſhall haue the rule of the common treaſure, merye mineded, full of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſubtile, gentle to be ſpoken to, <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:108"/>&amp; by a certain inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acceptable vnto men, as they whiche haue <hi>Venus</hi> in the rote of their natiuiti. Alſo fair of face, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with good learning and ſcience: as <hi>Mathematical</hi> ſciences, the lawes, and <hi>Arithmatick.</hi> This ſinguler gift he hath alſo before others, that being angrye, he can diſſemble and couer his anger. He ſhalbe in great dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger about .xxiii. yeres of age, ether to be bitten of a dog, or hurt by fire, or els by Iron or weapon.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:108"/>
               <head>The Sunne in Cancer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CAncer</hi> being naturally cold &amp; moiſte, doth make groſe the fleſh, and doth al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lure and prouoke to the loue and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of women. Alſo it cauſeth a good wit, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and wiſdome, ful of ſtrife and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate: &amp; for the moſt part geuing victorye ouer al his enemies. Attemptinge many thinges, and ſpecially on the ſea, often in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, and vexed with manye inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, with much pouerty &amp; miſery. And al be it he be the cauſer of gaine, yet ſhal he be neuer a whitte the richer: he ſhall digge for treaſure, and finde that, which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oked not for. But if it be a maid, ſhe ſhalbe fat, beautifull, nimble, angry, and ſone pleaſed, diligente, wiſe, ciuile and ſhamfaſt, witty, diſceitful, and crafty, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng one thinge and doinge another: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies careful and paineful, ordeyned to many dangers, as by water, by fallinge, by childe bearing, and by the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>licke, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing her firſte childe weake and tender, the other ſomewhat ſtronger. And if ſhe happen to commit any faut of infamye, after the age of .xxvi. yeres it ſhalbe clene
<pb facs="tcp:7828:109"/>aboliſhed &amp; put out of minde. After the which age, whether it be man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it promiſeth good ſucceſſe &amp; fortune. It maketh them alſo well heered, modeſt, faithful, painful, greadye of meate and drinke, acquainted with noble men, and fortunate in huſbandrye.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sunne in Leo.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Sunne</hi> in <hi>Leo,</hi> maketh a ſtoute ſtomacke, bolde, arrogant, eloquent
<pb facs="tcp:7828:109"/>and proud: a mocker &amp; ſcorner, vnmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, cruel, harde, and harde to be intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Beſet with manye miſeries and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilles, out of the whiche he beinge eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, ſhall obtaine ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon office: as to be a centurion or a captaine ouer .v.c. lokinge for benefite at the hands of thre noble men, vnfortunate in children, &amp; for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuſteininge muche laboure and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, prone to anger, and putting him ſelfe in manye daungers, enflaminge cholere, promoting to honours and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and bringeth them in daunger of fire, ſword, and violence of beaſts, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſhal dye oute of his owne houſe or place. How be it by the helpe of God, he ſhall eſcape oute of all theſe daungers. Likewiſe, if it be a maid, ſhe ſhalbe bold, haue a great and large breaſte and ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der legges, whiche are tokens of ſtoute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and boldneſſe, anger, ſlaunders and bablinge, albeit that the ſoftneſſe which is in women, dothe ſomwhat remit and aſſwage thexceſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. She ought alſo ſpecially to take hede of hot water &amp; fire, bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which ſhe ſhalbe gretli in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger
<pb facs="tcp:7828:110"/>ſhe ſhal alſo be much inclined to the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or knawinge of the ſtomacke. But after the age of .xx. or .xxi. yeres, ſhe ſhal be fortunate in richeſſe, the whiche ſhe ſhal obtaine by the helpe of greate men, and the vſe of other mennes goodes: alſo in houſekeping, beauty, and loue. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandinge, ſhe ſhall haue but fewe children.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sunne in Virgo.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:110"/>
               <p>SO likewiſe <hi>Virgo</hi> dothe make them fortunate in houſholde affaires, witty, true, ſtout, and ambitious. His wife ſhal die before he know of it, diuerſe thinges alſo ſhalbe taken and ſtoine from him, and he ſhal be reuenged of his enemies. Moreouer, he ſhalbe ſo muche geuen to boaſtinge and bablinge, that he can not hide and keepe cloſe his owne ſecreates, faire of face, well mannered, a louer of women, and deliting to be in the courtes of great men and princes. Moreouer, iuſt wiſe, good, and honourable, a patr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne &amp; defender of his frendes: alſo holy &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, comelye bodied and well frended. A maide of the ſame birthe, ſhalbe wittye, honeſt, and ſhamefaſte, wel willinge, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligente, circumſpecte and angrye, ſhe ſhall marrye aboute the age of ſixtene yeares, and ſhall bringe forthe her firſte begotten of an elogant and goodly form or ſhape. Howbeit, whether thei be men or women, they ſhalbe wrapped in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pearils and daungers.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:111"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sunne in Libra.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Sunne</hi> in <hi>Libra</hi> cauſeth the childe to bee libidinous, buſye, fortunate, and ſpecyallye vppon the waters, or things perteinyng to the water. Alſo by ſwete ſpices and precious ſtones, &amp; ſuche like. It cauſeth likewiſe a comely bodye and nimble, a pleaſant tongue or ſpeche, a good name, ſekinge oute ſecretes, but ſeldome ſtedfaſt in promiſes, althoughe he pretende otherwiſe. He ſhal put him
<pb facs="tcp:7828:111"/>ſelfe in greate daungers and troubles. His firſte wife ſhall not continue wyth him longe, he ſhal alſo haue enheritance of the goodes of deade men, and partely by his owne witte and induſtrye. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall he bee altogether vnfortunate by foure foted beaſts. He ſhal ſuffer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and great things for wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſakes, and ſhal be infamed for vnlawfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paniynge with them. Alſo he ſhall be a good interpreter of dreames, whether his birthe be by daie or night. The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhall bee frendelie, merie, and io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunde, ſettinge her whole delite on the fieldes and hearbes, wanderinge into ſtraunge places. Aboute the age of .xxiii. ſhee ſhal marie, whiche maxiage ſhal be fortunate: whoſe beautie, pleaſant ſpeche or tongue, and comelie behauiour, ſhall greately preferre and promote her. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are the children of <hi>Libra</hi> altogether vnapt to letters or good learnynge. But let them take heede of ſcaldinge water and of fire, for they ſhall receiue hurt by them, without great regard he had.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:112"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sunne in Scorpio.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SCorpio</hi> dothe augmente the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and addeth boldnes and ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, alſo flatterie, by the which he ſhall diſceiue manye, ſhewynge (as they ſay) breade in the one hande, and hidynge a Stone in the other: minglynge poyſon with honye, perfourmynge almoſte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge that he promiſeth. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, merye, and ieſtynge, yght of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, and a Conquerour of his enemies.
<pb facs="tcp:7828:112"/>It cauſeth alſo the women to be frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, wyſe, and craftye, whiche ſhall be diſceyued of her firſte hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bande: her o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther huſbande ſhee ſhal ioyfully vſe, &amp; ouercome her enemies. Shee ſhall alſo haue the paine of the ſplene, &amp; bee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked either in the heade, or ſhoulders, or brawne of the arme. It maketh bothe kyndes bolde and raſſhe to robbe and ſteale, and to ſearche oute forbidden thinges, and to make contractes or bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaines. Alſo it maketh them wanton, fornicatours, vnſtable, and full of euyll thoughtes and imaginations, babblyng and angrye, and ſometyme very ſadde and afflicte. Howbeit, there ſhall bee Princes and greate menne whiche ſhall eſteme and ſette muche by ſuche ſorte of menne, and alſo of the common people whiche ſhall flatter them, whereby they ſhalbe hadde in reputation and honour.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:113"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sunne in Sagittarius.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAgittarius</hi> is not altogether euil, for the <hi>Sunne</hi> dwellyng in it dothe geue fortune, &amp; miniſtreth a courage to take anie thinge in hande, whatſoeuer thou purpoſeſt: and ſpecially to trauel ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge countreys, and to paſſe the ſeas, and not to returne without great gaine. He ſhal alſo get frendes to come into the houſes and courtes of princes, (not to gather vp the trenchers, or licke the diſſhes as the
<pb facs="tcp:7828:113"/>common and viler ſorte of courtiers do: but to be put in ſome office, as to be ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or ſuche like, to the which promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his agility and ſtrength ſhal great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prefer him. Moreouer, he ſhalbe alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether geuen to ridinge, haukinge, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge, daunſinge, and leapinge, playes and games, combates and conflictes, for the whiche he ſhall haue many enemies whiche ſhal enuy him and impugn him greuouſly, whome he ſhal not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge vanquiſhe and ouercome. He ſhall alſo poſſeſſe his fathers inheritance, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che hapneth not vnto al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it maketh them iuſte, wittye, ſtil, harty, ingenious, faithful, gentle, firme and ſtable, paineful and boaſtinge. The woman alſo ſhal not much differ: for ſhe ſhalbe full of anxietie, painful, merciful, and muche enuied and lien in waite for by euel men: but ſhe ſhal ouercome them and be fertile in childe bearing. She ſhal mary about the age of .xvii. yeares, but if that mariage procede not, ſhe ſhall not mary vntil the age of .xxiiii. yeares.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:114"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sunne in Capricorne.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CApricorne</hi> maketh the childe angrye and light, accompaniynge him ſelfe with vyle and ſuſpicious perſons. Alſo painefull, and diſtracte and vexed wyth diuerſe variaunces, the whiche aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities he ſhall boldely and ſtoutlye beare out and ſuſtaine. He ſhall be readye to dye for the loue of ſome pore aud ſimple
<pb facs="tcp:7828:114"/>maide, the which at length ſhal caſt hym into ſome diſeaſe and ſickenes.</p>
               <p>It maketh them alſo meanelye riche, beneuolente, chearefull, and merye: but vnſtedfaſte, if the natiuitye be by night. In his age, when hee ſeeth his rycheſſe increaſe, he will beginne to loue mony, and decline from his former liberality, vnto couetouſneſſe, for in youth he was eaſye to be handeled. He ſhal proſpere in nauigations, and ſpeciallye towarde the Eaſt, for hys fortune ſhal come out of the Eaſte from greate menne. The <hi>Phiſiognomye</hi> of theſe children for the moſte parte is ſuche: a little heade, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe eyes, and a meane voyce. Bathes be profitable vnto hym beynge ſicke. The women are tymerous, and verye ſhamefaſt, and ſhal haue dominion and vyctorye ouer their ennemyes, and ſhall ſtraye farre abroade.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:115"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sunne in Aquarius.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AQuarius</hi> maketh the childe frendlye, but couetous, &amp; apte to quotidian a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, vnfortunate about waters, which naturally he ſhal abhorre. His good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune ſhal begin to increaſe about thage of .xv. or .xvi. yeares, at the whiche time he ſhall beginne to wander and ſtraye throughe diuers places, and waxe ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what riche, whiche richeſſe ſhall neuer
<pb facs="tcp:7828:115"/>come to aboundaunce, but ſhalbe diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againe vntil his latter yeares, which ſhall make amendes for that which hath bene ouer liberally ſpent afore. Neither ſhall his long iourneis turne him to any greate lucre or gaine, but he ſhal loke for, and obtaine greater profite at the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of others. Further, he ſhalbe vexed with ſondry incommodities, loſſes, and pearils, and ſpecially with his wife, and other women: for ſhe ſhal fal into a pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey, neyther ſhal he haue the fruition of her any long time, nether ſhal he proſper with other women, but ſhe beinge once deade, al thinges ſhall come more fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to paſſe.</p>
               <p>The maide borne in <hi>Aquarius</hi> ſhalbe proper and fine, true, and conſtant, and in theſe three pointes, ſhe ſhall excell the man. She ſhal alſo be enriched by other mens goodes, and let her take heede of her childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for ſhe ſhalbe vexed with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, and attempte ſtraunge places, ſhe ſhalbe but of a mene eſtate vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to thage of .xxii. yeares, and then fortune
<pb facs="tcp:7828:116"/>ſhall begin ſomewhat to fauour her: and ſhe ſhal optaine meane richeſſe. Often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times bothe the men and wemen be ſoft of ſpeche, wiſe, ingenious, faithfull, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, and continually angry with theyr enemies.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sunne in Piſces.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PIſces</hi> in youthe, dothe vere his children with many euils, and oftentimes with out deſerte: and maketh them couetous, merye, diligente, players, neglecting for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,
<pb facs="tcp:7828:116"/>of a good diſpoſition, louing the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye of good men. Alſo of a quicke and readye tonge, bolde, ſtandinge muche in their owne conceite, and fortunate in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge oute treaſures: for this is only ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto them, that they ſhal finde ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vnloked for. Thei ſhal alſo be part<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly enriched by other mens goodes. Thei ſhal not liue lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, except they paſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age of. <hi>35.</hi> yeres, then ther is hope of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g life: yet ſhal they neuer be very riche, al be it in their own opinion, they thinke to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the richeſſe of <hi>Creſus.</hi> Full of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous thoughtes, and ſhalbe brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to captiuitye throughe women, and few thinges ſhal proſper with them in their childehode or youthe. They ſhalbe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the elbowe or fote, and their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune is towardes the Southe. The mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den children ſhall be hote, bolde, of inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lente tonges, contumelious, and full of braulinge and ſcoldinge, beſet with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye pearilles, (and puttinge all honeſtye aparte) ſhe ſhall forſake her huſbande: and if ſhe be not let, ſhe will marye her ſelf vnto an aduoutrer. Alſo they ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:7828:117"/>muche vexed with the tormentes of the belly and ſtomacke. And thus you haue the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d time the influe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the ſignes ſufficiently ſpoken and intreated of.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The nature of the houſes.</head>
               <p>NOwe there dothe remaine to ſpeake of the natures of the houſes &amp; ſignes howe and in what thinges they fauoure or helpe our doinges, and what is to be
<pb facs="tcp:7828:117"/>done in euerie ſigne: whereby we may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo ordre all our accions and doinges, that all thinges maie come proſperouſlie and happelie to paſſe. For this is the onelye ſcope of <hi>Naturall Aſtrology,</hi> to the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che if we do not attaine, I know not (as <hi>Alchabitius</hi> ſaith) to what ende it can o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be profitable vnto vs.</p>
               <p>THe firſt houſe is geuen vnto <hi>Aries,</hi> who alſo is the firſt ſigne in order, and is called of the <hi>Aſtronomers</hi> the houſe of life, and ſignifieth the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of all workes: and that whiche in the beginning of the life ſhall either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite the childe, or els vexe him and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him, alſo his ſtrength and weaknes: and finally, al things that pertain to the natural life.</p>
               <p>The ſecond houſe is of <hi>Taurus,</hi> and is the houſe of ſubſtaunce, liuinge, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, and ſeruauntes, and betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ende of youthe. In the which<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> houſe if <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> happen to bee: they will chiefelye encreaſe thoſe goodes which amongeſt the lawers are
<pb facs="tcp:7828:118"/>called mouables, and alſo vnmouables, as gardens, fieldes, vineyardes and yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rentes, and what ſo euer dothe endure longe. Alſo if any man do hier any bond ſeruaunte vnder this ſigne, he ſhall be faithfull in all thinges he ſhalbe put in truſte withal.</p>
               <p>The thirde houſe whiche ſignifieth ſucceſſe by brethren, ſiſters, kinred, and ſmal iourneis, is attribute vnto <hi>Gemini.</hi> Wherefore if anye manne haue <hi>Aries</hi> in the <hi>Horoſcope,</hi> you may pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto him good fortune by his brethren &amp; kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, by greate men, and his neighbours.</p>
               <p>It is good vnder this ſigne, to write and ſende letters, to take in hande ſhort iourneys, to begin frendſhip or brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode, and ſende letters, to take in hande ſhort or ſuch like.</p>
               <p>The fourthe houſe is called the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of parentes, inheritance, treaſures, and ſecreates. In this houſe it is good to contract, bie and ſell, &amp; to chaunge vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yardes, fieldes, and poſſeſſions, to builde houſes and engines, to lay foundations, to big the earth, &amp; to chuſe thy ſepulchre, for al theſe things <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer</hi> doth proſperate.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:118"/>
               <p>The fifte houſe, is the houſe of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and loue, legacies, and giftes, and of al thoſe thinges whiche after deathe do pertaine either to praiſe or reproche. It is expedient therfore vnder this ſigne to take in hande all thinges that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in minde, to cheariſhe thy ſelfe, to banket and make good cheare, to ſtraye abroade, to entre in couenauntes and frendſhip, becauſe of <hi>Venus</hi> miniſtringe gladneſſe. It is good alſo to put on newe garmentes, to write Epiſtles, to be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye and playe, and to gette him faithful frendes, whiche maye defend him in his neceſſity and nede.</p>
               <p>The ſixte is the houſe of infirmitie and ſickeneſſe, ſadneſſe, and ſeruaunts, the delite of <hi>Mars,</hi> and is imputed vnto <hi>Virgo.</hi> It is not good herein neither to bie nor ſel, becauſe of vnfaithfulneſſe, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and ſorow: and ſpecially by <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials</hi> and virgines, whome a man ought to eſchue. For it heapeth againſt vs falſe witneſſe, theues, and thoſe whiche ſhal lie in wait for our life, menſlears, &amp; bloud ſheders. Alſo tumultes, ſeditions, and
<pb facs="tcp:7828:119"/>factions, and al theſe ſhall happen by the <hi>Virginiſtes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mercurials,</hi> becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Mars</hi> as is aforſaid doth reioiſe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe things.</p>
               <p>The .vii. is in <hi>Libra,</hi> which folowing by and by after the ſickneſſe, is the houſe of mariage, and of thoſe thinges whiche are handled aboute the middle age, as it were in equal balance. In this it is good to amend and recouer things loſt and in deſperation: and becauſe it is the houſe of perfit enmity, it is good to haue to do with thine enemies, to begin warres &amp; debates, and ſpeciallye for them whiche haue <hi>Aries</hi> in thaſcendent.</p>
               <p>The .viii. manſion is attribute vnto <hi>Scorpio,</hi> &amp; is the houſe or portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of death, feare, and inheritance of deade men, and of ſuch thinges as are done after death. Wherfore take heede that in this ſigne thou take in hand nothing, nether entre vpon any iourney or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit thy ſelf vnto waters, becauſe that herein he ſhal eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take hurt. Wherfore al battailes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, vniuſt cauſes, enmities, &amp; euill wemen are to be eſchued, and ſpecially if they riſe by meanes of inheritance.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:119"/>
               <p>The .ix. is in <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> the houſe of faithe, religion, long iourneys, wiſdome, philoſophy, Mathematical ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, bokes, epiſtles, narrations, meſſages, dreames, and rumoures, whiche euerye one haue their proper ſtarre in the firmamente or heauen. Wherefore the <hi>Sunne</hi> or <hi>Mone</hi> beinge in that houſe, it is good to take in hande the thinges aforeſaid, for becauſe they ſhal ſoner take effecte at that time then at anye other, for it is the manſion of perfect frendſhip.</p>
               <p>The .x. houſe is in <hi>Capricorne,</hi> and is called the houſe of kingdome, rule, and office, and what ſo euer pertaineth to power. Wherfore, if thou wilt geue forth any precept or commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or bryng any prouince or city in ſubiection, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and get any rich kingdome, or haue to do with any iudge, or take in hand the defence of the poore, or haue conferens with great or noble men: al theſe things may haply &amp; fortunately be done the <hi>Sun</hi> or <hi>Mone</hi> being in this houſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monlye called the houſe of <hi>Capricorne</hi> by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler order, <hi>Aries</hi> being in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt houſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:120"/>
               <p>The .xi. is referred to <hi>Aquarius,</hi> and is the houſe of praiſe, of good Fortune, the delite of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> of ſeruauntes, and helpers in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſion. It is good to ſet vpon thine ennemies, to get frendes, to praiſe them by whom thou lokeſt for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde and gaine: and finally, to take in hande al thinges that wee woulde haue come wel to paſſe.</p>
               <p>The moſte euill and peſtilente houſe in a manner of all is the .xii. houſe, for it is the manſion of enemies, priſons, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, miſeries, enuye, murmurations, and beaſtes, and is the ende of life. In this houſe let no goodneſſe be loked for, but let him take hede of impriſonmente or fetters, the whiche (if he chaunce to come into in this ſigne) he ſhal be hardly deliuered oute. And if that <hi>Saturne</hi> the Lorde of the houſe, or <hi>Mars</hi> bee there: if woorketh deathe, and all kinde of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe. And thus ſucceſſiuelye of al the other ſignes.</p>
               <p>Hitherto we haue ſpoken of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and effectes of the ſignes, in what thinges thei beinge aſcendente, do helpe
<pb facs="tcp:7828:120"/>and furder vs. Nowe wee will call to minde againe ſomewhat whiche was ſpoken before concerninge the Planets, aboute the whiche, (as the matter dothe require) wee will not tarie with longe circumſtaunce accordinge to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, not mindynge to make an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant of a flie: a great matter of a ſmall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Saturne Lorde of the Birthe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAturnus</hi> wherſoeuer he be Lorde of birthe, doth draw the minde of thoſe whiche are borne vnder him, hauing the bridle at libertie: to bee hie minded and ſtubburne, to malice, and to manie miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and calamityes. Howbeit, he ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth faieth and wiſedome to perſwade, and to diſcerne that whiche is iuſte and true in all matters but in his owne, in the whiche he ſhal not be ſo circumſpect. He ſhall truſt muche vnto him ſelfe and to his owne witte, a ſmall eater, but a
<pb facs="tcp:7828:121"/>large drinker, not greatly affectioned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes his wife and children.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, he cauſeth the bodye to be leane, colde, and drie, filling it ful of euil humoures, maketh paleneſſe, bringeth ſickeneſſe ſone, and heapeth all diſeaſes together; as the inflammations of the lunges, with a feruent ague, the dropſy, the gout, the kings euil, botches &amp; biles, fallinge of the heere, and blindeneſſe, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge ſickeneſſe: and finallye, the whole ſeas and floude of noughtye and vicious humours. He dothe alſo cut of and ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the life, either in a moiſte place, or els in a ſtraunge or deſerte place, oute of his natiue countrye. It is alſo very euell if <hi>Mercury</hi> do fal in the houſe of <hi>Saturn,</hi> for he maketh an inchaunter, a coniurer, a Southſayer, a truſe breaker, and an enemy of his parents and brethren, and of al other men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Iupiter Lorde of the <hi>birthe.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:121"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>IVpiter</hi> doth euery wher deſerue praiſe for there is no pointe of counſel, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, knowledge, eloquence, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, whiche he dothe not liberallye mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and geue: ſo that if you will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe anye good manne, you maye wel faine him to be a <hi>Iouial.</hi> And brieflye, if thou wendicate vnto him al vertues and goodneſſe, thou canſte not erre. For the <hi>Iouialles</hi> be fullye repleniſhed wyth all thoſe thinges, ſo much leſſe do they lacke anye thinge. To what ende ſhal I nede to commende and praiſe their magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, with their large honours and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I ſaide before, there is nothinge founde to be wantinge or lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Mars Lord of the Birthe.</head>
               <p>COntrariwiſe, <hi>Mars</hi> beinge naturally euil, dothe make them diſpoſed to all kinde of euell. And as we ſayde, there was nothing in <hi>Iupiter</hi> blame worthy:
<pb facs="tcp:7828:122"/>ſo wee do againe pronounce, that there is none ſo greate a miſchiefe, but that the <hi>Martialiſtes</hi> dare boldly take in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: nor none ſo foule a crime, wherewyth they are not contaminate and defiled. It is counted an heynous thinge amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt them to be honeſt and good. And it is counted a greate vertue to robbe and ſteale, to kill, to burne, to lye, to diſceaue, and delude. And to be ſhorte, it is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vnto them to commit all vnlawful thinges. And if there be any thing more miſcheuous then other, they thinke it lawfull for them to do it without ſhame or puniſhment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Venus ladie of the birthe.</head>
               <p>THe properties of <hi>Venus</hi> are ſo well knowen that I ſhal not nede to ſtand about it with greate circumſtances: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I ſee why ſhe ſhould not be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with <hi>Iupiter.</hi> For vnto al the effects and workes, to al the vertues and ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and finallye, to all the good thinges that <hi>Iupiter</hi> doth geue: ſhe addeth ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doure
<pb facs="tcp:7828:122"/>and renowme, and alſo riote, and ſpecially if <hi>Iupiter</hi> be in any frendlye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte with her: or that <hi>Mercurye</hi> be in coniunction with <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> her ſignification is well knowen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Mercuri lord of the birth</head>
               <p>VNto ſome <hi>Mercury</hi> ſemeth doubtful good with the good, &amp; euill with the euil. Howbeit alone he is verye good in geuinge the dowries of the witte or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, in the which he doth excel <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Venus.</hi> As for the ſortes &amp; kinds of ſciences and learning, they are ſo wel knowen, that we ſhal not nede to repete them here againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Sunne vvith the lord of the birth.</head>
               <p>AL y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is aforeſaid of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nets, we wold alſo haue it vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the <hi>Sunne.</hi> For he is aſſured of a good planet which hath him, I mean not lord of y<hi rend="sup">c</hi> birth: for that he is neuer. Likewiſe as the <hi>Moone</hi> being with the lord of the birthe ſemeth to me to bee (as it were) meane betwene <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:7828:123"/>therfore kepeth as it were a mean in the natural gifts. But if ſhe happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come in coniunction with <hi>Iupiter, Venus,</hi> and <hi>Mercurye:</hi> who wil not iudge that man moſt happye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Mone vvith the lord of the birth.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Mone</hi> onely for this cauſe is euyl reported, bicauſe it doth brede inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie and vnſtedfaſtnes, the which in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bringeth alſo al kind of miſchiefe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Canons or rules for the <hi>erexion of the figure of the heauen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE ſame order of the ſignes is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued herein that is in the artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, for what ſigne is aſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, euery pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net accordynge to the order, is to be put into euerie houſe. As if <hi>Aries</hi> be the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendente of the birthe: place <hi>Aries</hi> in the firſte houſe, <hi>Taurus</hi> in the ſeconde, <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> in the thirde, and <hi>Cancer</hi> in the
<pb facs="tcp:7828:123"/>fourth. If the <hi>Sunne</hi> be in <hi>Cancer,</hi> ſhort ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> place <hi>Cancer</hi> in the firſt houſe, <hi>Leo</hi> in the ſeconde, <hi>Virgo</hi> in the thirde, <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra</hi> in the fourth, <hi>Scorpio</hi> in the fift, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gittarius</hi> in the ſixte, <hi>Capricorne</hi> in the ſeuenthe, whiche is oppoſite to <hi>Cancer,</hi> and the other in their order as you well knowe.</p>
               <p>But the Lordſhippe and gouernours of the ſignes is cleane prepoſterous and contrarye to that whiche is alledged of <hi>Firmicus:</hi> for here onelye reſpecte is had to the Lorde of the aſcendente, and after him the other Planettes in eche houſe are to bee placed accordynge to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall order.</p>
               <p>And in this onlye it agreeth with the artificial, that the Lord of the aſcendent is placed with the aſcendent of the other planets, there is no order but onlye the natural order. As for example, I deſire to erect a figure of natiuity, the <hi>Sun</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Aries,</hi> I knowe the order of the houſes. I will ſette in the firſte houſe <hi>Aries,</hi> in the ſeconde <hi>Taurus,</hi> in the eyght <hi>Scorpio,</hi> in the nynthe <hi>Sagittarius,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7828:124"/>in the .x. <hi>Capricorne,</hi> in the .xi. <hi>Aquarius,</hi> in the .xii. <hi>Piſces.</hi> And the ſignes beinge thus ſette, is almooſte the whole order of them whiche iudge by the <hi>Horoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope.</hi> Nowe foloweth the order of the Planettes. Firſte of al I appointe to the Lordſhip of <hi>Aries, Mars:</hi> for he is Lorde of the ſign, to the ſecond houſe I aſcribe the <hi>Sunne,</hi> to the thirde <hi>Venus,</hi> to the fourthe <hi>Mercurye,</hi> to the fifte the <hi>Mone,</hi> to the ſixthe <hi>Saturne,</hi> to the ſeuenthe <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> to the eighte <hi>Mars,</hi> to the ninthe the <hi>Sunne,</hi> to the tenthe <hi>Venus,</hi> to the leuenth <hi>Mercury,</hi> to the .xii. the <hi>Mone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſee the Lorde of the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente onlye, excepte al other planets, to be placed according to their natural or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. I wold not that any man ſhuld vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand me herein, that when I ſpeake of the aſcendente, that I meane the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendente of the houre or <hi>Horoſcope:</hi> but of the ſigne in the whiche the <hi>Sunne</hi> is at that time.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, in the ſeconde reuolution, thou ſhal ſet <hi>Saturne</hi> in the firſte houſe, and ſhalbe the Lorde of life at the age of
<pb facs="tcp:7828:124"/>xiii. yeares. In the ſeconde houſe <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and accordynge to his nature iudge the ſubſtaunce of the childe. To the thirde houſe adde <hi>Mars,</hi> and by him iudge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerninge brethren and kinred, and ſhort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ournets. To the fourth houſe, the <hi>ſunne,</hi> and accordinge to his Nature, haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the parentes and inheritance at xvi. yeres of age. And by this example you maie raiſe to anye man a like reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and perceiue thereby what ſhall happen yerelye. For this houſe doth not ſignifie that ſhorte reuolution wherein the <hi>Sunne</hi> is euery two hours: but a yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye reuolution. Wherfore we haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a reuolution, ſtretching to. <hi>84.</hi> yeres, accordyng to the aſcendent in <hi>Aries:</hi> but if that any other ſigne be aſcendent, you muſt fourme an other reuolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to this tipe or rule. If thou wilt iudge of children, loke to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fift houſe. For ſicknes, ſmal beaſtes, or ſeruants: behold the ſixte houſe. For mariages and open enemies, the ſeuenth houſe. For deathe and inheritance by deade men, and ſuch kinds of thinges: geue iudgement by the
<pb facs="tcp:7828:125"/>eight houſe, and ſo likewiſe of all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther houſes. Neither do I vnderſtande and perceiue what ether ought or can be furder ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſaid herein. The ſumme of this art is to know the natures of the ſignes &amp; planets, &amp; then to erect a figure, &amp; to exerciſe that which you haue reade. Proue it who will, and he ſhal ſee it not onely to agree with the artificial: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for to excel it, as wel for the eaſineſſe, as alſo for the certainetie of the ſame. Thou ſeeſt (as we ſaid before in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, &amp; now againe without ſhame) that there is nothing ſo much to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de of, as a few things which are taken out of the artificial. Neither is it vnknowen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Liechtenbergius</hi> the beſt learned of his time in naturall Mathematical ſciences, by this onely Arte to haue made all the aſtronomers aſtonied, &amp; to haue wrought ſtraungs thinges. Wherfore it ſhoulde feme very euill, if that we ſhoulde ſuffer the learnyng and cunning of ſuch a man to be obſcured &amp; kept cloſe, for theſe oure doinges wee haue drawen out of him. Wherfore we are the leſſe to be blamed
<pb facs="tcp:7828:125"/>if that we haue not ſatiſfied eueri mans mind: except you wil count it faut wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye, that we haue expounded and ſette oute other mens good workes, vnto the poſteritye, and preferre them before our owne. The whiche thinge if it be culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, who is then withoute ſhame or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche, euen they whiche are counted beſt learned in this time and ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We haue added hereunto a figure of the reuolution: he that will knowe thother reuolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, let him read the tables folowinge.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:126"/>
               <p>A Figure of the reuolution of the Signes and Planettes accordynge to <hi>Naturall Aſtrologye,</hi> whoſe aſcendente is ♈, and the Lorde of the ſame ♂.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>A continuation or prolongyng of the figure aforeſaide, from the firſt yeare of the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> in ♈, vnto the ende of <hi>.84.</hi> yeres.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7828:126"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1 ♈ ♂</cell>
                        <cell>13 ♄</cell>
                        <cell>25 ☿</cell>
                        <cell>37 ☉</cell>
                        <cell>49 ♃</cell>
                        <cell>61 <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>73 ♀</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2 ♉ ☉</cell>
                        <cell>14 ♃</cell>
                        <cell>26 <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>38 ♀</cell>
                        <cell>50 ♂</cell>
                        <cell>62 ♄</cell>
                        <cell>74 ☿</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3 ♊ ♀</cell>
                        <cell>15 ♂</cell>
                        <cell>27 ♄</cell>
                        <cell>39 ☿</cell>
                        <cell>51 ☉</cell>
                        <cell>63 ♃</cell>
                        <cell>75 <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4 ♋ ☿</cell>
                        <cell>16 ☉</cell>
                        <cell>28 ♃</cell>
                        <cell>40 <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>52 ♀</cell>
                        <cell>64 ♂</cell>
                        <cell>76 ♄</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5 ♌ <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>17 ♀</cell>
                        <cell>29 ♂</cell>
                        <cell>41 ♄</cell>
                        <cell>53 ☿</cell>
                        <cell>65 ☉</cell>
                        <cell>77 ♃</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6 ♍ ♄</cell>
                        <cell>18 ☿</cell>
                        <cell>30 ☉</cell>
                        <cell>42 ♃</cell>
                        <cell>54 <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>66 ♀</cell>
                        <cell>78 ♂</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7 ♎ ♃</cell>
                        <cell>19 <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>31 ♀</cell>
                        <cell>43 ♂</cell>
                        <cell>55 ♄</cell>
                        <cell>67 ☿</cell>
                        <cell>79 ☉</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8 ♐ ♂</cell>
                        <cell>20 ♄</cell>
                        <cell>32 ☿</cell>
                        <cell>44 ☉</cell>
                        <cell>56 ♃</cell>
                        <cell>68 <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>80 ♀</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9 ♑ ☉</cell>
                        <cell>21 ♃</cell>
                        <cell>33 <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>45 ♀</cell>
                        <cell>57 ♂</cell>
                        <cell>69 ♄</cell>
                        <cell>81 ☿</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10  ♀</cell>
                        <cell>22 ♂</cell>
                        <cell>34 ♄</cell>
                        <cell>46 ☿</cell>
                        <cell>58 ☉</cell>
                        <cell>70 ♃</cell>
                        <cell>82 <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11  ☿</cell>
                        <cell>23 ☉</cell>
                        <cell>35 ♃</cell>
                        <cell>47 <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>59 ♀</cell>
                        <cell>71 ♂</cell>
                        <cell>83 ♄</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12  <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>24 ♀</cell>
                        <cell>36 ♂</cell>
                        <cell>48 ♄</cell>
                        <cell>60 ☿</cell>
                        <cell>72 ☉</cell>
                        <cell>84 ♃</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>¶ By this order (gentle Reader) you may multiply your reuolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into an infinite number.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:7828:127"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>Imprinted at London by Ihon Daie, for Richarde Iugge, dvvellinge at</hi> the Northe dore of Poules Churche, at the ſigne of the Bible.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7828:127"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
